<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>nano &#8211; sawberries</title>
	<atom:link href="http://localhost/sawberries/category/nano/feed/?simply_static_page=1692163" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>https://www.sawberries.com</link>
	<description>www.sawberry.com site</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Thu, 16 May 2024 07:55:49 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=6.5.3</generator>

<image>
	<url>https://www.sawberries.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/04/cropped-DALL·E-2024-04-26-12.21.04-A-512x512-favicon-design-that-incorporates-a-playful-twist-on-the-concept-of-a-strawberry-symbolizing-connections-between-people.-The-strawberry-shou-32x32.webp</url>
	<title>nano &#8211; sawberries</title>
	<link>https://www.sawberries.com</link>
	<width>32</width>
	<height>32</height>
</image> 
	<item>
		<title>Scientists develop an affordable sensor for lead contamination</title>
		<link>https://www.sawberries.com/2024/05/16/scientists-develop-affordable-sensor-for-lead-contamination-0514/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[ross]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 16 May 2024 07:55:49 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[DMSE]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Materials science and engineering]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[MIT.nano]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[nano]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Nanoscience and nanotechnology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Photonics]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Public health]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Research]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[School of Engineering]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Water]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.sawberries.com/2024/05/16/scientists-develop-affordable-sensor-for-lead-contamination-0514/</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Engineers at MIT, Nanyang Technological University, and several companies have developed a compact and inexpensive technology for detecting and measuring lead concentrations in water, potentially enabling a significant advance in tackling this persistent global health issue. The World Health Organization estimates that 240 million people worldwide are exposed to drinking water that contains unsafe amounts [&#8230;]]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<div>
<p>Engineers at MIT, Nanyang Technological University, and several companies have developed a compact and inexpensive technology for detecting and measuring lead concentrations in water, potentially enabling a significant advance in tackling this persistent global health issue.</p>
<p>The World Health Organization estimates that 240 million people worldwide are exposed to drinking water that contains unsafe amounts of toxic lead, which can affect brain development in children, cause birth defects, and produce a variety of neurological, cardiac, and other damaging effects. In the United States alone, an estimated 10 million households still get drinking water delivered through lead pipes.</p>
<p>“It’s an unaddressed public health crisis that leads to over 1 million deaths annually,” says Jia Xu Brian Sia, an MIT postdoc and the senior author of the paper describing the new technology.</p>
<p>But testing for lead in water requires expensive, cumbersome equipment and typically requires days to get results. Or, it uses simple test strips that simply reveal a yes-or-no answer about the presence of lead but no information about its concentration. Current EPA regulations require drinking water to contain no more that 15 parts per billion of lead, a concentration so low it is difficult to detect.</p>
<p>The new system, which could be ready for commercial deployment within two or three years, could detect lead concentrations as low as 1 part per billion, with high accuracy, using a simple chip-based detector housed in a handheld device. The technology gives nearly instant quantitative measurements and requires just a droplet of water.</p>
<p>The findings are described in a <a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/s41467-024-47938-6" target="_blank" rel="noopener">paper appearing today</a> in the journal <em>Nature Communications</em>, by Sia, MIT graduate student and lead author Luigi Ranno, Professor Juejun Hu, and 12 others at MIT and other institutions in academia and industry.</p>
<p>The team set out to find a simple detection method based on the use of photonic chips, which use light to perform measurements. The challenging part was finding a way to attach to the photonic chip surface certain ring-shaped molecules known as crown ethers, which can capture specific ions such as lead. After years of effort, they were able to achieve that attachment via a chemical process known as Fischer esterification. “That is one of the essential breakthroughs we have made in this technology,” Sia says.</p>
<p>In testing the new chip, the researchers showed that it can detect lead in water at concentrations as low as one part per billion. At much higher concentrations, which may be relevant for testing environmental contamination such as mine tailings, the accuracy is within 4 percent.</p>
<p>The device works in water with varying levels of acidity, ranging from pH values of 6 to 8, “which covers most environmental samples,” Sia says. They have tested the device with seawater as well as tap water, and verified the accuracy of the measurements.</p>
<p>In order to achieve such levels of accuracy, current testing requires a device called an inductive coupled plasma mass spectrometer. “These setups can be big and expensive,” Sia says. The sample processing can take days and requires experienced technical personnel.</p>
<p>While the new chip system they developed is “the core part of the innovation,” Ranno says, further work will be needed to develop this into an integrated, handheld device for practical use. “For making an actual product, you would need to package it into a usable form factor,” he explains. This would involve having a small chip-based laser coupled to the photonic chip. “It’s a matter of mechanical design, some optical design, some chemistry, and figuring out the supply chain,” he says. While that takes time, he says, the underlying concepts are straightforward.</p>
<p>The system can be adapted to detect other similar contaminants in water, including cadmium, copper, lithium, barium, cesium, and radium, Ranno says. The device could be used with simple cartridges that can be swapped out to detect different elements, each using slightly different crown ethers that can bind to a specific ion.</p>
<p>“There’s this problem that people don’t measure their water enough, especially in the developing countries,” Ranno says. “And that’s because they need to collect the water, prepare the sample, and bring it to these huge instruments that are extremely expensive.” Instead, “having this handheld device, something compact that even untrained personnel can just bring to the source for on-site monitoring, at low costs,” could make regular, ongoing widespread testing feasible.</p>
<p>Hu, who is the John F. Elliott Professor of Materials Science and Engineering, says, “I’m hoping this will be quickly implemented, so we can benefit human society. This is a good example of a technology coming from a lab innovation where it may actually make a very tangible impact on society, which is of course very fulfilling.”</p>
<p>“If this study can be extended to simultaneous detection of multiple metal elements, especially the presently concerning radioactive elements, its potential would be immense,” says Hou Wang, an associate professor of environmental science and engineering at Hunan University in China, who was not associated with this work.</p>
<p>Wang adds, “This research has engineered a sensor capable of instantaneously detecting lead concentration in water. This can be utilized in real-time to monitor the lead pollution concentration in wastewater discharged from industries such as battery manufacturing and lead smelting, facilitating the establishment of industrial wastewater monitoring systems. I think the innovative aspects and developmental potential of this research are quite commendable.”</p>
<p>Wang Qian, a principal research scientist at the Institute of Materials Research in Singapore, who also was not affiliated with this work, says, “The ability for the pervasive, portable, and quantitative detection of lead has proved to be challenging primarily due to cost concerns. This work demonstrates the potential to do so in a highly integrated form factor and is compatible with large-scale, low-cost manufacturing.”</p>
<p>The team included researchers at MIT, at Nanyang Technological University and Temasek Laboratories in Singapore, at the University of Southampton in the U.K., and at companies Fingate Technologies, in Singapore, and Vulcan Photonics, headquartered in Malaysia. The work used facilities at MIT.nano, the Harvard University Center for Nanoscale Systems, NTU’s Center for Micro- and Nano-Electronics, and the Nanyang Nanofabrication Center.</p>
</div>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>John Joannopoulos receives 2024-2025 Killian Award</title>
		<link>https://www.sawberries.com/2024/05/16/john-joannopoulos-receives-killian-award-0515/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[ross]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 16 May 2024 07:55:49 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Awards, honors and fellowships]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Faculty]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Institute for Soldier Nanotechnologies]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[nano]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Nanoscience and nanotechnology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Photonics]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Physics]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[School of Science]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.sawberries.com/2024/05/16/john-joannopoulos-receives-killian-award-0515/</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[John Joannopoulos, an innovator and mentor in the fields of theoretical condensed matter physics and nanophotonics, has been named the recipient of the 2024-2025 James R. Killian Jr. Faculty Achievement Award. Joannopoulos is the Francis Wright Davis Professor of Physics and director of MIT’s Institute for Soldier Nanotechnologies. He has been a member of the [&#8230;]]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<div>
<p>John Joannopoulos, an innovator and mentor in the fields of theoretical condensed matter physics and nanophotonics, has been named the recipient of the 2024-2025 James R. Killian Jr. Faculty Achievement Award.</p>
<p>Joannopoulos is the Francis Wright Davis Professor of Physics and director of MIT’s Institute for Soldier Nanotechnologies. He has been a member of the MIT faculty for 50 years.</p>
<p>“Professor Joannopoulos’s profound and lasting impact on the field of theoretical condensed matter physics finds its roots in his pioneering work in harnessing ab initio physics to elucidate the behavior of materials at the atomic level,” states the award citation, which was announced at today’s faculty meeting by Roger White, chair of the Killian Award Selection Committee and professor of philosophy at MIT. “His seminal research in the development of photonic crystals has revolutionized understanding of light-matter interactions, laying the groundwork for transformative advancements in diverse fields ranging from telecommunications to biomedical engineering.”</p>
<p>The award also honors Joannopoulos’ service as a “legendary mentor to generations of students, inspiring them to achieve excellence in science while at the same time facilitating the practical benefit to society through entrepreneurship.”</p>
<p>The Killian Award was established in 1971 to recognize outstanding professional contributions by MIT faculty members. It is the highest honor that the faculty can give to one of its members.</p>
<p>“I have to tell you, it was a complete and utter surprise,” Joannopoulos told <em>MIT News</em> shortly after he received word of the award. “I didn’t expect it at all, and was extremely flattered, honored, and moved by it, frankly.”</p>
<p>Joannopoulous has spent his entire professional career at MIT. He came to the Institute in 1974, directly after receiving his PhD in physics at the University of California at Berkeley, where he also earned his bachelor’s degree. Starting out as an assistant professor in MIT’s Department of Physics, he quickly set up a research program focused on theoretical condensed matter physics.</p>
<p>Over the first half of his MIT career, Joannopoulos worked to elucidate the fundamental nature of the electronic, vibrational, and optical structure of crystalline and amorphous bulk solids, their surfaces, interfaces, and defects. He and his students developed numerous theoretical methods to enable tractable and accurate calculations of these complex systems.</p>
<p>In the 1990s, his work with microscopic material systems expanded to a new class of materials, called photonic crystals — materials that could be engineered at the micro- and nanoscale to manipulate light in ways that impart surprising and exotic optical qualities to the material as a whole.</p>
<p>“I saw that you could create photonic crystals with defects that can affect the properties of photons, in much the same way that defects in a semiconductor affect the properties of electrons,” Joannopoulos says. “So I started working in this area to try and explore what anomalous light phenomena can we discover using this approach?”</p>
<p>Among his various breakthroughs in the field was the realization of a <a href="https://news.mit.edu/1998/mirror-1209" target="_blank" rel="noopener">“perfect dielectic mirror”</a> — a multilayered optical device that reflects light from all angles as normal metallic mirrors do, and that can also be tuned to reflect and trap light at specific frequencies. He and his colleagues saw potential for the mirror to be made into a hollow fiber that could serve as a highly effective optical conduit, for use in a wide range of applications. To further advance the technology, he and his colleagues launched a startup, which has since developed the technology into a flexible, fiber-optic “surgical scalpel.”</p>
<p>Throughout his career, Joannopoulos has helped to launch numerous startups and photonics-based technologies.</p>
<p>“His ability to bridge the gap between academia and industry has not only advanced scientific knowledge but also led to the creation of dozens of new companies, thousands of jobs, and groundbreaking products that continue to benefit society to this day,” the award citation states.</p>
<p>In 2006, Joannopoulos accepted the position as director of MIT’s Institute for Soldier Nanotechnologies (ISN), a collaboration between MIT researchers, industry partners, and military defense experts, who seek innovations to protect and enhance soldiers’ survivability in the field. In his role as ISN head, Joannopoulos has worked across MIT, making connections and supporting new projects with researchers specializing in fields far from his own.</p>
<p>“I get a chance to explore and learn fascinating new things,” says Joannopoulos, who is currently overseeing projects related to hyperspectral imaging, smart and responsive fabrics, and nanodrug delivery. “I love that aspect of really getting to understand what people in other fields are doing. And they’re doing great work across many, many different fields.”</p>
<p>Throughout his career at MIT, Joannopoulos has been especially inspired and motivated by his students, many of whom have gone on to found companies, lead top academic and research institutions, and make significant contributions to their respective fields, including one student who was awarded the Nobel Prize in Physics in 1998.</p>
<p>“One’s proudest moments are the successes of one’s students, and in that regard, I’ve been extremely lucky to have had truly exceptional students over the years,” Joannopolous says.</p>
<p>His many contributions to academia and industry have earned Joannopoulos numerous honors and awards, including his election to both the National Academy of Sciences and the American Academy of Arts and Sciences. He is also a fellow of both the American Physical Society and the American Association for the Advancement of Science.</p>
<p>“The Selection Committee is delighted to have this opportunity to honor Professor John Joannopoulos: a visionary scientist, a beloved mentor, a great believer in the goodness of people, and a leader whose contributions to MIT and the broader scientific community are immeasurable,” the award citation concludes.</p>
</div>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>The power of App Inventor: Democratizing possibilities for mobile applications</title>
		<link>https://www.sawberries.com/2024/05/16/power-of-app-inventor-democratizing-possibilities-mobile-applications-0510/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[ross]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 16 May 2024 07:55:42 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Apps]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Artificial Intelligence]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Education, teaching, academics]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Electrical Engineering & Computer Science (eecs)]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Global]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[History of MIT]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[History of science]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[K-12 education]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Media Lab]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[MIT Schwarzman College of Computing]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Online learning]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Open access]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Open source]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Programming]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[School of Architecture and Planning]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[School of Engineering]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[STEM education]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.sawberries.com/2024/05/16/power-of-app-inventor-democratizing-possibilities-mobile-applications-0510/</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[In June 2007, Apple unveiled the first iPhone. But the company made a strategic decision about iPhone software: its new App Store would be a walled garden. An iPhone user wouldn’t be able to install applications that Apple itself hadn’t vetted, at least not without breaking Apple’s terms of service. That business decision, however, left [&#8230;]]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<div>
<p>In June 2007, Apple unveiled the first iPhone. But the company made a strategic decision about iPhone software: its new App Store would be a walled garden. An iPhone user wouldn’t be able to install applications that Apple itself hadn’t vetted, at least not without breaking Apple’s terms of service.</p>
<p>That business decision, however, left educators out in the cold. They had no way to bring mobile software development — about to become part of everyday life — into the classroom. How could a young student code, futz with, and share apps if they couldn’t get it into the App Store?</p>
<p>MIT professor Hal Abelson was on sabbatical at Google at the time, when the company was deciding how to respond to Apple’s gambit to corner the mobile hardware and software market. Abelson recognized the restrictions Apple was placing on young developers; Google recognized the market need for an open-source alternative operating system — what became Android. Both saw the opportunity that became App Inventor.</p>
<p>“Google started the Android project sort of in reaction to the iPhone,” Abelson says. “And I was there, looking at what we did at MIT with education-focused software like <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Logo_(programming_language)">Logo</a> and <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Scratch_(programming_language)">Scratch</a>, and said ‘what a cool thing it would be if kids could make mobile apps also.’”</p>
<p>Google software engineer Mark Friedman volunteered to work with Abelson on what became “Young Android,” soon renamed Google App Inventor. Like Scratch, App Inventor is a block-based language, allowing programmers to visually snap together pre-made “blocks” of code rather than need to learn specialized programming syntax.</p>
<p>Friedman describes it as novel for the time, particularly for mobile development, to make it as easy as possible to build simple mobile apps. “That meant a web-based app,” he says, “where everything was online and no external tools were required, with a simple programming model, drag-and-drop user interface designing, and blocks-based visual programming.” Thus an app someone programmed in a web interface could be installed on an Android device.</p>
<p>App Inventor scratched an itch. Boosted by the explosion in smartphone adoption and the fact App Inventor is free (and eventually open source), soon more than 70,000 teachers were using it with hundreds of thousands of students, with Google providing the backend infrastructure to keep it going.</p>
<p>“I remember answering a question from my manager at Google who asked how many users I thought we&#8217;d get in the first year,” Friedman says. “I thought it would be about 15,000 — and I remember thinking that might be too optimistic. I was ultimately off by a factor of 10–20.” Friedman was quick to credit more than their choices about the app. “I think that it&#8217;s fair to say that while some of that growth was due to the quality of the tool, I don&#8217;t think you can discount the effect of it being from Google and of the effect of Hal Abelson&#8217;s reputation and network.”</p>
<p>Some early apps took App Inventor in ambitious, unexpected directions, such as “Discardious,” developed by teenage girls in Nigeria. Discardious helped business owners and individuals dispose of waste in communities where disposal was unreliable or too cumbersome.</p>
<p>But even before apps like Discardious came along, the team knew Google’s support wouldn’t be open-ended. No one wanted to cut teachers off from a tool they were thriving with, so around 2010, Google and Abelson agreed to transfer App Inventor to MIT. The transition meant major staff contributions to recreate App Inventor without Google’s proprietary software but MIT needing to work with Google to continue to provide the network resources to keep App Inventor free for the world.</p>
<p>With such a large user base, however, that left Abelson “worried the whole thing was going to collapse” without Google’s direct participation.</p>
<p>Friedman agrees. “I would have to say that I had my fears. App Inventor has a pretty complicated technical implementation, involving multiple programming languages, libraries and frameworks, and by the end of its time at Google we had a team of about 10 people working on it.”</p>
<p>Yet not only did Google provide significant funding to aid the transfer, but, Friedman says of the transfer’s ultimate success, “Hal would be in charge and he had fairly extensive knowledge of the system and, of course, had great passion for the vision and the product.”</p>
<p>MIT enterprise architect Jeffrey Schiller, who built the Institute’s computer network and became its manager in 1984, was another key part in sustaining App Inventor after its transition, helping introduce technical features fundamental to its accessibility and long-term success. He led the integration of the platform into web browsers, the addition of WiFi support rather than needing to connect phones and computers via USB, and the laying of groundwork for technical support of older phones because, as Schiller says, “many of our users cannot rush out and purchase the latest and most expensive devices.”</p>
<p>These collaborations and contributions over time resulted in App Inventor’s greatest resource: its user base. As it grew, and with support from community managers, volunteer know-how grew with it. Now, more than a decade since its launch and four years after its overdue inclusion in the Apple App Store, App Inventor recently crossed several major milestones, the most remarkable being the creation of its 100 millionth project and registration of its 20 millionth user. Young developers continue to make incredible applications, boosted now by the advantages of AI. College students created “<a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=RGiFiBSu4Ho">Brazilian XôDengue</a>” as a way for users to use phone cameras to identify mosquito larvae that may be carrying the dengue virus. High school students recently developed “<a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=dyeZAqOqco8">Calmify</a>,” a journaling app that uses AI for emotion detection. And a mother in Kuwait wanted something to help manage the often-overwhelming experience of new motherhood when returning to work, so she built the chatbot “<a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=4uEQsam7C4k">PAM (Personal Advisor to Mothers)</a>” as a non-judgmental space to talk through the challenges.</p>
<p>App Inventor’s long-term sustainability now rests with the App Inventor Foundation, created in 2022 to grow its resources and further drive its adoption. It is led by executive director Natalie Lao.</p>
<p>In <a href="https://www.appinventorfoundation.org/s/App-Inventor-Foundation-Annual-Impact-Report-2023.pdf">a letter</a> to the App Inventor community, Lao highlighted the foundation’s commitment to equitable access to educational resources, which for App Inventor required a rapid shift toward AI education — but in a way that upholds App Inventor’s core values to be “a free, open-source, easy-to-use platform” for mobile devices. “Our mission is to not only democratize access to technology,” Lao wrote, “but also foster a culture of innovation and digital literacy.”</p>
<p>Within MIT, App Inventor today falls under the umbrella of the MIT RAISE Initiative — Responsible AI for Social Empowerment and Education, run by Dean for Digital Learning Cynthia Breazeal, Professor Eric Klopfer, and Abelson. Together they are able to integrate App Inventor into ever-broader communities, events, and funding streams, leading to opportunities like this summer’s inaugural <a href="https://raise.mit.edu/events/ai-education-summit/">AI and Education Summit</a> on July 24-26. The summit will include awards for winners of a <a href="https://raise.mit.edu/events/global-ai-hackathon/">Global AI Hackathon</a>, whose roughly 180 submissions used App Inventor to create AI tools in two tracks: Climate &amp; Sustainability and Health &amp; Wellness. Tying together another of RAISE’s major projects, participants were encouraged to draw from <a href="https://dayofai.org/">Day of AI</a> curricula, including its newest courses on <a href="https://dayofai.org/new-courses-on-data-science-climate-change/">data science and climate change</a>.</p>
<p>“Over the past year, there&#8217;s been an enormous mushrooming in the possibilities for mobile apps through the integration of AI,” says Abelson. “The opportunity for App Inventor and MIT is to democratize those new possibilities for young people — and for everyone — as an enhanced source of power and creativity.”</p>
</div>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Seizing solar’s bright future</title>
		<link>https://www.sawberries.com/2024/05/07/optigon-seizing-bright-solar-future-0506/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[ross]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 07 May 2024 00:01:15 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Alumni/ae]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Climate change]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Department of Energy (DoE)]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Energy]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Energy efficiency]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Innovation and Entrepreneurship (I&E)]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Manufacturing]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[MIT Energy Initiative]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[MIT.nano]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[nano]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Photovoltaics]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Renewable energy]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Solar]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Startups]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Supply chains]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.sawberries.com/2024/05/07/optigon-seizing-bright-solar-future-0506/</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Consider the dizzying ascent of solar energy in the United States: In the past decade, solar capacity increased nearly 900 percent, with electricity production eight times greater in 2023 than in 2014. The jump from 2022 to 2023 alone was 51 percent, with a record 32 gigawatts (GW) of solar installations coming online. In the [&#8230;]]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<div>
<p>Consider the dizzying ascent of solar energy in the United States: In the past decade, solar capacity increased nearly 900 percent, with electricity production eight times greater in 2023 than in 2014. The jump from 2022 to 2023 alone was 51 percent, with a record 32 gigawatts (GW) of solar installations coming online. In the past four years, more solar has been added to the grid than any other form of generation. Installed solar now tops 179 GW, enough to power nearly 33 million homes. The U.S. Department of Energy (DOE) is so bullish on the sun that its decarbonization plans envision solar satisfying 45 percent of the nation’s electricity demands by 2050.</p>
<p>But the continued rapid expansion of solar requires advances in technology, notably to improve the efficiency and durability of solar photovoltaic (PV) materials and manufacturing. That’s where Optigon, a three-year-old MIT spinout company, comes in.</p>
<p>“Our goal is to build tools for research and industry that can accelerate the energy transition,” says Dane deQuilettes, the company’s co-founder and chief science officer. “The technology we have developed for solar will enable measurements and analysis of materials as they are being made both in lab and on the manufacturing line, dramatically speeding up the optimization of PV.”</p>
<p>With roots in MIT’s vibrant solar research community, Optigon is poised for a 2024 rollout of technology it believes will drastically pick up the pace of solar power and other clean energy projects.</p>
<p><strong>Beyond silicon</strong></p>
<p>Silicon, the material mainstay of most PV, is limited by the laws of physics in the efficiencies it can achieve converting photons from the sun into electrical energy. Silicon-based solar cells can theoretically reach power conversion levels of just 30 percent, and real-world efficiency levels hover in the low 20s. But beyond the physical limitations of silicon, there is another issue at play for many researchers and the solar industry in the United States and elsewhere: China dominates the silicon PV market, from supply chains to manufacturing.</p>
<p>Scientists are eagerly pursuing alternative materials, either for enhancing silicon’s solar conversion capacity or for replacing silicon altogether.</p>
<p>In the past decade, a family of crystal-structured semiconductors known as perovskites has risen to the fore as a next-generation PV material candidate. Perovskite devices lend themselves to a novel manufacturing process using printing technology that could circumvent the supply chain juggernaut China has built for silicon. Perovskite solar cells can be stacked on each other or layered atop silicon PV, to achieve higher conversion efficiencies. Because perovskite technology is flexible and lightweight, modules can be used on roofs and other structures that cannot support heavier silicon PV, lowering costs and enabling a wider range of building-integrated solar devices.</p>
<p>But these new materials require testing, both during R&amp;D and then on assembly lines, where missing or defective optical, electrical, or dimensional properties in the nano-sized crystal structures can negatively impact the end product.</p>
<p>“The actual measurement and data analysis processes have been really, really slow, because you have to use a bunch of separate tools that are all very manual,” says Optigon co-founder and chief executive officer Anthony Troupe ’21. “We wanted to come up with tools for automating detection of a material’s properties, for determining whether it could make a good or bad solar cell, and then for optimizing it.”</p>
<p>“Our approach packed several non-contact, optical measurements using different types of light sources and detectors into a single system, which together provide a holistic, cross-sectional view of the material,” says Brandon Motes ’21, ME ’22, co-founder and chief technical officer.</p>
<p>“This breakthrough in achieving millisecond timescales for data collection and analysis means we can take research-quality tools and actually put them on a full production system, getting extremely detailed information about products being built at massive, gigawatt scale in real-time,” says Troupe.</p>
<p>This streamlined system takes measurements “in the snap of the fingers, unlike the traditional tools,” says Joseph Berry, director of the US Manufacturing of Advanced Perovskites Consortium and a senior research scientist at the National Renewable Energy Laboratory. “Optigon’s techniques are high precision and allow high throughput, which means they can be used in a lot of contexts where you want rapid feedback and the ability to develop materials very, very quickly.”</p>
<p>According to Berry, Optigon’s technology may give the solar industry not just better materials, but the ability to pump out high-quality PV products at a brisker clip than is currently possible. “If Optigon is successful in deploying their technology, then we can more rapidly develop the materials that we need, manufacturing with the requisite precision again and again,” he says. “This could lead to the next generation of PV modules at a much, much lower cost.”</p>
<p><strong>Measuring makes the difference</strong></p>
<p>With Small Business Innovation Research funding from DOE to commercialize its products and a grant from the Massachusetts Clean Energy Center, Optigon has settled into a space at the climate technology incubator Greentown Labs in Somerville, Massachusetts. Here, the team is preparing for this spring’s launch of its first commercial product, whose genesis lies in MIT’s GridEdge Solar Research Program.</p>
<p>Led by Vladimir Bulović, a professor of electrical engineering and the director of MIT.nano, the GridEdge program was established with funding from the Tata Trusts to develop lightweight, flexible, and inexpensive solar cells for distribution to rural communities around the globe. When deQuilettes joined the group in 2017 as a postdoc, he was tasked with directing the program and building the infrastructure to study and make perovskite solar modules.</p>
<p>“We were trying to understand once we made the material whether or not it was good,” he recalls. “There were no good commercial metrology [the science of measurements] tools for materials beyond silicon, so we started to build our own.” Recognizing the group’s need for greater expertise on the problem, especially in the areas of electrical, software, and mechanical engineering, deQuilettes put a call out for undergraduate researchers to help build metrology tools for new solar materials.</p>
<p>“Forty people inquired, but when I met Brandon and Anthony, something clicked; it was clear we had a complementary skill set,” says deQuilettes. “We started working together, with Anthony coming up with beautiful designs to integrate multiple measurements, and Brandon creating boards to control all of the hardware, including different types of lasers. We started filing multiple patents and that was when we saw it all coming together.”</p>
<p>“We knew from the start that metrology could vastly improve not just materials, but production yields,” says Troupe. Adds deQuilettes, “Our goal was getting to the highest performance orders of magnitude faster than it would ordinarily take, so we developed tools that would not just be useful for research labs but for manufacturing lines to give live feedback on quality.”</p>
<p>The device Optigon designed for industry is the size of a football, “with sensor packages crammed into a tiny form factor, taking measurements as material flows directly underneath,” says Motes. “We have also thought carefully about ways to make interaction with this tool as seamless and, dare I say, as enjoyable as possible, streaming data to both a dashboard an operator can watch and to a custom database.”</p>
<p><strong>Photovoltaics is just the start</strong></p>
<p>The company may have already found its market niche. “A research group paid us to use our in-house prototype because they have such a burning need to get these sorts of measurements,” says Troupe, and according to Motes, “Potential customers ask us if they can buy the system now.” deQuilettes says, “Our hope is that we become the de facto company for doing any sort of characterization metrology in the United States and beyond.”</p>
<p>Challenges lie ahead for Optigon: product launches, full-scale manufacturing, technical assistance, and sales. Greentown Labs offers support, as does MIT’s own rich community of solar researchers and entrepreneurs. But the founders are already thinking about next phases.</p>
<p>“We are not limiting ourselves to the photovoltaics area,” says deQuilettes. “We’re planning on working in other clean energy materials such as batteries and fuel cells.”</p>
<p>That’s because the team wants to make the maximum impact on the climate challenge. “We’ve thought a lot about the potential our tools will have on reducing carbon emissions, and we’ve done a really in-depth analysis looking at how our system can increase production yields of solar panels and other energy technologies, reducing materials and energy wasted in conventional optimization,” deQuilettes says. “If we look across all these sectors, we can expect to offset about 1,000 million metric tons of CO<sub>2 </sub>[carbon<sub></sub>dioxide] per year in the not-too-distant future.”</p>
<p>The team has written scale into its business plan. “We want to be the key enabler for bringing these new energy technologies to market,” says Motes. “We envision being deployed on every manufacturing line making these types of materials. It’s our goal to walk around and know that if we see a solar panel deployed, there’s a pretty high likelihood that it will be one we measured at some point.”</p>
</div>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>President Sally Kornbluth and OpenAI CEO Sam Altman discuss the future of AI</title>
		<link>https://www.sawberries.com/2024/05/06/president-sally-kornbluth-openai-ceo-sam-altman-discuss-future-ai-0506/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[ross]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 06 May 2024 15:01:15 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Artificial Intelligence]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Business and management]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Careers]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Community]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Ethics]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[History of science]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Human-computer interaction]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Innovation and Entrepreneurship (I&E)]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Invention]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Labor and jobs]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Machine Learning]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[MIT Schwarzman College of Computing]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[MIT Sloan School of Management]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[President Sally Kornbluth]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[School of Architecture and Planning]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[School of Engineering]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[School of Humanities Arts and Social Sciences]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[School of Science]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Special events and guest speakers]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Sustainability]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Technology and society]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.sawberries.com/2024/05/06/president-sally-kornbluth-openai-ceo-sam-altman-discuss-future-ai-0506/</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[How is the field of artificial intelligence evolving and what does it mean for the future of work, education, and humanity? MIT President Sally Kornbluth and OpenAI CEO Sam Altman covered all that and more in a wide-ranging discussion on MIT’s campus May 2. The success of OpenAI’s ChatGPT large language models has helped spur [&#8230;]]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<div>
<p>How is the field of artificial intelligence evolving and what does it mean for the future of work, education, and humanity? MIT President Sally Kornbluth and OpenAI CEO Sam Altman covered all that and more in a wide-ranging discussion on MIT’s campus May 2.</p>
<p>The success of OpenAI’s ChatGPT large language models has helped spur a wave of investment and innovation in the field of artificial intelligence. ChatGPT-3.5 became the fastest-growing consumer software application in history after its release at the end of 2022, with hundreds of millions of people using the tool. Since then, OpenAI has also demonstrated AI-driven image-, audio-, and video-generation products and partnered with Microsoft.</p>
<p>The event, which took place in a packed Kresge Auditorium, captured the excitement of the moment around AI, with an eye toward what’s next.</p>
<p>“I think most of us remember the first time we saw ChatGPT and were like, ‘Oh my god, that is so cool!’” Kornbluth said. “Now we’re trying to figure out what the next generation of all this is going to be.”</p>
<p>For his part, Altman welcomes the high expectations around his company and the field of artificial intelligence more broadly.</p>
<p>“I think it’s awesome that for two weeks, everybody was freaking out about ChatGPT-4, and then by the third week, everyone was like, ‘Come on, where’s GPT-5?’” Altman said. “I think that says something legitimately great about human expectation and striving and why we all have to [be working to] make things better.”</p>
<p><strong>The problems with AI</strong></p>
<p>Early on in their discussion, Kornbluth and Altman discussed the many ethical dilemmas posed by AI.</p>
<p>“I think we’ve made surprisingly good progress around how to align a system around a set of values,” Altman said. “As much as people like to say ‘You can’t use these things because they’re spewing toxic waste all the time,’ GPT-4 behaves kind of the way you want it to, and we’re able to get it to follow a given set of values, not perfectly well, but better than I expected by this point.”</p>
<p>Altman also pointed out that people don’t agree on exactly how an AI system should behave in many situations, complicating efforts to create a universal code of conduct.</p>
<p>“How do we decide what values a system should have?” Altman asked. “How do we decide what a system should do? How much does society define boundaries versus trusting the user with these tools? Not everyone will use them the way we like, but that’s just kind of the case with tools. I think it’s important to give people a lot of control … but there are some things a system just shouldn’t do, and we’ll have to collectively negotiate what those are.”</p>
<p>Kornbluth agreed doing things like eradicating bias in AI systems will be difficult.</p>
<p>“It’s interesting to think about whether or not we can make models less biased than we are as human beings,” she said.</p>
<p>Kornbluth also brought up privacy concerns associated with the vast amounts of data needed to train today’s large language models. Altman said society has been grappling with those concerns since the dawn of the internet, but AI is making such considerations more complex and higher-stakes. He also sees entirely new questions raised by the prospect of powerful AI systems.</p>
<p>“How are we going to navigate the privacy versus utility versus safety tradeoffs?” Altman asked. “Where we all individually decide to set those tradeoffs, and the advantages that will be possible if someone lets the system be trained on their entire life, is a new thing for society to navigate. I don’t know what the answers will be.”</p>
<p>For both privacy and energy consumption concerns surrounding AI, Altman said he believes progress in future versions of AI models will help.</p>
<p>&#8220;What we want out of GPT-5 or 6 or whatever is for it to be the best reasoning engine possible,” Altman said. “It is true that right now, the only way we’re able to do that is by training it on tons and tons of data. In that process, it’s learning something about how to do very, very limited reasoning or cognition or whatever you want to call it. But the fact that it can memorize data, or the fact that it’s storing data at all in its parameter space, I think we&#8217;ll look back and say, ‘That was kind of a weird waste of resources.’ I assume at some point, we’ll figure out how to separate the reasoning engine from the need for tons of data or storing the data in [the model], and be able to treat them as separate things.”</p>
<p>Kornbluth also asked about how AI might lead to job displacement.</p>
<p>“One of the things that annoys me most about people who work on AI is when they stand up with a straight face and say, ‘This will never cause any job elimination. This is just an additive thing. This is just all going to be great,’” Altman said. “This is going to eliminate a lot of current jobs, and this is going to change the way that a lot of current jobs function, and this is going to create entirely new jobs. That always happens with technology.&#8221;</p>
<p><strong>The promise of AI</strong></p>
<p>Altman believes progress in AI will make grappling with all of the field’s current problems worth it.</p>
<p>“If we spent 1 percent of the world’s electricity training a powerful AI, and that AI helped us figure out how to get to non-carbon-based energy or make deep carbon capture better, that would be a massive win,” Altman said.</p>
<p>He also said the application of AI he’s most interested in is scientific discovery.</p>
<p>“I believe [scientific discovery] is the core engine of human progress and that it is the only way we drive sustainable economic growth,” Altman said. “People aren’t content with GPT-4. They want things to get better. Everyone wants life more and better and faster, and science is how we get there.”</p>
<p>Kornbluth also asked Altman for his advice for students thinking about their careers. He urged students not to limit themselves.</p>
<p>“The most important lesson to learn early on in your career is that you can kind of figure anything out, and no one has all of the answers when they start out,” Altman said. “You just sort of stumble your way through, have a fast iteration speed, and try to drift toward the most interesting problems to you, and be around the most impressive people and have this trust that you’ll successfully iterate to the right thing. &#8230; You can do more than you think, faster than you think.”</p>
<p>The advice was part of a broader message Altman had about staying optimistic and working to create a better future.</p>
<p>“The way we are teaching our young people that the world is totally screwed and that it’s hopeless to try to solve problems, that all we can do is sit in our bedrooms in the dark and think about how awful we are, is a really deeply unproductive streak,” Altman said. “I hope MIT is different than a lot of other college campuses. I assume it is. But you all need to make it part of your life mission to fight against this. Prosperity, abundance, a better life next year, a better life for our children. That is the only path forward. That is the only way to have a functioning society &#8230; and the anti-progress streak, the anti ‘people deserve a great life’ streak, is something I hope you all fight against.”</p>
</div>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Hugging Face Introduces LeRobot: The First Robotics Library</title>
		<link>https://www.sawberries.com/2024/05/06/hugging-face-introduces-lerobot-the-first-robotics-library/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[ross]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 06 May 2024 15:01:13 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[AI]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Artificial Intelligence]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Community]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Datasets]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[hugging face]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[LeRobot]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Libraries]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[library]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Models]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Robotics]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.sawberries.com/2024/05/06/hugging-face-introduces-lerobot-the-first-robotics-library/</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[In a significant stride towards democratizing robotics, Hugging Face introduces LeRobot, a pioneering library tailored for real-world applications. This new library emerges as a bridge between cutting-edge research and tangible robotic behaviors. Let’s delve into the intricacies of this promising, community-driven initiative. Also Read: Hugging Face Releases World’s Largest Open Synthetic Dataset The Birth of [&#8230;]]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<div>
<p>In a significant stride towards democratizing robotics, Hugging Face introduces LeRobot, a pioneering library tailored for real-world applications. This new library emerges as a bridge between cutting-edge research and tangible robotic behaviors. Let’s delve into the intricacies of this promising, community-driven initiative. Also Read: Hugging Face Releases World’s Largest Open Synthetic Dataset The Birth of […]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://www.analyticsvidhya.com/blog/2024/05/hugging-face-introduces-lerobot-the-first-robotics-library/">Hugging Face Introduces LeRobot: The First Robotics Library</a> appeared first on <a href="https://www.analyticsvidhya.com/">Analytics Vidhya</a>.</p>
</div>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Creating bespoke programming languages for efficient visual AI systems</title>
		<link>https://www.sawberries.com/2024/05/03/creating-bespoke-programming-languages-efficient-visual-ai-systems-0503/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[ross]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 03 May 2024 21:01:17 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Artificial Intelligence]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Computer graphics]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Computer Science and Artificial Intelligence Laboratory (CSAIL)]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Computer science and technology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Computer vision]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Electrical Engineering & Computer Science (eecs)]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Faculty]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[games]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Information systems and technology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Machine Learning]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[MIT Schwarzman College of Computing]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[MIT-IBM Watson AI Lab]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Profile]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Programming]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[programming languages]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[School of Engineering]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[video]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.sawberries.com/2024/05/03/creating-bespoke-programming-languages-efficient-visual-ai-systems-0503/</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[A single photograph offers glimpses into the creator’s world — their interests and feelings about a subject or space. But what about creators behind the technologies that help to make those images possible?  MIT Department of Electrical Engineering and Computer Science Associate Professor Jonathan Ragan-Kelley is one such person, who has designed everything from tools [&#8230;]]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<div>
<p>A single photograph offers glimpses into the creator’s world — their interests and feelings about a subject or space. But what about creators behind the technologies that help to make those images possible? </p>
<p>MIT Department of Electrical Engineering and Computer Science Associate Professor Jonathan Ragan-Kelley is one such person, who has designed everything from tools for visual effects in movies to the Halide programming language that’s widely used in industry for photo editing and processing. As a researcher with the MIT-IBM Watson AI Lab and the Computer Science and Artificial Intelligence Laboratory, Ragan-Kelley specializes in high-performance, domain-specific programming languages and machine learning that enable 2D and 3D graphics, visual effects, and computational photography.</p>
<p>“The single biggest thrust through a lot of our research is developing new programming languages that make it easier to write programs that run really efficiently on the increasingly complex hardware that is in your computer today,” says Ragan-Kelley. “If we want to keep increasing the computational power we can actually exploit for real applications — from graphics and visual computing to AI — we need to change how we program.”</p>
<p><strong>Finding a middle ground</strong></p>
<p>Over the last two decades, chip designers and programming engineers have witnessed a slowing of <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Moore%27s_law" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Moore’s law</a> and a marked shift from general-purpose computing on CPUs to more varied and specialized computing and processing units like GPUs and accelerators. With this transition comes a trade-off: the ability to run general-purpose code somewhat slowly on CPUs, for faster, more efficient hardware that requires code to be heavily adapted to it and mapped to it with tailored programs and compilers. Newer hardware with improved programming can better support applications like high-bandwidth cellular radio interfaces, decoding highly compressed videos for streaming, and graphics and video processing on power-constrained cellphone cameras, to name a few applications.</p>
<p>“Our work is largely about unlocking the power of the best hardware we can build to deliver as much computational performance and efficiency as possible for these kinds of applications in ways that that traditional programming languages don&#8217;t.”</p>
<p>To accomplish this, Ragan-Kelley breaks his work down into two directions. First, he sacrifices generality to capture the structure of particular and important computational problems and exploits that for better computing efficiency. This can be seen in the image-processing language Halide, which he co-developed and has helped to transform the image editing industry in programs like Photoshop. Further, because it is specially designed to quickly handle dense, regular arrays of numbers (tensors), it also works well for neural network computations. The second focus targets automation, specifically how compilers map programs to hardware. One such project with the MIT-IBM Watson AI Lab leverages Exo, a language developed in Ragan-Kelley’s group.</p>
<p>Over the years, researchers have worked doggedly to automate coding with compilers, which can be a black box; however, there’s still a large need for explicit control and tuning by performance engineers. Ragan-Kelley and his group are developing methods that straddle each technique, balancing trade-offs to achieve effective and resource-efficient programming. At the core of many high-performance programs like video game engines or cellphone camera processing are state-of-the-art systems that are largely hand-optimized by human experts in low-level, detailed languages like C, C++, and assembly. Here, engineers make specific choices about how the program will run on the hardware.</p>
<p>Ragan-Kelley notes that programmers can opt for “very painstaking, very unproductive, and very unsafe low-level code,” which could introduce bugs, or “more safe, more productive, higher-level programming interfaces,” that lack the ability to make fine adjustments in a compiler about how the program is run, and usually deliver lower performance. So, his team is trying to find a middle ground. “We&#8217;re trying to figure out how to provide control for the key issues that human performance engineers want to be able to control,” says Ragan-Kelley, “so, we&#8217;re trying to build a new class of languages that we call user-schedulable languages that give safer and higher-level handles to control what the compiler does or control how the program is optimized.”</p>
<p><strong>Unlocking hardware: high-level and underserved ways</strong></p>
<p>Ragan-Kelley and his research group are tackling this through two lines of work: applying machine learning and modern AI techniques to automatically generate optimized schedules, an interface to the compiler, to achieve better compiler performance. Another uses “exocompilation” that he’s working on with the lab. He describes this method as a way to “turn the compiler inside-out,” with a skeleton of a compiler with controls for human guidance and customization. In addition, his team can add their bespoke schedulers on top, which can help target specialized hardware like machine-learning accelerators from IBM Research. Applications for this work span the gamut: computer vision, object recognition, speech synthesis, image synthesis, speech recognition, text generation (large language models), etc.</p>
<p>A big-picture project of his with the lab takes this another step further, approaching the work through a systems lens. In work led by his advisee and lab intern William Brandon, in collaboration with lab research scientist Rameswar Panda, Ragan-Kelley’s team is rethinking large language models (LLMs), finding ways to change the computation and the model’s programming architecture slightly so that the transformer-based models can run more efficiently on AI hardware without sacrificing accuracy. Their work, Ragan-Kelley says, deviates from the standard ways of thinking in significant ways with potentially large payoffs for cutting costs, improving capabilities, and/or shrinking the LLM to require less memory and run on smaller computers.</p>
<p>It&#8217;s this more avant-garde thinking, when it comes to computation efficiency and hardware, that Ragan-Kelley excels at and sees value in, especially in the long term. “I think there are areas [of research] that need to be pursued, but are well-established, or obvious, or are conventional-wisdom enough that lots of people either are already or will pursue them,” he says. “We try to find the ideas that have both large leverage to practically impact the world, and at the same time, are things that wouldn&#8217;t necessarily happen, or I think are being underserved relative to their potential by the rest of the community.”</p>
<p>The course that he now teaches, 6.106 (Software Performance Engineering), exemplifies this. About 15 years ago, there was a shift from single to multiple processors in a device that caused many academic programs to begin teaching parallelism. But, as Ragan-Kelley explains, MIT realized the importance of students understanding not only parallelism but also optimizing memory and using specialized hardware to achieve the best performance possible.</p>
<p>“By changing how we program, we can unlock the computational potential of new machines, and make it possible for people to continue to rapidly develop new applications and new ideas that are able to exploit that ever-more complicated and challenging hardware.”</p>
</div>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>HPI-MIT design research collaboration creates powerful teams</title>
		<link>https://www.sawberries.com/2024/05/03/hpi-mit-design-research-collaboration-creates-powerful-teams-0503/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[ross]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 03 May 2024 21:01:16 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Artificial Intelligence]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Business and management]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Cleaner industry]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Climate change]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Collaboration]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Computer Science and Artificial Intelligence Laboratory (CSAIL)]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Cybersecurity]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Design]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Electrical Engineering & Computer Science (eecs)]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Environmental Solutions Initiative]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Innovation and Entrepreneurship (I&E)]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Machine Learning]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Manufacturing]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[MIT Morningside Academy for Design]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[MIT Sloan School of Management]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Renewable energy]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Research]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[School of Architecture and Planning]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[School of Engineering]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Startups]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Supply chains]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.sawberries.com/2024/05/03/hpi-mit-design-research-collaboration-creates-powerful-teams-0503/</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[The recent ransomware attack on ChangeHealthcare, which severed the network connecting health care providers, pharmacies, and hospitals with health insurance companies, demonstrates just how disruptive supply chain attacks can be. In this case, it hindered the ability of those providing medical services to submit insurance claims and receive payments. This sort of attack and other [&#8230;]]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<div>
<p>The recent ransomware attack on ChangeHealthcare, which severed the network connecting health care providers, pharmacies, and hospitals with health insurance companies, demonstrates just how disruptive supply chain attacks can be. In this case, it hindered the ability of those providing medical services to submit insurance claims and receive payments.</p>
<p>This sort of attack and other forms of data theft are becoming increasingly common and often target large, multinational corporations through the small and mid-sized vendors in their corporate supply chains, enabling breaks in these enormous systems of interwoven companies.</p>
<p>Cybersecurity researchers at MIT and the <a href="https://hpi.de/en/research/research-school/international-branches/hasso-plattner-institute.html">Hasso Plattner Institute</a> (HPI) in Potsdam, Germany, are focused on the different organizational security cultures that exist within large corporations and their vendors because it’s that difference that creates vulnerabilities, often due to the lack of emphasis on cybersecurity by the senior leadership in these small to medium-sized enterprises (SMEs).</p>
<p>Keri Pearlson, executive director of Cybersecurity at MIT Sloan (CAMS); Jillian Kwong, a research scientist at CAMS; and Christian Doerr, a professor of cybersecurity and enterprise security at HPI, are co-principal investigators (PIs) on the research project, “Culture and the Supply Chain: Transmitting Shared Values, Attitudes and Beliefs across Cybersecurity Supply Chains.”</p>
<p>Their project was selected in the 2023 inaugural round of grants from the <a href="https://design.mit.edu/about/research">HPI-MIT Designing for Sustainability program</a>, a multiyear partnership funded by HPI and administered by the MIT Morningside Academy for Design (MAD). The program awards about 10 grants annually of up to $200,000 each to multidisciplinary teams with divergent backgrounds in computer science, artificial intelligence, machine learning, engineering, design, architecture, the natural sciences, humanities, and business and management. The <a href="https://design.mit.edu/about/research">2024 Call for Applications</a> is open through June 3.</p>
<p>Designing for Sustainability grants support scientific research that promotes the United Nations’ Sustainable Development Goals (SDGs) on topics involving sustainable design, innovation, and digital technologies, with teams made up of PIs from both institutions. The PIs on these projects, who have common interests but different strengths, create more powerful teams by working together.</p>
<p><strong>Transmitting shared values, attitudes, and beliefs to improve cybersecurity across supply chains</strong></p>
<p>The MIT and HPI cybersecurity researchers say that most ransomware attacks aren’t reported. Smaller companies hit with ransomware attacks just shut down, because they can’t afford the payment to retrieve their data. This makes it difficult to know just how many attacks and data breaches occur. “As more data and processes move online and into the cloud, it becomes even more important to focus on securing supply chains,” Kwong says. “Investing in cybersecurity allows information to be exchanged freely while keeping data safe. Without it, any progress towards sustainability is stalled.”</p>
<p>One of the first large data breaches in the United States to be widely publicized provides a clear example of how an SME cybersecurity can leave a multinational corporation vulnerable to attack. In 2013, hackers entered the Target Corporation’s own network by obtaining the credentials of a small vendor in its supply chain: a Pennsylvania HVAC company. Through that breach, thieves were able to install malware that stole the financial and personal information of 110 million Target customers, which they sold to card shops on the black market.</p>
<p>To prevent such attacks, SME vendors in a large corporation’s supply chain are required to agree to follow certain security measures, but the SMEs usually don’t have the expertise or training to make good on these cybersecurity promises, leaving their own systems, and therefore any connected to them, vulnerable to attack.</p>
<p>“Right now, organizations are connected economically, but not aligned in terms of organizational culture, values, beliefs, and practices around cybersecurity,” explains Kwong. “Basically, the big companies are realizing the smaller ones are not able to implement all the cybersecurity requirements. We have seen some larger companies address this by reducing requirements or making the process shorter. However, this doesn’t mean companies are more secure; it just lowers the bar for the smaller suppliers to clear it.”</p>
<p>Pearlson emphasizes the importance of board members and senior management taking responsibility for cybersecurity in order to change the culture at SMEs, rather than pushing that down to a single department, IT office, or in some cases, one IT employee.</p>
<p>The research team is using case studies based on interviews, field studies, focus groups, and direct observation of people in their natural work environments to learn how companies engage with vendors, and the specific ways cybersecurity is implemented, or not, in everyday operations. The goal is to create a shared culture around cybersecurity that can be adopted correctly by all vendors in a supply chain.</p>
<p>This approach is in line with the goals of the Charter of Trust Initiative, a partnership of large, multinational corporations formed to establish a better means of implementing cybersecurity in the supply chain network. The HPI-MIT team worked with companies from the Charter of Trust and others last year to understand the impacts of cybersecurity regulation on SME participation in supply chains and develop a conceptual framework to implement changes for stabilizing supply chains.</p>
<p>Cybersecurity is a prerequisite needed to achieve any of the United Nations’ SDGs, explains Kwong. Without secure supply chains, access to key resources and institutions can be abruptly cut off. This could include food, clean water and sanitation, renewable energy, financial systems, health care, education, and resilient infrastructure. Securing supply chains helps enable progress on all SDGs, and the HPI-MIT project specifically supports SMEs, which are a pillar of the U.S. and European economies.</p>
<p><strong>Personalizing product designs while minimizing material waste</strong></p>
<p>In a vastly different Designing for Sustainability joint research project that employs AI with engineering, “Personalizing Product Designs While Minimizing Material Waste” will use AI design software to lay out multiple parts of a pattern on a sheet of plywood, acrylic, or other material, so that they can be laser cut to create new products in real time without wasting material.</p>
<p>Stefanie Mueller, the TIBCO Career Development Associate Professor in the MIT Department of Electrical Engineering and Computer Science and a member of the Computer Science and Artificial Intelligence Laboratory, and Patrick Baudisch, a professor of computer science and chair of the Human Computer Interaction Lab at HPI, are co-PIs on the project. The two have worked together for years; Baudisch was Mueller’s PhD research advisor at HPI.</p>
<p>Baudisch’s lab developed an online design teaching system called <a href="https://kyub.com/">Kyub</a> that lets students design 3D objects in pieces that are laser cut from sheets of wood and assembled to become chairs, speaker boxes, radio-controlled aircraft, or even functional musical instruments. For instance, each leg of a chair would consist of four identical vertical pieces attached at the edges to create a hollow-centered column, four of which will provide stability to the chair, even though the material is very lightweight.</p>
<p>“By designing and constructing such furniture, students learn not only design, but also structural engineering,” Baudisch says. “Similarly, by designing and constructing musical instruments, they learn about structural engineering, as well as resonance, types of musical tuning, etc.”</p>
<p>Mueller was at HPI when Baudisch developed the Kyub software, allowing her to observe “how they were developing and making all the design decisions,” she says. “They built a really neat piece for people to quickly design these types of 3D objects.” However, using Kyub for material-efficient design is not fast; in order to fabricate a model, the software has to break the 3D models down into 2D parts and lay these out on sheets of material. This takes time, and makes it difficult to see the impact of design decisions on material use in real-time.</p>
<p>Mueller’s lab at MIT developed software based on a layout algorithm that uses AI to lay out pieces on sheets of material in real time. This allows AI to explore multiple potential layouts while the user is still editing, and thus provide ongoing feedback. “As the user develops their design, <a href="https://hcie.csail.mit.edu/research/fabricaide/fabricaide.html">Fabricaide</a> decides good placements of parts onto the user&#8217;s available materials, provides warnings if the user does not have enough material for a design, and makes suggestions for how the user can resolve insufficient material cases,” according to the project website.</p>
<p>The joint MIT-HPI project integrates Mueller’s AI software with Baudisch’s Kyub software and adds machine learning to train the AI to offer better design suggestions that save material while adhering to the user’s design intent.</p>
<p>“The project is all about minimizing the waste on these materials sheets,” Mueller says. She already envisions the next step in this AI design process: determining how to integrate the laws of physics into the AI’s knowledge base to ensure the structural integrity and stability of objects it designs.</p>
<p><strong>AI-powered startup design for the Anthropocene: Providing guidance for novel enterprises</strong></p>
<p>Through her work with the teams of <a href="https://designx.mit.edu/">MITdesignX</a> and its international programs, Svafa Grönfeldt, faculty director of MITdesignX and professor of the practice in MIT MAD, has helped scores of people in startup companies use the tools and methods of design to ensure that the solution a startup proposes actually fits the problem it seeks to solve. This is often called the problem-solution fit.</p>
<p>Grönfeldt and MIT postdoc Norhan Bayomi are now extending this work to incorporate AI into the process, in collaboration with MIT Professor John Fernández and graduate student Tyler Kim. The HPI team includes Professor Gerard de Melo; HPI School of Entrepreneurship Director Frank Pawlitschek; and doctoral student Michael Mansfeld.</p>
<p>“The startup ecosystem is characterized by uncertainty and volatility compounded by growing uncertainties in climate and planetary systems,” Grönfeldt says. “Therefore, there is an urgent need for a robust model that can objectively predict startup success and guide design for the Anthropocene.”</p>
<p>While startup-success forecasting is gaining popularity, it currently focuses on aiding venture capitalists in selecting companies to fund, rather than guiding the startups in the design of their products, services and business plans.</p>
<p>“The coupling of climate and environmental priorities with startup agendas requires deeper analytics for effective enterprise design,” Grönfeldt says. The project aims to explore whether AI-augmented decision-support systems can enhance startup-success forecasting.</p>
<p>“We&#8217;re trying to develop a machine learning approach that will give a forecasting of probability of success based on a number of parameters, including the type of business model proposed, how the team came together, the team members’ backgrounds and skill sets, the market and industry sector they&#8217;re working in and the problem-solution fit,” says Bayomi, who works with Fernández in the MIT Environmental Solutions Initiative. The two are co-founders of the startup Lamarr.AI, which employs robotics and AI to help reduce the carbon dioxide impact of the built environment.</p>
<p>The team is studying “how company founders make decisions across four key areas, starting from the opportunity recognition, how they are selecting the team members, how they are selecting the business model, identifying the most automatic strategy, all the way through the product market fit to gain an understanding of the key governing parameters in each of these areas,” explains Bayomi.</p>
<p>The team is “also developing a large language model that will guide the selection of the business model by using large datasets from different companies in Germany and the U.S. We train the model based on the specific industry sector, such as a technology solution or a data solution, to find what would be the most suitable business model that would increase the success probability of a company,” she says.</p>
<p>The project falls under several of the United Nations’ Sustainable Development Goals, including economic growth, innovation and infrastructure, sustainable cities and communities, and climate action.</p>
<p><strong>Furthering the goals of the HPI-MIT Joint Research Program</strong></p>
<p>These three diverse projects all advance the mission of the HPI-MIT collaboration. MIT MAD aims to use design to transform learning, catalyze innovation, and empower society by inspiring people from all disciplines to interweave design into problem-solving. HPI uses digital engineering concentrated on the development and research of user-oriented innovations for all areas of life.</p>
<p>Interdisciplinary teams with members from both institutions are encouraged to develop and submit proposals for ambitious, sustainable projects that use design strategically to generate measurable, impactful solutions to the world’s problems.</p>
</div>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Exploring frontiers of mechanical engineering</title>
		<link>https://www.sawberries.com/2024/05/03/mechanical-engineering-graduate-students-explore-frontiers-0503/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[ross]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 03 May 2024 18:01:16 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Artificial Intelligence]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Design]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Graduate, postdoctoral]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Health sciences and technology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Human-computer interaction]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Independent Activities Period]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mechanical engineering]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Nanoscience and nanotechnology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Oceanography and ocean engineering]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Profile]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[School of Engineering]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Spaceflight]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Sports analytics]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Students]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Water]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.sawberries.com/2024/05/03/mechanical-engineering-graduate-students-explore-frontiers-0503/</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[From cutting-edge robotics, design, and bioengineering to sustainable energy solutions, ocean engineering, nanotechnology, and innovative materials science, MechE students and their advisors are doing incredibly innovative work. The graduate students highlighted here represent a snapshot of the great work in progress this spring across the Department of Mechanical Engineering, and demonstrate the ways the future [&#8230;]]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<div>
<p>From cutting-edge robotics, design, and bioengineering to sustainable energy solutions, ocean engineering, nanotechnology, and innovative materials science, MechE students and their advisors are doing incredibly innovative work. The graduate students highlighted here represent a snapshot of the great work in progress this spring across the Department of Mechanical Engineering, and demonstrate the ways the future of this field is as limitless as the imaginations of its practitioners.</p>
<p><strong>Democratizing design through AI</strong></p>
<p>Lyle Regenwetter<br />Hometown: Champaign, Illinois<br />Advisor: Assistant Professor Faez Ahmed<br />Interests: Food, climbing, skiing, soccer, tennis, cooking</p>
<p>Lyle Regenwetter finds excitement in the prospect of generative AI to &#8220;democratize&#8221; design and enable inexperienced designers to tackle complex design problems. His research explores new training methods through which generative AI models can be taught to implicitly obey design constraints and synthesize higher-performing designs. Knowing that prospective designers often have an intimate knowledge of the needs of users, but may otherwise lack the technical training to create solutions, Regenwetter also develops human-AI collaborative tools that allow AI models to interact and support designers in popular CAD software and real design problems. </p>
<p><strong>Solving a whale of a problem </strong></p>
<p>Loïcka Baille<br />Hometown: L’Escale, France<br />Advisor: Daniel Zitterbart<br />Interests: Being outdoors — scuba diving, spelunking, or climbing. Sailing on the Charles River, martial arts classes, and playing volleyball</p>
<p>Loïcka Baille’s research focuses on developing remote sensing technologies to study and protect marine life. Her main project revolves around improving onboard whale detection technology to prevent vessel strikes, with a special focus on protecting North Atlantic right whales. Baille is also involved in an ongoing study of Emperor penguins. Her team visits Antarctica annually to tag penguins and gather data to enhance their understanding of penguin population dynamics and draw conclusions regarding the overall health of the ecosystem.</p>
<p><strong>Water, water anywhere</strong></p>
<p>Carlos Díaz-Marín<br />Hometown: San José, Costa Rica<br />Advisor: Professor Gang Chen | Former Advisor: Professor Evelyn Wang<br />Interests: New England hiking, biking, and dancing</p>
<p>Carlos Díaz-Marín designs and synthesizes inexpensive salt-polymer materials that can capture large amounts of humidity from the air. He aims to change the way we generate potable water from the air, even in arid conditions. In addition to water generation, these salt-polymer materials can also be used as thermal batteries, capable of storing and reusing heat. Beyond the scientific applications, Díaz-Marín is excited to continue doing research that can have big social impacts, and that finds and explains new physical phenomena. As a LatinX person, Díaz-Marín is also driven to help increase diversity in STEM.</p>
<p><strong>Scalable fabrication of nano-architected materials</strong></p>
<p>Somayajulu Dhulipala<br />Hometown: Hyderabad, India<br />Advisor: Assistant Professor Carlos Portela<br />Interests: Space exploration, taekwondo, meditation.</p>
<p>Somayajulu Dhulipala works on developing lightweight materials with tunable mechanical properties. He is currently working on methods for the scalable fabrication of nano-architected materials and predicting their mechanical properties. The ability to fine-tune the mechanical properties of specific materials brings versatility and adaptability, making these materials suitable for a wide range of applications across multiple industries. While the research applications are quite diverse, Dhulipala is passionate about making space habitable for humanity, a crucial step toward becoming a spacefaring civilization.</p>
<p><strong>Ingestible health-care devices</strong></p>
<p>Jimmy McRae<br />Hometown: Woburn, Massachusetts<br />Advisor: Associate Professor Giovani Traverso<br />Interests: Anything basketball-related: playing, watching, going to games, organizing hometown tournaments </p>
<p>Jimmy McRae aims to drastically improve diagnostic and therapeutic capabilities through noninvasive health-care technologies. His research focuses on leveraging materials, mechanics, embedded systems, and microfabrication to develop novel ingestible electronic and mechatronic devices. This ranges from ingestible electroceutical capsules that modulate hunger-regulating hormones to devices capable of continuous ultralong monitoring and remotely triggerable actuations from within the stomach. The principles that guide McRae’s work to develop devices that function in extreme environments can be applied far beyond the gastrointestinal tract, with applications for outer space, the ocean, and more.</p>
<p><strong>Freestyle BMX meets machine learning</strong></p>
<p>Eva Nates<br />Hometown: Narberth, Pennsylvania <br />Advisor: Professor Peko Hosoi<br />Interests: Rowing, running, biking, hiking, baking</p>
<p>Eva Nates is working with the Australian Cycling Team to create a tool to classify Bicycle Motocross Freestyle (BMX FS) tricks. She uses a singular value decomposition method to conduct a principal component analysis of the time-dependent point-tracking data of an athlete and their bike during a run to classify each trick. The 2024 Olympic team hopes to incorporate this tool in their training workflow, and Nates worked alongside the team at their facilities on the Gold Coast of Australia during MIT’s Independent Activities Period in January.</p>
<p><strong>Augmenting Astronauts with Wearable Limbs </strong></p>
<p>Erik Ballesteros<br />Hometown: Spring, Texas<br />Advisor: Professor Harry Asada<br />Interests: Cosplay, Star Wars, Lego bricks</p>
<p>Erik Ballesteros’s research seeks to support astronauts who are conducting planetary extravehicular activities through the use of supernumerary robotic limbs (SuperLimbs). His work is tailored toward design and control manifestation to assist astronauts with post-fall recovery, human-leader/robot-follower quadruped locomotion, and coordinated manipulation between the SuperLimbs and the astronaut to perform tasks like excavation and sample handling.</p>
<p><em>This article appeared in the Spring 2024 edition of the Department of Mechanical Engineering&#8217;s magazine, </em><a href="https://meche.mit.edu/magazine">MechE Connects</a><em>. </em></p>
</div>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Physicists arrange atoms in extremely close proximity</title>
		<link>https://www.sawberries.com/2024/05/03/physicists-arrange-atoms-extremely-close-proximity-0502/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[ross]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 03 May 2024 00:01:05 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Department of Defense (DoD)]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Light]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[nano]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Nanoscience and nanotechnology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[National Science Foundation (NSF)]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Physics]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Quantum computing]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Research]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Research Laboratory of Electronics]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[School of Science]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.sawberries.com/2024/05/03/physicists-arrange-atoms-extremely-close-proximity-0502/</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Proximity is key for many quantum phenomena, as interactions between atoms are stronger when the particles are close. In many quantum simulators, scientists arrange atoms as close together as possible to explore exotic states of matter and build new quantum materials. They typically do this by cooling the atoms to a stand-still, then using laser [&#8230;]]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<div>
<p>Proximity is key for many quantum phenomena, as interactions between atoms are stronger when the particles are close. In many quantum simulators, scientists arrange atoms as close together as possible to explore exotic states of matter and build new quantum materials.</p>
<p>They typically do this by cooling the atoms to a stand-still, then using laser light to position the particles as close as 500 nanometers apart — a limit that is set by the wavelength of light. Now, MIT physicists have developed a technique that allows them to arrange atoms in much closer proximity, down to a mere 50 nanometers. For context, a red blood cell is about 1,000 nanometers wide.</p>
<p>The physicists demonstrated the new approach in experiments with dysprosium, which is the most magnetic atom in nature. They used the new approach to manipulate two layers of dysprosium atoms, and positioned the layers precisely 50 nanometers apart. At this extreme proximity, the magnetic interactions were 1,000 times stronger than if the layers were separated by 500 nanometers.</p>
<p>What’s more, the scientists were able to measure two new effects caused by the atoms’ proximity. Their enhanced magnetic forces caused “thermalization,” or the transfer of heat from one layer to another, as well as synchronized oscillations between layers. These effects petered out as the layers were spaced farther apart.</p>
<p>“We have gone from positioning atoms from 500 nanometers to 50 nanometers apart, and there is a lot you can do with this,” says Wolfgang Ketterle, the John D. MacArthur Professor of Physics at MIT. “At 50 nanometers, the behavior of atoms is so much different that we’re really entering a new regime here.”</p>
<p>Ketterle and his colleagues say the new approach can be applied to many other atoms to study quantum phenomena. For their part, the group plans to use the technique to manipulate atoms into configurations that could generate the first purely magnetic quantum gate — a key building block for a new type of quantum computer.</p>
<p>The team has <a href="https://www.science.org/doi/10.1126/science.adh3023" target="_blank" rel="noopener">published their results today</a> in the journal <em>Science</em>. The study’s co-authors include lead author and physics graduate student Li Du, along with Pierre Barral, Michael Cantara, Julius de Hond, and Yu-Kun Lu — all members of the MIT-Harvard Center for Ultracold Atoms, the Department of Physics, and the Research Laboratory of Electronics at MIT.</p>
<p><strong>Peaks and valleys</strong></p>
<p>To manipulate and arrange atoms, physicists typically first cool a cloud of atoms to temperatures approaching absolute zero, then use a system of laser beams to corral the atoms into an optical trap.</p>
<p>Laser light is an electromagnetic wave with a specific wavelength (the distance between maxima of the electric field) and frequency. The wavelength limits the smallest pattern into which light can be shaped to typically 500 nanometers, the so-called optical resolution limit. Since atoms are attracted by laser light of certain frequencies, atoms will be positioned at the points of peak laser intensity. For this reason, existing techniques have been limited in how close they can position atomic particles, and could not be used to explore phenomena that happen at much shorter distances.</p>
<p>“Conventional techniques stop at 500 nanometers, limited not by the atoms but by the wavelength of light,” Ketterle explains. “We have found now a new trick with light where we can break through that limit.”</p>
<p>The team’s new approach, like current techniques, starts by cooling a cloud of atoms — in this case, to about 1 microkelvin, just a hair above absolute zero — at which point, the atoms come to a near-standstill. Physicists can then use lasers to move the frozen particles into desired configurations.</p>
<p>Then, Du and his collaborators worked with two laser beams, each with a different frequency, or color, and circular polarization, or direction of the laser’s electric field. When the two beams travel through a super-cooled cloud of atoms, the atoms can orient their spin in opposite directions, following either of the two lasers’ polarization. The result is that the beams produce two groups of the same atoms, only with opposite spins.</p>
<p>Each laser beam formed a standing wave, a periodic pattern of electric field intensity with a spatial period of 500 nanometers. Due to their different polarizations, each standing wave attracted and corralled one of two groups of atoms, depending on their spin. The lasers could be overlaid and tuned such that the distance between their respective peaks is as small as 50 nanometers, meaning that the atoms gravitating to each respective laser’s peaks would be separated by the same 50 nanometers.</p>
<p>But in order for this to happen, the lasers would have to be extremely stable and immune to all external noise, such as from shaking or even breathing on the experiment. The team realized they could stabilize both lasers by directing them through an optical fiber, which served to lock the light beams in place in relation to each other.</p>
<p>“The idea of sending both beams through the optical fiber meant the whole machine could shake violently, but the two laser beams stayed absolutely stable with respect to each others,” Du says.</p>
<p><strong>Magnetic forces at close range</strong></p>
<p>As a first test of their new technique, the team used atoms of dysprosium — a rare-earth metal that is one of the strongest magnetic elements in the periodic table, particularly at ultracold temperatures. However, at the scale of atoms, the element’s magnetic interactions are relatively weak at distances of even 500 nanometers. As with common refrigerator magnets, the magnetic attraction between atoms increases with proximity, and the scientists suspected that if their new technique could space dysprosium atoms as close as 50 nanometers apart, they might observe the emergence of otherwise weak interactions between the magnetic atoms.</p>
<p>“We could suddenly have magnetic interactions, which used to be almost neglible but now are really strong,” Ketterle says.</p>
<p>The team applied their technique to dysprosium, first super-cooling the atoms, then passing two lasers through to split the atoms into two spin groups, or layers. They then directed the lasers through an optical fiber to stabilize them, and found that indeed, the two layers of dysprosium atoms gravitated to their respective laser peaks, which in effect separated the layers of atoms by 50 nanometers — the closest distance that any ultracold atom experiment has been able to achieve.</p>
<p>At this extremely close proximity, the atoms’ natural magnetic interactions were significantly enhanced, and were 1,000 times stronger than if they were positioned 500 nanometers apart. The team observed that these interactions resulted in two novel quantum phenomena: collective oscillation, in which one layer’s vibrations caused the other layer to vibrate in sync; and thermalization, in which one layer transferred heat to the other, purely through magnetic fluctuations in the atoms.</p>
<p>“Until now, heat between atoms could only by exchanged when they were in the same physical space and could collide,” Du notes. “Now we have seen atomic layers, separated by vacuum, and they exchange heat via fluctuating magnetic fields.”</p>
<p>The team’s results introduce a new technique that can be used to position many types of atom in close proximity. They also show that atoms, placed close enough together, can exhibit interesting quantum phenomena, that could be harnessed to build new quantum materials, and potentially, magnetically-driven atomic systems for quantum computers.</p>
<p>“We are really bringing super-resolution methods to the field, and it will become a general tool for doing quantum simulations,” Ketterle says. “There are many variants possible, which we are working on.”</p>
<p>This research was funded, in part, by the National Science Foundation and the Department of Defense.</p>
</div>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
