<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>nano &#8211; sawberries</title>
	<atom:link href="http://localhost/sawberries/category/nano/feed/?simply_static_page=788257" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>https://www.sawberries.com</link>
	<description>www.sawberry.com site</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Fri, 03 May 2024 21:01:17 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=6.5.2</generator>

<image>
	<url>https://www.sawberries.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/04/cropped-DALL·E-2024-04-26-12.21.04-A-512x512-favicon-design-that-incorporates-a-playful-twist-on-the-concept-of-a-strawberry-symbolizing-connections-between-people.-The-strawberry-shou-32x32.webp</url>
	<title>nano &#8211; sawberries</title>
	<link>https://www.sawberries.com</link>
	<width>32</width>
	<height>32</height>
</image> 
	<item>
		<title>Creating bespoke programming languages for efficient visual AI systems</title>
		<link>https://www.sawberries.com/2024/05/03/creating-bespoke-programming-languages-efficient-visual-ai-systems-0503/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[ross]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 03 May 2024 21:01:17 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Artificial Intelligence]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Computer graphics]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Computer Science and Artificial Intelligence Laboratory (CSAIL)]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Computer science and technology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Computer vision]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Electrical Engineering & Computer Science (eecs)]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Faculty]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[games]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Information systems and technology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Machine Learning]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[MIT Schwarzman College of Computing]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[MIT-IBM Watson AI Lab]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Profile]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Programming]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[programming languages]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[School of Engineering]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[video]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.sawberries.com/2024/05/03/creating-bespoke-programming-languages-efficient-visual-ai-systems-0503/</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[A single photograph offers glimpses into the creator’s world — their interests and feelings about a subject or space. But what about creators behind the technologies that help to make those images possible?  MIT Department of Electrical Engineering and Computer Science Associate Professor Jonathan Ragan-Kelley is one such person, who has designed everything from tools [&#8230;]]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<div>
<p>A single photograph offers glimpses into the creator’s world — their interests and feelings about a subject or space. But what about creators behind the technologies that help to make those images possible? </p>
<p>MIT Department of Electrical Engineering and Computer Science Associate Professor Jonathan Ragan-Kelley is one such person, who has designed everything from tools for visual effects in movies to the Halide programming language that’s widely used in industry for photo editing and processing. As a researcher with the MIT-IBM Watson AI Lab and the Computer Science and Artificial Intelligence Laboratory, Ragan-Kelley specializes in high-performance, domain-specific programming languages and machine learning that enable 2D and 3D graphics, visual effects, and computational photography.</p>
<p>“The single biggest thrust through a lot of our research is developing new programming languages that make it easier to write programs that run really efficiently on the increasingly complex hardware that is in your computer today,” says Ragan-Kelley. “If we want to keep increasing the computational power we can actually exploit for real applications — from graphics and visual computing to AI — we need to change how we program.”</p>
<p><strong>Finding a middle ground</strong></p>
<p>Over the last two decades, chip designers and programming engineers have witnessed a slowing of <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Moore%27s_law" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Moore’s law</a> and a marked shift from general-purpose computing on CPUs to more varied and specialized computing and processing units like GPUs and accelerators. With this transition comes a trade-off: the ability to run general-purpose code somewhat slowly on CPUs, for faster, more efficient hardware that requires code to be heavily adapted to it and mapped to it with tailored programs and compilers. Newer hardware with improved programming can better support applications like high-bandwidth cellular radio interfaces, decoding highly compressed videos for streaming, and graphics and video processing on power-constrained cellphone cameras, to name a few applications.</p>
<p>“Our work is largely about unlocking the power of the best hardware we can build to deliver as much computational performance and efficiency as possible for these kinds of applications in ways that that traditional programming languages don&#8217;t.”</p>
<p>To accomplish this, Ragan-Kelley breaks his work down into two directions. First, he sacrifices generality to capture the structure of particular and important computational problems and exploits that for better computing efficiency. This can be seen in the image-processing language Halide, which he co-developed and has helped to transform the image editing industry in programs like Photoshop. Further, because it is specially designed to quickly handle dense, regular arrays of numbers (tensors), it also works well for neural network computations. The second focus targets automation, specifically how compilers map programs to hardware. One such project with the MIT-IBM Watson AI Lab leverages Exo, a language developed in Ragan-Kelley’s group.</p>
<p>Over the years, researchers have worked doggedly to automate coding with compilers, which can be a black box; however, there’s still a large need for explicit control and tuning by performance engineers. Ragan-Kelley and his group are developing methods that straddle each technique, balancing trade-offs to achieve effective and resource-efficient programming. At the core of many high-performance programs like video game engines or cellphone camera processing are state-of-the-art systems that are largely hand-optimized by human experts in low-level, detailed languages like C, C++, and assembly. Here, engineers make specific choices about how the program will run on the hardware.</p>
<p>Ragan-Kelley notes that programmers can opt for “very painstaking, very unproductive, and very unsafe low-level code,” which could introduce bugs, or “more safe, more productive, higher-level programming interfaces,” that lack the ability to make fine adjustments in a compiler about how the program is run, and usually deliver lower performance. So, his team is trying to find a middle ground. “We&#8217;re trying to figure out how to provide control for the key issues that human performance engineers want to be able to control,” says Ragan-Kelley, “so, we&#8217;re trying to build a new class of languages that we call user-schedulable languages that give safer and higher-level handles to control what the compiler does or control how the program is optimized.”</p>
<p><strong>Unlocking hardware: high-level and underserved ways</strong></p>
<p>Ragan-Kelley and his research group are tackling this through two lines of work: applying machine learning and modern AI techniques to automatically generate optimized schedules, an interface to the compiler, to achieve better compiler performance. Another uses “exocompilation” that he’s working on with the lab. He describes this method as a way to “turn the compiler inside-out,” with a skeleton of a compiler with controls for human guidance and customization. In addition, his team can add their bespoke schedulers on top, which can help target specialized hardware like machine-learning accelerators from IBM Research. Applications for this work span the gamut: computer vision, object recognition, speech synthesis, image synthesis, speech recognition, text generation (large language models), etc.</p>
<p>A big-picture project of his with the lab takes this another step further, approaching the work through a systems lens. In work led by his advisee and lab intern William Brandon, in collaboration with lab research scientist Rameswar Panda, Ragan-Kelley’s team is rethinking large language models (LLMs), finding ways to change the computation and the model’s programming architecture slightly so that the transformer-based models can run more efficiently on AI hardware without sacrificing accuracy. Their work, Ragan-Kelley says, deviates from the standard ways of thinking in significant ways with potentially large payoffs for cutting costs, improving capabilities, and/or shrinking the LLM to require less memory and run on smaller computers.</p>
<p>It&#8217;s this more avant-garde thinking, when it comes to computation efficiency and hardware, that Ragan-Kelley excels at and sees value in, especially in the long term. “I think there are areas [of research] that need to be pursued, but are well-established, or obvious, or are conventional-wisdom enough that lots of people either are already or will pursue them,” he says. “We try to find the ideas that have both large leverage to practically impact the world, and at the same time, are things that wouldn&#8217;t necessarily happen, or I think are being underserved relative to their potential by the rest of the community.”</p>
<p>The course that he now teaches, 6.106 (Software Performance Engineering), exemplifies this. About 15 years ago, there was a shift from single to multiple processors in a device that caused many academic programs to begin teaching parallelism. But, as Ragan-Kelley explains, MIT realized the importance of students understanding not only parallelism but also optimizing memory and using specialized hardware to achieve the best performance possible.</p>
<p>“By changing how we program, we can unlock the computational potential of new machines, and make it possible for people to continue to rapidly develop new applications and new ideas that are able to exploit that ever-more complicated and challenging hardware.”</p>
</div>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>HPI-MIT design research collaboration creates powerful teams</title>
		<link>https://www.sawberries.com/2024/05/03/hpi-mit-design-research-collaboration-creates-powerful-teams-0503/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[ross]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 03 May 2024 21:01:16 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Artificial Intelligence]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Business and management]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Cleaner industry]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Climate change]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Collaboration]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Computer Science and Artificial Intelligence Laboratory (CSAIL)]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Cybersecurity]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Design]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Electrical Engineering & Computer Science (eecs)]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Environmental Solutions Initiative]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Innovation and Entrepreneurship (I&E)]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Machine Learning]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Manufacturing]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[MIT Morningside Academy for Design]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[MIT Sloan School of Management]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Renewable energy]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Research]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[School of Architecture and Planning]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[School of Engineering]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Startups]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Supply chains]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.sawberries.com/2024/05/03/hpi-mit-design-research-collaboration-creates-powerful-teams-0503/</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[The recent ransomware attack on ChangeHealthcare, which severed the network connecting health care providers, pharmacies, and hospitals with health insurance companies, demonstrates just how disruptive supply chain attacks can be. In this case, it hindered the ability of those providing medical services to submit insurance claims and receive payments. This sort of attack and other [&#8230;]]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<div>
<p>The recent ransomware attack on ChangeHealthcare, which severed the network connecting health care providers, pharmacies, and hospitals with health insurance companies, demonstrates just how disruptive supply chain attacks can be. In this case, it hindered the ability of those providing medical services to submit insurance claims and receive payments.</p>
<p>This sort of attack and other forms of data theft are becoming increasingly common and often target large, multinational corporations through the small and mid-sized vendors in their corporate supply chains, enabling breaks in these enormous systems of interwoven companies.</p>
<p>Cybersecurity researchers at MIT and the <a href="https://hpi.de/en/research/research-school/international-branches/hasso-plattner-institute.html">Hasso Plattner Institute</a> (HPI) in Potsdam, Germany, are focused on the different organizational security cultures that exist within large corporations and their vendors because it’s that difference that creates vulnerabilities, often due to the lack of emphasis on cybersecurity by the senior leadership in these small to medium-sized enterprises (SMEs).</p>
<p>Keri Pearlson, executive director of Cybersecurity at MIT Sloan (CAMS); Jillian Kwong, a research scientist at CAMS; and Christian Doerr, a professor of cybersecurity and enterprise security at HPI, are co-principal investigators (PIs) on the research project, “Culture and the Supply Chain: Transmitting Shared Values, Attitudes and Beliefs across Cybersecurity Supply Chains.”</p>
<p>Their project was selected in the 2023 inaugural round of grants from the <a href="https://design.mit.edu/about/research">HPI-MIT Designing for Sustainability program</a>, a multiyear partnership funded by HPI and administered by the MIT Morningside Academy for Design (MAD). The program awards about 10 grants annually of up to $200,000 each to multidisciplinary teams with divergent backgrounds in computer science, artificial intelligence, machine learning, engineering, design, architecture, the natural sciences, humanities, and business and management. The <a href="https://design.mit.edu/about/research">2024 Call for Applications</a> is open through June 3.</p>
<p>Designing for Sustainability grants support scientific research that promotes the United Nations’ Sustainable Development Goals (SDGs) on topics involving sustainable design, innovation, and digital technologies, with teams made up of PIs from both institutions. The PIs on these projects, who have common interests but different strengths, create more powerful teams by working together.</p>
<p><strong>Transmitting shared values, attitudes, and beliefs to improve cybersecurity across supply chains</strong></p>
<p>The MIT and HPI cybersecurity researchers say that most ransomware attacks aren’t reported. Smaller companies hit with ransomware attacks just shut down, because they can’t afford the payment to retrieve their data. This makes it difficult to know just how many attacks and data breaches occur. “As more data and processes move online and into the cloud, it becomes even more important to focus on securing supply chains,” Kwong says. “Investing in cybersecurity allows information to be exchanged freely while keeping data safe. Without it, any progress towards sustainability is stalled.”</p>
<p>One of the first large data breaches in the United States to be widely publicized provides a clear example of how an SME cybersecurity can leave a multinational corporation vulnerable to attack. In 2013, hackers entered the Target Corporation’s own network by obtaining the credentials of a small vendor in its supply chain: a Pennsylvania HVAC company. Through that breach, thieves were able to install malware that stole the financial and personal information of 110 million Target customers, which they sold to card shops on the black market.</p>
<p>To prevent such attacks, SME vendors in a large corporation’s supply chain are required to agree to follow certain security measures, but the SMEs usually don’t have the expertise or training to make good on these cybersecurity promises, leaving their own systems, and therefore any connected to them, vulnerable to attack.</p>
<p>“Right now, organizations are connected economically, but not aligned in terms of organizational culture, values, beliefs, and practices around cybersecurity,” explains Kwong. “Basically, the big companies are realizing the smaller ones are not able to implement all the cybersecurity requirements. We have seen some larger companies address this by reducing requirements or making the process shorter. However, this doesn’t mean companies are more secure; it just lowers the bar for the smaller suppliers to clear it.”</p>
<p>Pearlson emphasizes the importance of board members and senior management taking responsibility for cybersecurity in order to change the culture at SMEs, rather than pushing that down to a single department, IT office, or in some cases, one IT employee.</p>
<p>The research team is using case studies based on interviews, field studies, focus groups, and direct observation of people in their natural work environments to learn how companies engage with vendors, and the specific ways cybersecurity is implemented, or not, in everyday operations. The goal is to create a shared culture around cybersecurity that can be adopted correctly by all vendors in a supply chain.</p>
<p>This approach is in line with the goals of the Charter of Trust Initiative, a partnership of large, multinational corporations formed to establish a better means of implementing cybersecurity in the supply chain network. The HPI-MIT team worked with companies from the Charter of Trust and others last year to understand the impacts of cybersecurity regulation on SME participation in supply chains and develop a conceptual framework to implement changes for stabilizing supply chains.</p>
<p>Cybersecurity is a prerequisite needed to achieve any of the United Nations’ SDGs, explains Kwong. Without secure supply chains, access to key resources and institutions can be abruptly cut off. This could include food, clean water and sanitation, renewable energy, financial systems, health care, education, and resilient infrastructure. Securing supply chains helps enable progress on all SDGs, and the HPI-MIT project specifically supports SMEs, which are a pillar of the U.S. and European economies.</p>
<p><strong>Personalizing product designs while minimizing material waste</strong></p>
<p>In a vastly different Designing for Sustainability joint research project that employs AI with engineering, “Personalizing Product Designs While Minimizing Material Waste” will use AI design software to lay out multiple parts of a pattern on a sheet of plywood, acrylic, or other material, so that they can be laser cut to create new products in real time without wasting material.</p>
<p>Stefanie Mueller, the TIBCO Career Development Associate Professor in the MIT Department of Electrical Engineering and Computer Science and a member of the Computer Science and Artificial Intelligence Laboratory, and Patrick Baudisch, a professor of computer science and chair of the Human Computer Interaction Lab at HPI, are co-PIs on the project. The two have worked together for years; Baudisch was Mueller’s PhD research advisor at HPI.</p>
<p>Baudisch’s lab developed an online design teaching system called <a href="https://kyub.com/">Kyub</a> that lets students design 3D objects in pieces that are laser cut from sheets of wood and assembled to become chairs, speaker boxes, radio-controlled aircraft, or even functional musical instruments. For instance, each leg of a chair would consist of four identical vertical pieces attached at the edges to create a hollow-centered column, four of which will provide stability to the chair, even though the material is very lightweight.</p>
<p>“By designing and constructing such furniture, students learn not only design, but also structural engineering,” Baudisch says. “Similarly, by designing and constructing musical instruments, they learn about structural engineering, as well as resonance, types of musical tuning, etc.”</p>
<p>Mueller was at HPI when Baudisch developed the Kyub software, allowing her to observe “how they were developing and making all the design decisions,” she says. “They built a really neat piece for people to quickly design these types of 3D objects.” However, using Kyub for material-efficient design is not fast; in order to fabricate a model, the software has to break the 3D models down into 2D parts and lay these out on sheets of material. This takes time, and makes it difficult to see the impact of design decisions on material use in real-time.</p>
<p>Mueller’s lab at MIT developed software based on a layout algorithm that uses AI to lay out pieces on sheets of material in real time. This allows AI to explore multiple potential layouts while the user is still editing, and thus provide ongoing feedback. “As the user develops their design, <a href="https://hcie.csail.mit.edu/research/fabricaide/fabricaide.html">Fabricaide</a> decides good placements of parts onto the user&#8217;s available materials, provides warnings if the user does not have enough material for a design, and makes suggestions for how the user can resolve insufficient material cases,” according to the project website.</p>
<p>The joint MIT-HPI project integrates Mueller’s AI software with Baudisch’s Kyub software and adds machine learning to train the AI to offer better design suggestions that save material while adhering to the user’s design intent.</p>
<p>“The project is all about minimizing the waste on these materials sheets,” Mueller says. She already envisions the next step in this AI design process: determining how to integrate the laws of physics into the AI’s knowledge base to ensure the structural integrity and stability of objects it designs.</p>
<p><strong>AI-powered startup design for the Anthropocene: Providing guidance for novel enterprises</strong></p>
<p>Through her work with the teams of <a href="https://designx.mit.edu/">MITdesignX</a> and its international programs, Svafa Grönfeldt, faculty director of MITdesignX and professor of the practice in MIT MAD, has helped scores of people in startup companies use the tools and methods of design to ensure that the solution a startup proposes actually fits the problem it seeks to solve. This is often called the problem-solution fit.</p>
<p>Grönfeldt and MIT postdoc Norhan Bayomi are now extending this work to incorporate AI into the process, in collaboration with MIT Professor John Fernández and graduate student Tyler Kim. The HPI team includes Professor Gerard de Melo; HPI School of Entrepreneurship Director Frank Pawlitschek; and doctoral student Michael Mansfeld.</p>
<p>“The startup ecosystem is characterized by uncertainty and volatility compounded by growing uncertainties in climate and planetary systems,” Grönfeldt says. “Therefore, there is an urgent need for a robust model that can objectively predict startup success and guide design for the Anthropocene.”</p>
<p>While startup-success forecasting is gaining popularity, it currently focuses on aiding venture capitalists in selecting companies to fund, rather than guiding the startups in the design of their products, services and business plans.</p>
<p>“The coupling of climate and environmental priorities with startup agendas requires deeper analytics for effective enterprise design,” Grönfeldt says. The project aims to explore whether AI-augmented decision-support systems can enhance startup-success forecasting.</p>
<p>“We&#8217;re trying to develop a machine learning approach that will give a forecasting of probability of success based on a number of parameters, including the type of business model proposed, how the team came together, the team members’ backgrounds and skill sets, the market and industry sector they&#8217;re working in and the problem-solution fit,” says Bayomi, who works with Fernández in the MIT Environmental Solutions Initiative. The two are co-founders of the startup Lamarr.AI, which employs robotics and AI to help reduce the carbon dioxide impact of the built environment.</p>
<p>The team is studying “how company founders make decisions across four key areas, starting from the opportunity recognition, how they are selecting the team members, how they are selecting the business model, identifying the most automatic strategy, all the way through the product market fit to gain an understanding of the key governing parameters in each of these areas,” explains Bayomi.</p>
<p>The team is “also developing a large language model that will guide the selection of the business model by using large datasets from different companies in Germany and the U.S. We train the model based on the specific industry sector, such as a technology solution or a data solution, to find what would be the most suitable business model that would increase the success probability of a company,” she says.</p>
<p>The project falls under several of the United Nations’ Sustainable Development Goals, including economic growth, innovation and infrastructure, sustainable cities and communities, and climate action.</p>
<p><strong>Furthering the goals of the HPI-MIT Joint Research Program</strong></p>
<p>These three diverse projects all advance the mission of the HPI-MIT collaboration. MIT MAD aims to use design to transform learning, catalyze innovation, and empower society by inspiring people from all disciplines to interweave design into problem-solving. HPI uses digital engineering concentrated on the development and research of user-oriented innovations for all areas of life.</p>
<p>Interdisciplinary teams with members from both institutions are encouraged to develop and submit proposals for ambitious, sustainable projects that use design strategically to generate measurable, impactful solutions to the world’s problems.</p>
</div>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Exploring frontiers of mechanical engineering</title>
		<link>https://www.sawberries.com/2024/05/03/mechanical-engineering-graduate-students-explore-frontiers-0503/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[ross]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 03 May 2024 18:01:16 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Artificial Intelligence]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Design]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Graduate, postdoctoral]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Health sciences and technology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Human-computer interaction]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Independent Activities Period]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mechanical engineering]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Nanoscience and nanotechnology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Oceanography and ocean engineering]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Profile]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[School of Engineering]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Spaceflight]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Sports analytics]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Students]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Water]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.sawberries.com/2024/05/03/mechanical-engineering-graduate-students-explore-frontiers-0503/</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[From cutting-edge robotics, design, and bioengineering to sustainable energy solutions, ocean engineering, nanotechnology, and innovative materials science, MechE students and their advisors are doing incredibly innovative work. The graduate students highlighted here represent a snapshot of the great work in progress this spring across the Department of Mechanical Engineering, and demonstrate the ways the future [&#8230;]]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<div>
<p>From cutting-edge robotics, design, and bioengineering to sustainable energy solutions, ocean engineering, nanotechnology, and innovative materials science, MechE students and their advisors are doing incredibly innovative work. The graduate students highlighted here represent a snapshot of the great work in progress this spring across the Department of Mechanical Engineering, and demonstrate the ways the future of this field is as limitless as the imaginations of its practitioners.</p>
<p><strong>Democratizing design through AI</strong></p>
<p>Lyle Regenwetter<br />Hometown: Champaign, Illinois<br />Advisor: Assistant Professor Faez Ahmed<br />Interests: Food, climbing, skiing, soccer, tennis, cooking</p>
<p>Lyle Regenwetter finds excitement in the prospect of generative AI to &#8220;democratize&#8221; design and enable inexperienced designers to tackle complex design problems. His research explores new training methods through which generative AI models can be taught to implicitly obey design constraints and synthesize higher-performing designs. Knowing that prospective designers often have an intimate knowledge of the needs of users, but may otherwise lack the technical training to create solutions, Regenwetter also develops human-AI collaborative tools that allow AI models to interact and support designers in popular CAD software and real design problems. </p>
<p><strong>Solving a whale of a problem </strong></p>
<p>Loïcka Baille<br />Hometown: L’Escale, France<br />Advisor: Daniel Zitterbart<br />Interests: Being outdoors — scuba diving, spelunking, or climbing. Sailing on the Charles River, martial arts classes, and playing volleyball</p>
<p>Loïcka Baille’s research focuses on developing remote sensing technologies to study and protect marine life. Her main project revolves around improving onboard whale detection technology to prevent vessel strikes, with a special focus on protecting North Atlantic right whales. Baille is also involved in an ongoing study of Emperor penguins. Her team visits Antarctica annually to tag penguins and gather data to enhance their understanding of penguin population dynamics and draw conclusions regarding the overall health of the ecosystem.</p>
<p><strong>Water, water anywhere</strong></p>
<p>Carlos Díaz-Marín<br />Hometown: San José, Costa Rica<br />Advisor: Professor Gang Chen | Former Advisor: Professor Evelyn Wang<br />Interests: New England hiking, biking, and dancing</p>
<p>Carlos Díaz-Marín designs and synthesizes inexpensive salt-polymer materials that can capture large amounts of humidity from the air. He aims to change the way we generate potable water from the air, even in arid conditions. In addition to water generation, these salt-polymer materials can also be used as thermal batteries, capable of storing and reusing heat. Beyond the scientific applications, Díaz-Marín is excited to continue doing research that can have big social impacts, and that finds and explains new physical phenomena. As a LatinX person, Díaz-Marín is also driven to help increase diversity in STEM.</p>
<p><strong>Scalable fabrication of nano-architected materials</strong></p>
<p>Somayajulu Dhulipala<br />Hometown: Hyderabad, India<br />Advisor: Assistant Professor Carlos Portela<br />Interests: Space exploration, taekwondo, meditation.</p>
<p>Somayajulu Dhulipala works on developing lightweight materials with tunable mechanical properties. He is currently working on methods for the scalable fabrication of nano-architected materials and predicting their mechanical properties. The ability to fine-tune the mechanical properties of specific materials brings versatility and adaptability, making these materials suitable for a wide range of applications across multiple industries. While the research applications are quite diverse, Dhulipala is passionate about making space habitable for humanity, a crucial step toward becoming a spacefaring civilization.</p>
<p><strong>Ingestible health-care devices</strong></p>
<p>Jimmy McRae<br />Hometown: Woburn, Massachusetts<br />Advisor: Associate Professor Giovani Traverso<br />Interests: Anything basketball-related: playing, watching, going to games, organizing hometown tournaments </p>
<p>Jimmy McRae aims to drastically improve diagnostic and therapeutic capabilities through noninvasive health-care technologies. His research focuses on leveraging materials, mechanics, embedded systems, and microfabrication to develop novel ingestible electronic and mechatronic devices. This ranges from ingestible electroceutical capsules that modulate hunger-regulating hormones to devices capable of continuous ultralong monitoring and remotely triggerable actuations from within the stomach. The principles that guide McRae’s work to develop devices that function in extreme environments can be applied far beyond the gastrointestinal tract, with applications for outer space, the ocean, and more.</p>
<p><strong>Freestyle BMX meets machine learning</strong></p>
<p>Eva Nates<br />Hometown: Narberth, Pennsylvania <br />Advisor: Professor Peko Hosoi<br />Interests: Rowing, running, biking, hiking, baking</p>
<p>Eva Nates is working with the Australian Cycling Team to create a tool to classify Bicycle Motocross Freestyle (BMX FS) tricks. She uses a singular value decomposition method to conduct a principal component analysis of the time-dependent point-tracking data of an athlete and their bike during a run to classify each trick. The 2024 Olympic team hopes to incorporate this tool in their training workflow, and Nates worked alongside the team at their facilities on the Gold Coast of Australia during MIT’s Independent Activities Period in January.</p>
<p><strong>Augmenting Astronauts with Wearable Limbs </strong></p>
<p>Erik Ballesteros<br />Hometown: Spring, Texas<br />Advisor: Professor Harry Asada<br />Interests: Cosplay, Star Wars, Lego bricks</p>
<p>Erik Ballesteros’s research seeks to support astronauts who are conducting planetary extravehicular activities through the use of supernumerary robotic limbs (SuperLimbs). His work is tailored toward design and control manifestation to assist astronauts with post-fall recovery, human-leader/robot-follower quadruped locomotion, and coordinated manipulation between the SuperLimbs and the astronaut to perform tasks like excavation and sample handling.</p>
<p><em>This article appeared in the Spring 2024 edition of the Department of Mechanical Engineering&#8217;s magazine, </em><a href="https://meche.mit.edu/magazine">MechE Connects</a><em>. </em></p>
</div>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Physicists arrange atoms in extremely close proximity</title>
		<link>https://www.sawberries.com/2024/05/03/physicists-arrange-atoms-extremely-close-proximity-0502/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[ross]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 03 May 2024 00:01:05 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Department of Defense (DoD)]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Light]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[nano]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Nanoscience and nanotechnology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[National Science Foundation (NSF)]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Physics]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Quantum computing]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Research]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Research Laboratory of Electronics]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[School of Science]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.sawberries.com/2024/05/03/physicists-arrange-atoms-extremely-close-proximity-0502/</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Proximity is key for many quantum phenomena, as interactions between atoms are stronger when the particles are close. In many quantum simulators, scientists arrange atoms as close together as possible to explore exotic states of matter and build new quantum materials. They typically do this by cooling the atoms to a stand-still, then using laser [&#8230;]]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<div>
<p>Proximity is key for many quantum phenomena, as interactions between atoms are stronger when the particles are close. In many quantum simulators, scientists arrange atoms as close together as possible to explore exotic states of matter and build new quantum materials.</p>
<p>They typically do this by cooling the atoms to a stand-still, then using laser light to position the particles as close as 500 nanometers apart — a limit that is set by the wavelength of light. Now, MIT physicists have developed a technique that allows them to arrange atoms in much closer proximity, down to a mere 50 nanometers. For context, a red blood cell is about 1,000 nanometers wide.</p>
<p>The physicists demonstrated the new approach in experiments with dysprosium, which is the most magnetic atom in nature. They used the new approach to manipulate two layers of dysprosium atoms, and positioned the layers precisely 50 nanometers apart. At this extreme proximity, the magnetic interactions were 1,000 times stronger than if the layers were separated by 500 nanometers.</p>
<p>What’s more, the scientists were able to measure two new effects caused by the atoms’ proximity. Their enhanced magnetic forces caused “thermalization,” or the transfer of heat from one layer to another, as well as synchronized oscillations between layers. These effects petered out as the layers were spaced farther apart.</p>
<p>“We have gone from positioning atoms from 500 nanometers to 50 nanometers apart, and there is a lot you can do with this,” says Wolfgang Ketterle, the John D. MacArthur Professor of Physics at MIT. “At 50 nanometers, the behavior of atoms is so much different that we’re really entering a new regime here.”</p>
<p>Ketterle and his colleagues say the new approach can be applied to many other atoms to study quantum phenomena. For their part, the group plans to use the technique to manipulate atoms into configurations that could generate the first purely magnetic quantum gate — a key building block for a new type of quantum computer.</p>
<p>The team has <a href="https://www.science.org/doi/10.1126/science.adh3023" target="_blank" rel="noopener">published their results today</a> in the journal <em>Science</em>. The study’s co-authors include lead author and physics graduate student Li Du, along with Pierre Barral, Michael Cantara, Julius de Hond, and Yu-Kun Lu — all members of the MIT-Harvard Center for Ultracold Atoms, the Department of Physics, and the Research Laboratory of Electronics at MIT.</p>
<p><strong>Peaks and valleys</strong></p>
<p>To manipulate and arrange atoms, physicists typically first cool a cloud of atoms to temperatures approaching absolute zero, then use a system of laser beams to corral the atoms into an optical trap.</p>
<p>Laser light is an electromagnetic wave with a specific wavelength (the distance between maxima of the electric field) and frequency. The wavelength limits the smallest pattern into which light can be shaped to typically 500 nanometers, the so-called optical resolution limit. Since atoms are attracted by laser light of certain frequencies, atoms will be positioned at the points of peak laser intensity. For this reason, existing techniques have been limited in how close they can position atomic particles, and could not be used to explore phenomena that happen at much shorter distances.</p>
<p>“Conventional techniques stop at 500 nanometers, limited not by the atoms but by the wavelength of light,” Ketterle explains. “We have found now a new trick with light where we can break through that limit.”</p>
<p>The team’s new approach, like current techniques, starts by cooling a cloud of atoms — in this case, to about 1 microkelvin, just a hair above absolute zero — at which point, the atoms come to a near-standstill. Physicists can then use lasers to move the frozen particles into desired configurations.</p>
<p>Then, Du and his collaborators worked with two laser beams, each with a different frequency, or color, and circular polarization, or direction of the laser’s electric field. When the two beams travel through a super-cooled cloud of atoms, the atoms can orient their spin in opposite directions, following either of the two lasers’ polarization. The result is that the beams produce two groups of the same atoms, only with opposite spins.</p>
<p>Each laser beam formed a standing wave, a periodic pattern of electric field intensity with a spatial period of 500 nanometers. Due to their different polarizations, each standing wave attracted and corralled one of two groups of atoms, depending on their spin. The lasers could be overlaid and tuned such that the distance between their respective peaks is as small as 50 nanometers, meaning that the atoms gravitating to each respective laser’s peaks would be separated by the same 50 nanometers.</p>
<p>But in order for this to happen, the lasers would have to be extremely stable and immune to all external noise, such as from shaking or even breathing on the experiment. The team realized they could stabilize both lasers by directing them through an optical fiber, which served to lock the light beams in place in relation to each other.</p>
<p>“The idea of sending both beams through the optical fiber meant the whole machine could shake violently, but the two laser beams stayed absolutely stable with respect to each others,” Du says.</p>
<p><strong>Magnetic forces at close range</strong></p>
<p>As a first test of their new technique, the team used atoms of dysprosium — a rare-earth metal that is one of the strongest magnetic elements in the periodic table, particularly at ultracold temperatures. However, at the scale of atoms, the element’s magnetic interactions are relatively weak at distances of even 500 nanometers. As with common refrigerator magnets, the magnetic attraction between atoms increases with proximity, and the scientists suspected that if their new technique could space dysprosium atoms as close as 50 nanometers apart, they might observe the emergence of otherwise weak interactions between the magnetic atoms.</p>
<p>“We could suddenly have magnetic interactions, which used to be almost neglible but now are really strong,” Ketterle says.</p>
<p>The team applied their technique to dysprosium, first super-cooling the atoms, then passing two lasers through to split the atoms into two spin groups, or layers. They then directed the lasers through an optical fiber to stabilize them, and found that indeed, the two layers of dysprosium atoms gravitated to their respective laser peaks, which in effect separated the layers of atoms by 50 nanometers — the closest distance that any ultracold atom experiment has been able to achieve.</p>
<p>At this extremely close proximity, the atoms’ natural magnetic interactions were significantly enhanced, and were 1,000 times stronger than if they were positioned 500 nanometers apart. The team observed that these interactions resulted in two novel quantum phenomena: collective oscillation, in which one layer’s vibrations caused the other layer to vibrate in sync; and thermalization, in which one layer transferred heat to the other, purely through magnetic fluctuations in the atoms.</p>
<p>“Until now, heat between atoms could only by exchanged when they were in the same physical space and could collide,” Du notes. “Now we have seen atomic layers, separated by vacuum, and they exchange heat via fluctuating magnetic fields.”</p>
<p>The team’s results introduce a new technique that can be used to position many types of atom in close proximity. They also show that atoms, placed close enough together, can exhibit interesting quantum phenomena, that could be harnessed to build new quantum materials, and potentially, magnetically-driven atomic systems for quantum computers.</p>
<p>“We are really bringing super-resolution methods to the field, and it will become a general tool for doing quantum simulations,” Ketterle says. “There are many variants possible, which we are working on.”</p>
<p>This research was funded, in part, by the National Science Foundation and the Department of Defense.</p>
</div>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Fostering research, careers, and community in materials science</title>
		<link>https://www.sawberries.com/2024/05/02/fostering-research-careers-community-materials-science-0501/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[ross]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 02 May 2024 07:25:30 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Abdul Latif Jameel World Education Lab (J-WEL)]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Algorithms]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Alumni/ae]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Classes and programs]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Collaboration]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Computer modeling]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Computer science and technology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Data]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Digital technology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[DMSE]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Education, teaching, academics]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Learning]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mentoring]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[MIT.nano]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[nano]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Office of Open Learning]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Online learning]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Programming]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Research]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[School of Engineering]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Special events and guest speakers]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[STEM education]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Students]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Undergraduate]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.sawberries.com/2024/05/02/fostering-research-careers-community-materials-science-0501/</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Gabrielle Wood, a junior at Howard University majoring in chemical engineering, is on a mission to improve the sustainability and life cycles of natural resources and materials. Her work in the Materials Initiative for Comprehensive Research Opportunity (MICRO) program has given her hands-on experience with many different aspects of research, including MATLAB programming, experimental design, [&#8230;]]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<div>
<p>Gabrielle Wood, a junior at Howard University majoring in chemical engineering, is on a mission to improve the sustainability and life cycles of natural resources and materials. Her work in the <a href="https://www.mse-micro.net/">Materials Initiative for Comprehensive Research Opportunity</a> (MICRO) program has given her hands-on experience with many different aspects of research, including MATLAB programming, experimental design, data analysis, figure-making, and scientific writing.</p>
<p>Wood is also one of 10 undergraduates from 10 universities around the United States to participate in the first MICRO Summit earlier this year. The internship program, developed by the MIT Department of Materials Science and Engineering (DMSE), first launched in fall 2021. Now in its third year, the program continues to grow, providing even more opportunities for non-MIT undergraduate students — including the MICRO Summit and the program’s expansion to include Northwestern University.</p>
<p>“I think one of the most valuable aspects of the MICRO program is the ability to do research long term with an experienced professor in materials science and engineering,” says Wood. “My school has limited opportunities for undergraduate research in sustainable polymers, so the MICRO program allowed me to gain valuable experience in this field, which I would not otherwise have.”</p>
<p>Like Wood, Griheydi Garcia, a senior chemistry major at Manhattan College, values the exposure to materials science, especially since she is not able to learn as much about it at her home institution.</p>
<p>“I learned a lot about crystallography and defects in materials through the MICRO curriculum, especially through videos,” says Garcia. “The research itself is very valuable, as well, because we get to apply what we’ve learned through the videos in the research we do remotely.”</p>
<p><strong>Expanding research opportunities</strong></p>
<p>From the beginning, the MICRO program was designed as a fully remote, rigorous education and mentoring program targeted toward students from underserved backgrounds interested in pursuing graduate school in materials science or related fields. Interns are matched with faculty to work on their specific research interests.</p>
<p>Jessica Sandland ’99, PhD ’05, principal lecturer in DMSE and co-founder of MICRO, says that research projects for the interns are designed to be work that they can do remotely, such as developing a machine-learning algorithm or a data analysis approach.</p>
<p>“It’s important to note that it’s not just about what the program and faculty are bringing to the student interns,” says Sandland, a member of the <a href="https://openlearning.mit.edu/mitx-digital-learning-lab">MIT Digital Learning Lab</a>, a joint program between MIT Open Learning and the Institute’s academic departments. “The students are doing real research and work, and creating things of real value. It’s very much an exchange.”</p>
<p>Cécile Chazot PhD ’22, now an assistant professor of materials science and engineering at Northwestern University, had helped to establish MICRO at MIT from the very beginning. Once at Northwestern, she quickly realized that expanding MICRO to Northwestern would offer even more research opportunities to interns than by relying on MIT alone — leveraging the university’s strong materials science and engineering department, as well as offering resources for biomaterials research through Northwestern’s medical school. The program received funding from 3M and officially launched at Northwestern in fall 2023. Approximately half of the MICRO interns are now in the program with MIT and half are with Northwestern. Wood and Garcia both participate in the program via Northwestern.</p>
<p>“By expanding to another school, we’ve been able to have interns work with a much broader range of research projects,” says Chazot. “It has become easier for us to place students with faculty and research that match their interests.”</p>
<p><strong>Building community</strong></p>
<p>The MICRO program received a Higher Education Innovation grant from the <a href="https://www.jwel.mit.edu/">Abdul Latif Jameel World Education Lab</a>, part of MIT Open Learning, to develop an in-person summit. In January 2024, interns visited MIT for three days of presentations, workshops, and campus tours — including a tour of the MIT.nano building — as well as various community-building activities.</p>
<p>“A big part of MICRO is the community,” says Chazot. “A highlight of the summit was just seeing the students come together.”</p>
<p>The summit also included panel discussions that allowed interns to gain insights and advice from graduate students and professionals. The graduate panel discussion included MIT graduate students Sam Figueroa (mechanical engineering), Isabella Caruso (DMSE), and Eliana Feygin (DMSE). The career panel was led by Chazot and included Jatin Patil PhD ’23, head of product at SiTration; Maureen Reitman ’90, ScD ’93, group vice president and principal engineer at Exponent; Lucas Caretta PhD ’19, assistant professor of engineering at Brown University; Raquel D’Oyen ’90, who holds a PhD from Northwestern University and is a senior engineer at Raytheon; and Ashley Kaiser MS ’19, PhD ’21, senior process engineer at 6K.</p>
<p>Students also had an opportunity to share their work with each other through research presentations. Their presentations covered a wide range of topics, including: developing a computer program to calculate solubility parameters for polymers used in textile manufacturing; performing a life-cycle analysis of a photonic chip and evaluating its environmental impact in comparison to a standard silicon microchip; and applying machine learning algorithms to scanning transmission electron microscopy images of CrSBr, a two-dimensional magnetic material. </p>
<p>“The summit was wonderful and the best academic experience I have had as a first-year college student,” says MICRO intern Gabriella La Cour, who is pursuing a major in chemistry and dual degree biomedical engineering at Spelman College and participates in MICRO through MIT. “I got to meet so many students who were all in grades above me … and I learned a little about how to navigate college as an upperclassman.” </p>
<p>“I actually have an extremely close friendship with one of the students, and we keep in touch regularly,” adds La Cour. “Professor Chazot gave valuable advice about applications and recommendation letters that will be useful when I apply to REUs [Research Experiences for Undergraduates] and graduate schools.”</p>
<p>Looking to the future, MICRO organizers hope to continue to grow the program’s reach.</p>
<p>“We would love to see other schools taking on this model,” says Sandland. “There are a lot of opportunities out there. The more departments, research groups, and mentors that get involved with this program, the more impact it can have.”</p>
</div>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>GitHub Unveils Copilot Workspace: A New Era in Developer Tools</title>
		<link>https://www.sawberries.com/2024/04/30/github-unveils-copilot-workspace-a-new-era-in-developer-tools/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[ross]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 30 Apr 2024 03:01:31 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[AI]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Artificial Intelligence]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Community]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Copilot Workspace]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Features]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Github]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[GitHub Copilot]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Natural Language]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[NLP]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[software]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[software development]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.sawberries.com/2024/04/30/github-unveils-copilot-workspace-a-new-era-in-developer-tools/</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[GitHub has introduced its revolutionary AI-driven developer environment, the Copilot Workspace. This new platform, aimed at transforming the process of software creation, has sent ripples through the developer community. Building upon the success of GitHub Copilot, this innovative platform promises to redefine the developer experience. Let’s delve deeper into the features of the Copilot Workspace [&#8230;]]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<div>
<p>GitHub has introduced its revolutionary AI-driven developer environment, the Copilot Workspace. This new platform, aimed at transforming the process of software creation, has sent ripples through the developer community. Building upon the success of GitHub Copilot, this innovative platform promises to redefine the developer experience. Let’s delve deeper into the features of the Copilot Workspace […]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://www.analyticsvidhya.com/blog/2024/04/github-unveils-copilot-workspace-a-new-era-in-developer-tools/">GitHub Unveils Copilot Workspace: A New Era in Developer Tools</a> appeared first on <a href="https://www.analyticsvidhya.com/">Analytics Vidhya</a>.</p>
</div>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>MIT faculty, instructors, students experiment with generative AI in teaching and learning</title>
		<link>https://www.sawberries.com/2024/04/29/mit-faculty-instructors-students-experiment-generative-ai-teaching-learning-0429/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[ross]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 29 Apr 2024 18:01:37 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Artificial Intelligence]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Classes and programs]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Education, teaching, academics]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Electrical Engineering & Computer Science (eecs)]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Faculty]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Human-computer interaction]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Innovation and Entrepreneurship (I&E)]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Internet]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[K-12 education]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Labor and jobs]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Languages]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Learning]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Machine Learning]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[MIT Schwarzman College of Computing]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[MIT Sloan School of Management]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[MITx]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Office of Open Learning]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Online learning]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[School of Engineering]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[School of Humanities Arts and Social Sciences]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[School of Science]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Special events and guest speakers]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Staff]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Students]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Technology and society]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Vice Chancellor]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.sawberries.com/2024/04/29/mit-faculty-instructors-students-experiment-generative-ai-teaching-learning-0429/</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[How can MIT’s community leverage generative AI to support learning and work on campus and beyond? At MIT’s Festival of Learning 2024, faculty and instructors, students, staff, and alumni exchanged perspectives about the digital tools and innovations they’re experimenting with in the classroom. Panelists agreed that generative AI should be used to scaffold — not [&#8230;]]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<div>
<p>How can MIT’s community leverage generative AI to support learning and work on campus and beyond?</p>
<p>At MIT’s Festival of Learning 2024, faculty and instructors, students, staff, and alumni exchanged perspectives about the digital tools and innovations they’re experimenting with in the classroom. Panelists agreed that generative AI should be used to scaffold — not replace — learning experiences.</p>
<p>This annual event, co-sponsored by MIT Open Learning and the Office of the Vice Chancellor, celebrates teaching and learning innovations. When introducing new teaching and learning technologies, panelists stressed the importance of iteration and teaching students how to develop critical thinking skills while leveraging technologies like generative AI.</p>
<p>“The Festival of Learning brings the MIT community together to explore and celebrate what we do every day in the classroom,” said Christopher Capozzola, senior associate dean for open learning. “This year&#8217;s deep dive into generative AI was reflective and practical — yet another remarkable instance of ‘mind and hand’ here at the Institute.” <strong> </strong></p>
<p><strong>Incorporating generative AI into learning experiences </strong></p>
<p>MIT faculty and instructors aren’t just willing to experiment with generative AI — some believe it’s a necessary tool to prepare students to be competitive in the workforce. “In a future state, we will know how to teach skills with generative AI, but we need to be making iterative steps to get there instead of waiting around,” said Melissa Webster, lecturer in managerial communication at MIT Sloan School of Management. </p>
<p>Some educators are revisiting their courses’ learning goals and redesigning assignments so students can achieve the desired outcomes in a world with AI. Webster, for example, previously paired written and oral assignments so students would develop ways of thinking. But, she saw an opportunity for teaching experimentation with generative AI. If students are using tools such as ChatGPT to help produce writing, Webster asked, “how do we still get the thinking part in there?”</p>
<p>One of the new assignments Webster developed asked students to generate cover letters through ChatGPT and critique the results from the perspective of future hiring managers. Beyond learning how to refine generative AI prompts to produce better outputs, Webster shared that “students are thinking more about their thinking.” Reviewing their ChatGPT-generated cover letter helped students determine what to say and how to say it, supporting their development of higher-level strategic skills like persuasion and understanding audiences.</p>
<p>Takako Aikawa, senior lecturer at the MIT Global Studies and Languages Section, redesigned a vocabulary exercise to ensure students developed a deeper understanding of the Japanese language, rather than just right or wrong answers. Students compared short sentences written by themselves and by ChatGPT and developed broader vocabulary and grammar patterns beyond the textbook. “This type of activity enhances not only their linguistic skills but stimulates their metacognitive or analytical thinking,” said Aikawa. “They have to think in Japanese for these exercises.”</p>
<p>While these panelists and other Institute faculty and instructors are redesigning their assignments, many MIT undergraduate and graduate students across different academic departments are leveraging generative AI for efficiency: creating presentations, summarizing notes, and quickly retrieving specific ideas from long documents. But this technology can also creatively personalize learning experiences. Its ability to communicate information in different ways allows students with different backgrounds and abilities to adapt course material in a way that’s specific to their particular context. </p>
<p>Generative AI, for example, can help with student-centered learning at the K-12 level. Joe Diaz, program manager and STEAM educator for MIT pK-12 at Open Learning, encouraged educators to foster learning experiences where the student can take ownership. “Take something that kids care about and they’re passionate about, and they can discern where [generative AI] might not be correct or trustworthy,” said Diaz.</p>
<p>Panelists encouraged educators to think about generative AI in ways that move beyond a course policy statement. When incorporating generative AI into assignments, the key is to be clear about learning goals and open to sharing examples of how generative AI could be used in ways that align with those goals. </p>
<p><strong>The importance of critical thinking</strong></p>
<p>Although generative AI can have positive impacts on educational experiences, users need to understand why large language models might produce incorrect or biased results. Faculty, instructors, and student panelists emphasized that it’s critical to contextualize how generative AI works. “[Instructors] try to explain what goes on in the back end and that really does help my understanding when reading the answers that I’m getting from ChatGPT or Copilot,” said Joyce Yuan, a senior in computer science. </p>
<p>Jesse Thaler, professor of physics and director of the National Science Foundation Institute for Artificial Intelligence and Fundamental Interactions, warned about trusting a probabilistic tool to give definitive answers without uncertainty bands. “The interface and the output needs to be of a form that there are these pieces that you can verify or things that you can cross-check,” Thaler said.</p>
<p>When introducing tools like calculators or generative AI, the faculty and instructors on the panel said it’s essential for students to develop critical thinking skills in those particular academic and professional contexts. Computer science courses, for example, could permit students to use ChatGPT for help with their homework if the problem sets are broad enough that generative AI tools wouldn’t capture the full answer. However, introductory students who haven’t developed the understanding of programming concepts need to be able to discern whether the information ChatGPT generated was accurate or not.</p>
<p>Ana Bell, senior lecturer of the Department of Electrical Engineering and Computer Science and <em>MITx </em>digital learning scientist, dedicated one class toward the end of the semester of Course 6.100L (Introduction to Computer Science and Programming Using Python) to teach students how to use ChatGPT for programming questions. She wanted students to understand why setting up generative AI tools with the context for programming problems, inputting as many details as possible, will help achieve the best possible results. “Even after it gives you a response back, you have to be critical about that response,” said Bell. By waiting to introduce ChatGPT until this stage, students were able to look at generative AI’s answers critically because they had spent the semester developing the skills to be able to identify whether problem sets were incorrect or might not work for every case. </p>
<p><strong>A scaffold for learning experiences</strong></p>
<p>The bottom line from the panelists during the Festival of Learning was that generative AI should provide scaffolding for engaging learning experiences where students can still achieve desired learning goals. The MIT undergraduate and graduate student panelists found it invaluable when educators set expectations for the course about when and how it’s appropriate to use AI tools. Informing students of the learning goals allows them to understand whether generative AI will help or hinder their learning. Student panelists asked for trust that they would use generative AI as a starting point, or treat it like a brainstorming session with a friend for a group project. Faculty and instructor panelists said they will continue iterating their lesson plans to best support student learning and critical thinking. </p>
<p>Panelists from both sides of the classroom discussed the importance of generative AI users being responsible for the content they produce and avoiding automation bias — trusting the technology’s response implicitly without thinking critically about why it produced that answer and whether it’s accurate. But since generative AI is built by people making design decisions, Thaler told students, “You have power to change the behavior of those tools.”</p>
</div>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Julie Shah named head of the Department of Aeronautics and Astronautics</title>
		<link>https://www.sawberries.com/2024/04/29/julie-shah-named-head-department-aeronautics-astronautics-0429/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[ross]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 29 Apr 2024 18:01:36 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Administration]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Aeronautical and astronautical engineering]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Alumni/ae]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Artificial Intelligence]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Computer Science and Artificial Intelligence Laboratory (CSAIL)]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Electrical Engineering & Computer Science (eecs)]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Faculty]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Leadership]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[MIT Schwarzman College of Computing]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Robotics]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[School of Engineering]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.sawberries.com/2024/04/29/julie-shah-named-head-department-aeronautics-astronautics-0429/</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Julie Shah ’04, SM ’06, PhD ’11, the H.N. Slater Professor in Aeronautics and Astronautics, has been named the new head of the Department of Aeronautics and Astronautics (AeroAstro), effective May 1. “Julie brings an exceptional record of visionary and interdisciplinary leadership to this role. She has made substantial technical contributions in the field of [&#8230;]]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<div>
<p>Julie Shah ’04, SM ’06, PhD ’11, the H.N. Slater Professor in Aeronautics and Astronautics, has been named the new head of the Department of Aeronautics and Astronautics (AeroAstro), effective May 1.</p>
<p>“Julie brings an exceptional record of visionary and interdisciplinary leadership to this role. She has made substantial technical contributions in the field of robotics and AI, particularly as it relates to the future of work, and has bridged important gaps in the social, ethical, and economic implications of AI and computing,” says Anantha Chandrakasan, MIT’s chief innovation and strategy officer, dean of the School of Engineering, and the Vannevar Bush Professor of Electrical Engineering and Computer Science.</p>
<p>In addition to her role as a faculty member in AeroAstro, Shah served as associate dean of Social and Ethical Responsibilities of Computing in the MIT Schwarzman College of Computing from 2019 to 2022, helping launch a coordinated curriculum that engages more than 2,000 students a year at the Institute. She currently directs the Interactive Robotics Group in MIT’s Computer Science and Artificial Intelligence Lab (CSAIL), and MIT’s Industrial Performance Center.</p>
<p>Shah and her team at the Interactive Robotics Group conduct research that aims to imagine the future of work by designing collaborative robot teammates that enhance human capability. She is expanding the use of human cognitive models for artificial intelligence and has translated her work to manufacturing assembly lines, health-care applications, transportation, and defense. In 2020, Shah co-authored the popular book “What to Expect When You’re Expecting Robots,” which explores the future of human-robot collaboration.</p>
<p>As an expert on how humans and robots interact in the workforce, Shah was named co-director of the Work of the Future Initiative, a successor group of MIT’s Task Force on the Work of the Future, alongside Ben Armstrong, executive director and research scientist at MIT’s Industrial Performance Center. In March of this year, Shah was named a co-leader of the Working Group on Generative AI and the Work of the Future, alongside Armstrong and Kate Kellogg, the David J. McGrath Jr. Professor of Management and Innovation. The group is examining how generative AI tools can contribute to higher-quality jobs and inclusive access to the latest technologies across sectors.</p>
<p>Shah’s contributions as both a researcher and educator have been recognized with many awards and honors throughout her career. She was named an associate fellow of the American Institute of Aeronautics and Astronautics (AIAA) in 2017, and in 2018 she was the recipient of the IEEE Robotics and Automation Society Academic Early Career Award. Shah was also named a Bisplinghoff Faculty Fellow, was named to <em>MIT Technology Review</em>’s TR35 List, and received an NSF Faculty Early Career Development Award. In 2013, her work on human-robot collaboration was included on <em>MIT Technology Review</em>’s list of 10 Breakthrough Technologies.</p>
<p>In January 2024, she was appointed to the first-ever AIAA Aerospace Artificial Intelligence Advisory Group, which was founded “to advance the appropriate use of AI technology particularly in aeronautics, aerospace R&amp;D, and space.” Shah currently serves as editor-in-chief of <em>Foundations and Trends in Robotics</em>, as an editorial board member of the AIAA Progress Series, and as an executive council member of the Association for the Advancement of Artificial Intelligence.</p>
<p>A dedicated educator, Shah has been recognized for her collaborative and supportive approach as a mentor. She was honored by graduate students as “Committed to Caring” (C2C) in 2019. For the past 10 years, she has served as an advocate, community steward, and mentor for students in her role as head of house of the Sidney Pacific Graduate Community.</p>
<p>Shah received her bachelor’s and master’s degrees in aeronautical and astronautical engineering, and her PhD in autonomous systems, all from MIT. After receiving her doctoral degree, she joined Boeing as a postdoc, before returning to MIT in 2011 as a faculty member.</p>
<p>Shah succeeds Professor Steven Barrett, who has led AeroAstro as both interim department head and then department head since May 2023.</p>
</div>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Exploring the history of data-driven arguments in public life</title>
		<link>https://www.sawberries.com/2024/04/28/william-deringer-explores-history-data-driven-arguments-0428/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[ross]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sun, 28 Apr 2024 12:53:46 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[economics]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Faculty]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[History of science]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Profile]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Program in STS]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[School of Humanities Arts and Social Sciences]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.sawberries.com/2024/04/28/william-deringer-explores-history-data-driven-arguments-0428/</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Political debates today may not always be exceptionally rational, but they are often infused with numbers. If people are discussing the economy or health care or climate change, sooner or later they will invoke statistics. It was not always thus. Our habit of using numbers to make political arguments has a history, and William Deringer [&#8230;]]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<div>
<p>Political debates today may not always be exceptionally rational, but they are often infused with numbers. If people are discussing the economy or health care or climate change, sooner or later they will invoke statistics.</p>
</p>
<p>It was not always thus. Our habit of using numbers to make political arguments has a history, and William Deringer is a leading historian of it. Indeed, in recent years Deringer, an associate professor in MIT’s Program in Science, Technology, and Society (STS), has carved out a distinctive niche through his scholarship showing how quantitative reasoning has become part of public life.</p>
</p>
<p>In his prize-winning 2018 book “<a href="https://news.mit.edu/2018/book-statistical-arguments-public-debate-0205" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Calculated Values</a>” (Harvard University Press), Deringer identified a time in British public life from the 1680s to the 1720s as a key moment when the practice of making numerical arguments took hold — a trend deeply connected with the rise of parliamentary power and political parties. Crucially, freedom of the press also expanded, allowing greater scope for politicians and the public to have frank discussions about the world as it was, backed by empirical evidence.</p>
</p>
<p>Deringer’s second book project, in progress and under contract to Yale University Press, digs further into a concept from the first book — the idea of financial discounting. This is a calculation to estimate what money (or other things) in the future is worth today, to assign those future objects a “present value.” Some skilled mathematicians understood discounting in medieval times; its use expanded in the 1600s; today it is very common in finance and is the subject of debate in relation to climate change, as experts try to estimate ideal spending levels on climate matters.</p>
</p>
<p>“The book is about how this particular technique came to have the power to weigh in on profound social questions,” Deringer says. “It’s basically about compound interest, and it’s at the center of the most important global question we have to confront.”</p>
</p>
<p>Numbers alone do not make a debate rational or informative; they can be false, misleading, used to entrench interests, and so on. Indeed, a key theme in Deringer’s work is that when quantitiative reasoning gains more ground, the question is why, and to whose benefit. In this sense his work aligns with the long-running and always-relevant approach of the Institute’s STS faculty, in thinking carefully about how technology and knowledge is applied to the world.</p>
</p>
<p>“The broader culture more has become attuned to STS, whether it’s conversations about AI or algorithmic fairness or climate change or energy, these are simultaneously technical and social issues,” Deringer says. “Teaching undergraduates, I’ve found the awareness of that at MIT has only increased.” For both his research and teaching, Deringer received tenure from MIT earlier this year.</p>
</p>
<p><strong>Dig in, work outward</strong></p>
</p>
<p>Deringer has been focused on these topics since he was an undergraduate at Harvard University.</p>
</p>
<p>“I found myself becoming really interested in the history of economics, the history of practical mathematics, data, statistics, and how it came to be that so much of our world is organized quantitatively,” he says.</p>
</p>
<p>Deringer wrote a college thesis about how England measured the land it was seizing from Ireland in the 1600s, and then, after graduating, went to work in the finance sector, which gave him a further chance to think about the application of quantification to modern life.</p>
</p>
<p>“That was not what I wanted to do forever, but for some of the conceptual questions I was interested in, the societal life of calculations, I found it to be a really interesting space,” Deringer says.</p>
</p>
<p>He returned to academia by pursuing his PhD in the history of science at Princeton University. There, in his first year of graduate school, in the archives, Deringer found 18th-century pamphlets about financial calculations concering the value of stock involved in the infamous episode of speculation known as the South Sea Bubble. That became part of his dissertation; skeptics of the South Sea Bubble were among the prominent early voices bringing data into public debates. It has also helped inform his second book.</p>
</p>
<p>First, though, Deringer earned his doctorate from Princeton in 2012, then spent three years as a Mellon Postdoctoral Research Fellow at Columbia University. He joined the MIT faculty in 2015. At the Institute, he finished turning his dissertation into the “Calculated Values” book — which won the 2019 Oscar Kenshur Prize for the best book from the Center for Eighteenth-Century Studies at Indiana University, and was co-winner of the 2021 Joseph J. Spengler Prize for best book from the History of Economics Society.</p>
</p>
<p>“My method as a scholar is to dig into the technical details, then work outward historically from them,” Deringer says.</p>
</p>
<p><strong>A long historical chain</strong></p>
</p>
<p>Even as Deringer was writing his first book, the idea for the second one was taking root in his mind. Those South Sea Bubble pamphets he had found while at Princeton incorporated discounting, which was intermittently present in “Calculated Values.” Deringer was intrigued by how adept 18th-century figures were at discounting.</p>
</p>
<p>“Something that I thought of as a very modern technique seemed to be really well-known by a lot of people in the 1720s,” he says.</p>
</p>
<p>At the same time, a conversation with an academic colleague in philosophy made it clear to Deringer how different conclusions about discounting had become debated in climate change policy. He soon resolved to write the “biography of a calculation” about financial discounting.</p>
</p>
<p>“I knew my next book had to be about this,” Deringer says. “I was very interested in the deep historical roots of discounting, and it has a lot of present urgency.”</p>
</p>
<p>Deringer says the book will incorporate material about the financing of English cathedrals, the heavy use of discounting in the mining industry during the Industrial Revolution, a revival of discounting in 1960s policy circles, and climate change, among other things. In each case, he is carefully looking at the interests and historical dynamics behind the use of discounting.</p>
</p>
<p>“For people who use discounting regularly, it’s like gravity: It’s very obvious that to be rational is to discount the future according to this formula,” Deringer says. “But if you look at history, what is thought of as rational is part of a very long historical chain of people applying this calculation in various ways, and over time that’s just how things are done. I’m really interested in pulling apart that idea that this is a sort of timeless rational calculation, as opposed to a product of this interesting history.”</p>
</p>
<p>Working in STS, Deringer notes, has helped encourage him to link together numerous historical time periods into one book about the numerous ways discounting has been used.</p>
</p>
<p>“I’m not sure that pursuing a book that stretches from the 17th century to the 21st century is something I would have done in other contexts,” Deringer says. He is also quick to credit his colleagues in STS and in other programs for helping create the scholarly environment in which he is thriving.</p>
</p>
<p>“I came in with a really amazing cohort of other scholars in SHASS,” Deringer notes, referring to the MIT School of Humanities, Arts, and Social Sciences. He cites others receiving tenure in the last year such as his STS colleague Robin Scheffler, historian Megan Black, and historian Caley Horan, with whom Deringer has taught graduate classes on the concept of risk in history. In all, Deringer says, the Institute has been an excellent place for him to pursue interdisciplinary work on technical thought in history.</p>
</p>
<p>“I work on very old things and very technical things,” Deringer says. “But I’ve found a wonderful welcoming at MIT from people in different fields who light up when they hear what I’m interested in.”</p>
</div>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>A musical life: Carlos Prieto ’59 in conversation and concert</title>
		<link>https://www.sawberries.com/2024/04/28/musical-life-carlos-prieto-conversation-and-concert-0426/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[ross]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sun, 28 Apr 2024 12:53:45 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Alumni/ae]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[DMSE]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[economics]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Music]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[School of Engineering]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[School of Humanities Arts and Social Sciences]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Special events and guest speakers]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.sawberries.com/2024/04/28/musical-life-carlos-prieto-conversation-and-concert-0426/</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[World-renowned cellist Carlos Prieto ’59 returned to campus for an event to perform and to discuss his new memoir, “Mi Vida Musical.” At the April 9 event in the Samberg Conference Center, Prieto spoke about his formative years at MIT and his subsequent career as a professional cellist. The talk was followed by performances of J.S. [&#8230;]]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<div>
<p>World-renowned cellist Carlos Prieto ’59 returned to campus for an event to perform and to discuss his new memoir, “Mi Vida Musical.”</p>
<p>At the April 9 event in the Samberg Conference Center, Prieto spoke about his formative years at MIT and his subsequent career as a professional cellist. The talk was <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=noO9329Er9I" target="_blank" rel="noopener">followed by performances</a> of J.S. Bach’s “Cello Suite No. 3” and Eugenio “Toussaint’s Bachriation.” Valerie Chen, a 2022 Sudler Prize winner and Emerson/Harris Fellow, also performed Phillip Glass’s “Orbit.”</p>
<p>Prieto was born in Mexico City and began studying the cello when he was 4. He graduated from MIT with BS degrees in 1959 in Course 3, then called the Metallurgical Engineering and today Materials Science and Engineering, and in Course 14 (Economics). He was the first cello and soloist of the MIT Symphony Orchestra. While at MIT, he took all available courses in Russian, which allowed him, years later, to study at Lomonosov University in Moscow.</p>
<p>After graduation from MIT, Prieto returned to Mexico, where he rose to become the head of an integrated iron and steel company.</p>
<p>“When I returned to Mexico, I was very active in my business life, but I was also very active in my music life,” he told the audience. “And at one moment, the music overcame all the other activities and I left my business activities to devote all my time to the cello and I’ve been doing this for the past 50 years.”</p>
<p>During his musical career, Prieto played all over the world and has played and recorded the world premieres of 115 compositions, most of which were written for him. He is the author of 14 books, some of which have been translated into English, Russian, and Portuguese.</p>
<p>Prieto’s honors include the Order of the Arts and Letters from France, the Order of Civil Merit from the King of Spain, and the National Prize for Arts and Sciences from the president of Mexico. In 1993 he was appointed member of the MIT Music and Theater Advisory Committee. In 2014, the School of Humanities, Arts, and Social Sciences awarded Prieto the Robert A. Muh Alumni Award.</p>
</div>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
