<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>sawberries</title>
	<atom:link href="http://localhost/sawberries/feed/?simply_static_page=4962" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>https://www.sawberries.com</link>
	<description>part of www.sawberry.com sites</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Fri, 26 Apr 2024 09:15:13 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=6.5.2</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Introduction to Natural Language Processing [Free NLP Course]</title>
		<link>https://www.sawberries.com/2024/04/26/free-course-on-nlp/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[ross]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 26 Apr 2024 09:15:13 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Beginner]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Courses]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Free NLP Course]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Introduction to Natural Language Processing]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[NLP]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[NLP Course by Analytics Vidhya]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.sawberries.com/2024/04/26/free-course-on-nlp/</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Introduction Natural Language Processing (NLP) has recently received much attention in computationally representing and analyzing human speech. Machine translation is widely used in many fields such as spam detection, data extraction, typing, medicine, question answering, and more. But what if you want to learn NLP without spending money? In this article, let’s explore a free [&#8230;]]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<div>
<p>Introduction Natural Language Processing (NLP) has recently received much attention in computationally representing and analyzing human speech. Machine translation is widely used in many fields such as spam detection, data extraction, typing, medicine, question answering, and more. But what if you want to learn NLP without spending money? In this article, let’s explore a free […]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://www.analyticsvidhya.com/blog/2024/04/free-course-on-nlp/">Introduction to Natural Language Processing [Free NLP Course]</a> appeared first on <a href="https://www.analyticsvidhya.com/">Analytics Vidhya</a>.</p>
</div>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Cohere Launches Toolkit to Expedite Generative AI Application Development</title>
		<link>https://www.sawberries.com/2024/04/25/cohere-launches-toolkit-to-expedite-generative-ai-application-development/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[ross]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 25 Apr 2024 21:02:17 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[AI]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[AI app]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[AI App Building]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[AI toolkit]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Applications]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Artificial Intelligence]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Cohere]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[deployment]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Features]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Generative AI Toolkit]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Models]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Toolkit]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[tools]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.sawberries.com/2024/04/25/cohere-launches-toolkit-to-expedite-generative-ai-application-development/</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Cohere, a leading figure in AI innovation, has unveiled a new toolkit for enterprise AI. This new toolkit is aimed at speeding up the pace of generative AI application development within the enterprise sphere. It offers developers a comprehensive set of tools and resources to expedite their projects. It further promises to streamline the intricate [&#8230;]]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<div>
<p>Cohere, a leading figure in AI innovation, has unveiled a new toolkit for enterprise AI. This new toolkit is aimed at speeding up the pace of generative AI application development within the enterprise sphere. It offers developers a comprehensive set of tools and resources to expedite their projects. It further promises to streamline the intricate […]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://www.analyticsvidhya.com/blog/2024/04/cohere-launches-toolkit-to-expedite-generative-ai-application-development/">Cohere Launches Toolkit to Expedite Generative AI Application Development</a> appeared first on <a href="https://www.analyticsvidhya.com/">Analytics Vidhya</a>.</p>
</div>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Flask Application Dockerization: Creating a Docker Image</title>
		<link>https://www.sawberries.com/2024/04/25/flask-application-dockerization-creating-a-docker-image/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[ross]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 25 Apr 2024 18:02:20 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[blockchain]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Command Line]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Container]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Database]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Docker]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Docker Containers]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Docker Hub]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dockerfile]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[EC2]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Ethereum]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Flask]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Guide]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Image]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Image Analysis]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[images]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Intermediate]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Python]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[software]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Swift]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.sawberries.com/2024/04/25/flask-application-dockerization-creating-a-docker-image/</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Introduction In the fast-paced software development industry, mastering robust application management and smooth deployment is crucial. Docker, a game-changing technology, has revolutionized software distribution, running, and bundles by separating applications from infrastructure, enabling quick software delivery. It improves portability, scalability, and workflow optimization, making it a standard component in current development practices. This article aims [&#8230;]]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<div>
<p>Introduction In the fast-paced software development industry, mastering robust application management and smooth deployment is crucial. Docker, a game-changing technology, has revolutionized software distribution, running, and bundles by separating applications from infrastructure, enabling quick software delivery. It improves portability, scalability, and workflow optimization, making it a standard component in current development practices. This article aims […]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://www.analyticsvidhya.com/blog/2024/04/flask-application-dockerization-creating-a-docker-image/">Flask Application Dockerization: Creating a Docker Image</a> appeared first on <a href="https://www.analyticsvidhya.com/">Analytics Vidhya</a>.</p>
</div>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>A new report explores the economic impact of generative AI</title>
		<link>https://www.sawberries.com/2024/04/25/a-new-report-explores-the-economic-impact-of-generative-ai/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[ross]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 25 Apr 2024 18:02:13 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[AI]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.sawberries.com/2024/04/25/a-new-report-explores-the-economic-impact-of-generative-ai/</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[A new report from inaugural Technology &#38; Society Visiting Fellow Andrew McAfee looks at the potential economic impacts of generative AI.]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<div><img decoding="async" src="https://storage.googleapis.com/gweb-uniblog-publish-prod/images/ai-hero.max-600x600.format-webp.webp">A new report from inaugural Technology &amp; Society Visiting Fellow Andrew McAfee looks at the potential economic impacts of generative AI.</div>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>10+ Deepfake Videos that You Must Watch in 2024</title>
		<link>https://www.sawberries.com/2024/04/25/deepfake-videos-that-you-must-watch/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[ross]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 25 Apr 2024 15:02:20 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Beginner]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Deep Learning]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[deepfake]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Generative AI]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Listicle]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Videos]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.sawberries.com/2024/04/25/deepfake-videos-that-you-must-watch/</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Introduction AI won’t kill us, but its footprint on society is concerning. As per AI ethics researcher Sasha Luccioni – with AI advancement, it is now high time for us to focus on the negative impacts of technology. These include AI’s current, tangible impacts, such as its environmental footprint. However, the most pressing concern is [&#8230;]]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<div>
<p>Introduction AI won’t kill us, but its footprint on society is concerning. As per AI ethics researcher Sasha Luccioni – with AI advancement, it is now high time for us to focus on the negative impacts of technology. These include AI’s current, tangible impacts, such as its environmental footprint. However, the most pressing concern is […]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://www.analyticsvidhya.com/blog/2024/04/deepfake-videos-that-you-must-watch/">10+ Deepfake Videos that You Must Watch in 2024</a> appeared first on <a href="https://www.analyticsvidhya.com/">Analytics Vidhya</a>.</p>
</div>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Seven from MIT elected to American Academy of Arts and Sciences for 2024</title>
		<link>https://www.sawberries.com/2024/04/25/seven-mit-elected-american-academy-arts-and-sciences-0425/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[ross]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 25 Apr 2024 14:14:54 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Aeronautical and astronautical engineering]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Awards, honors and fellowships]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Chemistry]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[economics]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Faculty]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mathematics]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Media Lab]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Physics]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[School of Architecture and Planning]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[School of Humanities Arts and Social Sciences]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[School of Science]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.sawberries.com/2024/04/25/seven-mit-elected-american-academy-arts-and-sciences-0425/</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Eight MIT faculty members are among the 250 leaders from academia, the arts, industry, public policy, and research elected to the American Academy of Arts and Sciences, the academy announced April 24. One of the nation’s most prestigious honorary societies, the academy is also a leading center for independent policy research. Members contribute to academy [&#8230;]]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<div>
<p>Eight MIT faculty members are among the 250 leaders from academia, the arts, industry, public policy, and research elected to the American Academy of Arts and Sciences, the academy announced April 24.</p>
</p>
<p>One of the nation’s most prestigious honorary societies, the academy is also a leading center for independent policy research. Members contribute to academy publications, as well as studies of science and technology policy, energy and global security, social policy and American institutions, the humanities and culture, and education.</p>
</p>
<p>Those elected from MIT in 2024 are:</p>
</p>
<ul>
<li>Edward F. Crawley, professor of aeronautics and astronautics, post-tenure;</li>
<li>Nathaniel Hendren, professor of economics;</li>
<li>Mei Hong, David A. Leighty Professor of Chemistry;</li>
<li>Tod Machover, Muriel R. Cooper Professor of Interactive Media Design;</li>
<li>Anna Mikusheva, professor of economics;</li>
<li>Elchanan Mossel, professor of mathematics; and</li>
<li>Xiao-Gang Wen, Cecil and Ida Green Professor of Physics.</li>
</ul>
<p>“We honor these artists, scholars, scientists, and leaders in the public, non-profit, and private sectors for their accomplishments and for the curiosity, creativity, and courage required to reach new heights,” says David Oxtoby, president of the academy. “We invite these exceptional individuals to join in the academy’s work to address serious challenges and advance the common good.”</p>
</p>
<p>Since its founding in 1780, the academy has elected leading thinkers from each generation, including George Washington and Benjamin Franklin in the 18th century, Maria Mitchell and Daniel Webster in the 19th century, and Toni Morrison and Albert Einstein in the 20th century. The current membership includes more than 250 Nobel and Pulitzer Prize winners.</p>
</div>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Bringing an investigator’s eye to complex social challenges</title>
		<link>https://www.sawberries.com/2024/04/25/bringing-investigators-eye-complex-social-challenges-anna-russo-0424/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[ross]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 25 Apr 2024 14:14:53 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Agriculture]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Climate change]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[economics]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Government]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Graduate, postdoctoral]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Health care]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mentoring]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Policy]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Profile]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[School of Humanities Arts and Social Sciences]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Social justice]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Students]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.sawberries.com/2024/04/25/bringing-investigators-eye-complex-social-challenges-anna-russo-0424/</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Anna Russo likes puzzles. They require patience, organization, and a view of the big picture. She brings an investigator’s eye to big institutional and societal challenges whose solutions can have wide-ranging, long-term impacts. Russo’s path to MIT began with questions. She didn’t have the whole picture yet. “I had no idea what I wanted to [&#8230;]]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<div>
<p>Anna Russo likes puzzles. They require patience, organization, and a view of the big picture. She brings an investigator’s eye to big institutional and societal challenges whose solutions can have wide-ranging, long-term impacts.</p>
<p>Russo’s path to MIT began with questions. She didn’t have the whole picture yet. “I had no idea what I wanted to do with my life,” says Russo, who is completing her PhD in economics in 2024. “I was good at math and science and thought I wanted to be a doctor.”</p>
<p>While completing her undergraduate studies at Yale University, where she double majored in economics and applied math, Russo discovered a passion for problem-solving, where she could apply an analytical lens to answering the kinds of thorny questions whose solutions could improve policy. “Empirical research is fun and exciting,” Russo says.</p>
<p>After Yale, Russo considered what to do next. She worked as a full-time research assistant with MIT economist <a href="https://economics.mit.edu/people/faculty/amy-finkelstein">Amy Finkelstein</a>. Russo’s work with Finkelstein led her toward identifying, studying, and developing answers to complex questions. </p>
<p>“My research combines ideas from two fields of economic inquiry — public finance and industrial organization — and applies them to questions about the design of environmental and health care policy,” Russo says. “I like the way economists think analytically about social problems.”</p>
<p><strong>Narrowing her focus</strong></p>
<p>Studying with and being advised by renowned economists as both an undergraduate and a doctoral student helped Russo narrow her research focus, fitting more pieces into the puzzle. “What drew me to MIT was its investment in its graduate students,” Russo says.</p>
<p>Economic research meant digging into policy questions, identifying market failures, and proposing solutions. Doctoral study allowed Russo to assemble data to rigorously follow each line of inquiry.</p>
<p>“Doctoral study means you get to write about something you’re really interested in,” Russo notes. This led her to study policy responses to climate change adaptation and mitigation. </p>
<p>“In my first year, I worked on a project exploring the notion that floodplain regulation design doesn’t do a good job of incentivizing the right level of development in flood-prone areas,” she says. “How can economists help governments convince people to act in society’s best interest?”</p>
<p>It’s important to understand institutional details, Russo adds, which can help investigators identify and implement solutions. </p>
<p>“Feedback, advice, and support from faculty were crucial as I grew as a researcher at MIT,” she says. Beyond her two main MIT advisors, Finkelstein and economist <a href="https://economics.mit.edu/people/faculty/nikhil-agarwal">Nikhil Agarwal</a> — educators she describes as “phenomenal, dedicated advisors and mentors” — Russo interacted regularly with faculty across the department. </p>
<p>Russo later discovered another challenge she hoped to solve: inefficiencies in conservation and carbon offset programs. She set her sights on the United States Department of Agriculture’s <a href="https://www.fsa.usda.gov/programs-and-services/conservation-programs/conservation-reserve-program/index">Conservation Reserve Program</a> because she believes it and programs like it can be improved. </p>
<p>The CRP is a land conservation plan administered by USDA’s Farm Service Agency. In exchange for a yearly rental payment, farmers enrolled in the program agree to remove environmentally sensitive land from agricultural production and plant species that will improve environmental health and quality.</p>
<p>“I think we can tweak the program’s design to improve cost-effectiveness,” Russo says. “There’s a trove of data available.” The data include information like auction participants’ bids in response to well-specified auction rules, which Russo links to satellite data measuring land use outcomes. Understanding how landowners bid in CRP auctions can help identify and improve the program’s function. </p>
<p>“We may be able to improve targeting and achieve more cost-effective conservation by adjusting the CRP’s scoring system,” Russo argues. Opportunities may exist to scale the incremental changes under study for other conservation programs and carbon offset markets more generally.  </p>
<p>Economics, Russo believes, can help us conceptualize problems and recommend effective alternative solutions.</p>
<p><strong>The next puzzle</strong></p>
<p>Russo wants to find her next challenge while continuing her research. She plans to continue her work as a junior fellow at the Harvard Society of Fellows, after which she’ll join the Harvard Department of Economics as an assistant professor. Russo also plans to continue helping other budding economists since she believes in the importance of supporting other students.   </p>
<p>Russo’s advisors are some of her biggest supporters. </p>
<p>Finklestein emphasizes Russo’s curiosity, enthusiasm, and energy as key drivers in her success. “Her genuine curiosity and interest in getting to the bottom of a problem with the data — with an econometric analysis, with a modeling issue — is the best antidote for [the stress that can be associated with research],” Finklestein says. “It&#8217;s a key ingredient in her ability to produce important and credible work.”</p>
<p>“She&#8217;s also incredibly generous with her time and advice,” Finklestein continues, “whether it&#8217;s helping an undergraduate research assistant with her senior thesis, or helping an advisor such as myself navigate a data access process she&#8217;s previously been through.”</p>
<p>“Instead of an advisor-advisee relationship, working with her on a thesis felt more like a collaboration between equals,” Agarwal adds. “[She] has the maturity and smarts to produce pathbreaking research.</p>
<p>“Doctoral study is an opportunity for students to find their paths collaboratively,” Russo says. “If I can help someone else solve a small piece of their puzzle, that’s a huge positive. Research is a series of many, many small steps forward.” </p>
<p>Identifying important causes for further investigation and study will always be important to Russo. “I also want to dig into some other market that’s not working well and figure out how to make it better,” she says. “Right now I’m really excited about understanding California wildfire mitigation.” </p>
<p>Puzzles are made to be solved, after all.</p>
</div>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Meet Malar, India’s First Autonomous AI Professor</title>
		<link>https://www.sawberries.com/2024/04/25/meet-malar-teacher-indias-first-autonomous-ai-professor/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[ross]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 25 Apr 2024 12:13:48 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[AI]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[AI in India]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[AI professor]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Anna University]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Artificial Intelligence]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Chennai]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Education]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[HaiVE]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[india]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Interviews]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Malar Teacher]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Startups]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Technology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Whatsapp]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.sawberries.com/2024/04/25/meet-malar-teacher-indias-first-autonomous-ai-professor/</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Two months after Kerala got its first AI teacher, Chennai researchers have developed the country’s first AI Professor! “Malar Teacher,” as she is named, is said to be the world’s first autonomous AI university professor. Malar is fully trained on the complete engineering syllabus of Anna University, ushering in a new era of teaching. This [&#8230;]]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<div>
<p>Two months after Kerala got its first AI teacher, Chennai researchers have developed the country’s first AI Professor! “Malar Teacher,” as she is named, is said to be the world’s first autonomous AI university professor. Malar is fully trained on the complete engineering syllabus of Anna University, ushering in a new era of teaching. This […]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://www.analyticsvidhya.com/blog/2024/04/meet-malar-teacher-indias-first-autonomous-ai-professor/">Meet Malar, India’s First Autonomous AI Professor</a> appeared first on <a href="https://www.analyticsvidhya.com/">Analytics Vidhya</a>.</p>
</div>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>GhostFaceNets: Efficient Face Recognition on Edge Devices</title>
		<link>https://www.sawberries.com/2024/04/25/ghostfacenets-efficient-face-recognition-on-edge-devices/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[ross]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 25 Apr 2024 12:13:48 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Advanced]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Applications]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[architecture]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[blogathon]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Classification]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[convolution]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Deep Learning]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[efficiency]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[face recognition]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Guide]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[IOT]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Layer]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Machine Learning]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Models]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[modules]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[recognition]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.sawberries.com/2024/04/25/ghostfacenets-efficient-face-recognition-on-edge-devices/</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Introduction GhostFaceNets is a revolutionary facial recognition technology that uses affordable operations without compromising accuracy. Inspired by attention-based models, it revolutionizes facial recognition technology. This blog post explores GhostFaceNets through captivating visuals and insightful illustrations, aiming to educate, motivate, and spark creativity. The journey is not just a blog post, but a unique exploration of [&#8230;]]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<div>
<p>Introduction GhostFaceNets is a revolutionary facial recognition technology that uses affordable operations without compromising accuracy. Inspired by attention-based models, it revolutionizes facial recognition technology. This blog post explores GhostFaceNets through captivating visuals and insightful illustrations, aiming to educate, motivate, and spark creativity. The journey is not just a blog post, but a unique exploration of […]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://www.analyticsvidhya.com/blog/2024/04/ghostfacenets-efficient-face-recognition-on-edge-devices/">GhostFaceNets: Efficient Face Recognition on Edge Devices</a> appeared first on <a href="https://www.analyticsvidhya.com/">Analytics Vidhya</a>.</p>
</div>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Convert Blurry Videos to HD with Adobe’s New AI</title>
		<link>https://www.sawberries.com/2024/04/25/adobe-videogigagan-elevates-video-quality-using-ai/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[ross]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 25 Apr 2024 12:13:47 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[adobe]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[AI]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[AI video editing]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Artificial Intelligence]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[challenges]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Features]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[GANs]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Generative AI]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Technology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[video]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[VideoGigaGAN]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Videos]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.sawberries.com/2024/04/25/adobe-videogigagan-elevates-video-quality-using-ai/</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Adobe’s latest innovation in AI technology, VideoGigaGAN, promises to revolutionize video upscaling by enhancing resolution without compromising on quality. With its new approach, Adobe aims to address the longstanding challenges of blurry videos. It presents a solution that offers remarkable results in converting blurry videos into HD. Let’s find out more about its features and [&#8230;]]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<div>
<p>Adobe’s latest innovation in AI technology, VideoGigaGAN, promises to revolutionize video upscaling by enhancing resolution without compromising on quality. With its new approach, Adobe aims to address the longstanding challenges of blurry videos. It presents a solution that offers remarkable results in converting blurry videos into HD. Let’s find out more about its features and […]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://www.analyticsvidhya.com/blog/2024/04/adobe-videogigagan-elevates-video-quality-using-ai/">Convert Blurry Videos to HD with Adobe’s New AI</a> appeared first on <a href="https://www.analyticsvidhya.com/">Analytics Vidhya</a>.</p>
</div>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
