<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Faculty &#8211; sawberries</title>
	<atom:link href="http://localhost/sawberries/category/nano/faculty/feed/?simply_static_page=144393" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>https://www.sawberries.com</link>
	<description>www.sawberry.com site</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Mon, 29 Apr 2024 18:01:37 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=6.5.2</generator>

<image>
	<url>https://www.sawberries.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/04/cropped-DALL·E-2024-04-26-12.21.04-A-512x512-favicon-design-that-incorporates-a-playful-twist-on-the-concept-of-a-strawberry-symbolizing-connections-between-people.-The-strawberry-shou-32x32.webp</url>
	<title>Faculty &#8211; sawberries</title>
	<link>https://www.sawberries.com</link>
	<width>32</width>
	<height>32</height>
</image> 
	<item>
		<title>MIT faculty, instructors, students experiment with generative AI in teaching and learning</title>
		<link>https://www.sawberries.com/2024/04/29/mit-faculty-instructors-students-experiment-generative-ai-teaching-learning-0429/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[ross]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 29 Apr 2024 18:01:37 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Artificial Intelligence]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Classes and programs]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Education, teaching, academics]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Electrical Engineering & Computer Science (eecs)]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Faculty]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Human-computer interaction]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Innovation and Entrepreneurship (I&E)]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Internet]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[K-12 education]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Labor and jobs]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Languages]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Learning]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Machine Learning]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[MIT Schwarzman College of Computing]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[MIT Sloan School of Management]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[MITx]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Office of Open Learning]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Online learning]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[School of Engineering]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[School of Humanities Arts and Social Sciences]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[School of Science]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Special events and guest speakers]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Staff]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Students]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Technology and society]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Vice Chancellor]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.sawberries.com/2024/04/29/mit-faculty-instructors-students-experiment-generative-ai-teaching-learning-0429/</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[How can MIT’s community leverage generative AI to support learning and work on campus and beyond? At MIT’s Festival of Learning 2024, faculty and instructors, students, staff, and alumni exchanged perspectives about the digital tools and innovations they’re experimenting with in the classroom. Panelists agreed that generative AI should be used to scaffold — not [&#8230;]]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<div>
<p>How can MIT’s community leverage generative AI to support learning and work on campus and beyond?</p>
<p>At MIT’s Festival of Learning 2024, faculty and instructors, students, staff, and alumni exchanged perspectives about the digital tools and innovations they’re experimenting with in the classroom. Panelists agreed that generative AI should be used to scaffold — not replace — learning experiences.</p>
<p>This annual event, co-sponsored by MIT Open Learning and the Office of the Vice Chancellor, celebrates teaching and learning innovations. When introducing new teaching and learning technologies, panelists stressed the importance of iteration and teaching students how to develop critical thinking skills while leveraging technologies like generative AI.</p>
<p>“The Festival of Learning brings the MIT community together to explore and celebrate what we do every day in the classroom,” said Christopher Capozzola, senior associate dean for open learning. “This year&#8217;s deep dive into generative AI was reflective and practical — yet another remarkable instance of ‘mind and hand’ here at the Institute.” <strong> </strong></p>
<p><strong>Incorporating generative AI into learning experiences </strong></p>
<p>MIT faculty and instructors aren’t just willing to experiment with generative AI — some believe it’s a necessary tool to prepare students to be competitive in the workforce. “In a future state, we will know how to teach skills with generative AI, but we need to be making iterative steps to get there instead of waiting around,” said Melissa Webster, lecturer in managerial communication at MIT Sloan School of Management. </p>
<p>Some educators are revisiting their courses’ learning goals and redesigning assignments so students can achieve the desired outcomes in a world with AI. Webster, for example, previously paired written and oral assignments so students would develop ways of thinking. But, she saw an opportunity for teaching experimentation with generative AI. If students are using tools such as ChatGPT to help produce writing, Webster asked, “how do we still get the thinking part in there?”</p>
<p>One of the new assignments Webster developed asked students to generate cover letters through ChatGPT and critique the results from the perspective of future hiring managers. Beyond learning how to refine generative AI prompts to produce better outputs, Webster shared that “students are thinking more about their thinking.” Reviewing their ChatGPT-generated cover letter helped students determine what to say and how to say it, supporting their development of higher-level strategic skills like persuasion and understanding audiences.</p>
<p>Takako Aikawa, senior lecturer at the MIT Global Studies and Languages Section, redesigned a vocabulary exercise to ensure students developed a deeper understanding of the Japanese language, rather than just right or wrong answers. Students compared short sentences written by themselves and by ChatGPT and developed broader vocabulary and grammar patterns beyond the textbook. “This type of activity enhances not only their linguistic skills but stimulates their metacognitive or analytical thinking,” said Aikawa. “They have to think in Japanese for these exercises.”</p>
<p>While these panelists and other Institute faculty and instructors are redesigning their assignments, many MIT undergraduate and graduate students across different academic departments are leveraging generative AI for efficiency: creating presentations, summarizing notes, and quickly retrieving specific ideas from long documents. But this technology can also creatively personalize learning experiences. Its ability to communicate information in different ways allows students with different backgrounds and abilities to adapt course material in a way that’s specific to their particular context. </p>
<p>Generative AI, for example, can help with student-centered learning at the K-12 level. Joe Diaz, program manager and STEAM educator for MIT pK-12 at Open Learning, encouraged educators to foster learning experiences where the student can take ownership. “Take something that kids care about and they’re passionate about, and they can discern where [generative AI] might not be correct or trustworthy,” said Diaz.</p>
<p>Panelists encouraged educators to think about generative AI in ways that move beyond a course policy statement. When incorporating generative AI into assignments, the key is to be clear about learning goals and open to sharing examples of how generative AI could be used in ways that align with those goals. </p>
<p><strong>The importance of critical thinking</strong></p>
<p>Although generative AI can have positive impacts on educational experiences, users need to understand why large language models might produce incorrect or biased results. Faculty, instructors, and student panelists emphasized that it’s critical to contextualize how generative AI works. “[Instructors] try to explain what goes on in the back end and that really does help my understanding when reading the answers that I’m getting from ChatGPT or Copilot,” said Joyce Yuan, a senior in computer science. </p>
<p>Jesse Thaler, professor of physics and director of the National Science Foundation Institute for Artificial Intelligence and Fundamental Interactions, warned about trusting a probabilistic tool to give definitive answers without uncertainty bands. “The interface and the output needs to be of a form that there are these pieces that you can verify or things that you can cross-check,” Thaler said.</p>
<p>When introducing tools like calculators or generative AI, the faculty and instructors on the panel said it’s essential for students to develop critical thinking skills in those particular academic and professional contexts. Computer science courses, for example, could permit students to use ChatGPT for help with their homework if the problem sets are broad enough that generative AI tools wouldn’t capture the full answer. However, introductory students who haven’t developed the understanding of programming concepts need to be able to discern whether the information ChatGPT generated was accurate or not.</p>
<p>Ana Bell, senior lecturer of the Department of Electrical Engineering and Computer Science and <em>MITx </em>digital learning scientist, dedicated one class toward the end of the semester of Course 6.100L (Introduction to Computer Science and Programming Using Python) to teach students how to use ChatGPT for programming questions. She wanted students to understand why setting up generative AI tools with the context for programming problems, inputting as many details as possible, will help achieve the best possible results. “Even after it gives you a response back, you have to be critical about that response,” said Bell. By waiting to introduce ChatGPT until this stage, students were able to look at generative AI’s answers critically because they had spent the semester developing the skills to be able to identify whether problem sets were incorrect or might not work for every case. </p>
<p><strong>A scaffold for learning experiences</strong></p>
<p>The bottom line from the panelists during the Festival of Learning was that generative AI should provide scaffolding for engaging learning experiences where students can still achieve desired learning goals. The MIT undergraduate and graduate student panelists found it invaluable when educators set expectations for the course about when and how it’s appropriate to use AI tools. Informing students of the learning goals allows them to understand whether generative AI will help or hinder their learning. Student panelists asked for trust that they would use generative AI as a starting point, or treat it like a brainstorming session with a friend for a group project. Faculty and instructor panelists said they will continue iterating their lesson plans to best support student learning and critical thinking. </p>
<p>Panelists from both sides of the classroom discussed the importance of generative AI users being responsible for the content they produce and avoiding automation bias — trusting the technology’s response implicitly without thinking critically about why it produced that answer and whether it’s accurate. But since generative AI is built by people making design decisions, Thaler told students, “You have power to change the behavior of those tools.”</p>
</div>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Julie Shah named head of the Department of Aeronautics and Astronautics</title>
		<link>https://www.sawberries.com/2024/04/29/julie-shah-named-head-department-aeronautics-astronautics-0429/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[ross]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 29 Apr 2024 18:01:36 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Administration]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Aeronautical and astronautical engineering]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Alumni/ae]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Artificial Intelligence]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Computer Science and Artificial Intelligence Laboratory (CSAIL)]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Electrical Engineering & Computer Science (eecs)]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Faculty]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Leadership]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[MIT Schwarzman College of Computing]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Robotics]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[School of Engineering]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.sawberries.com/2024/04/29/julie-shah-named-head-department-aeronautics-astronautics-0429/</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Julie Shah ’04, SM ’06, PhD ’11, the H.N. Slater Professor in Aeronautics and Astronautics, has been named the new head of the Department of Aeronautics and Astronautics (AeroAstro), effective May 1. “Julie brings an exceptional record of visionary and interdisciplinary leadership to this role. She has made substantial technical contributions in the field of [&#8230;]]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<div>
<p>Julie Shah ’04, SM ’06, PhD ’11, the H.N. Slater Professor in Aeronautics and Astronautics, has been named the new head of the Department of Aeronautics and Astronautics (AeroAstro), effective May 1.</p>
<p>“Julie brings an exceptional record of visionary and interdisciplinary leadership to this role. She has made substantial technical contributions in the field of robotics and AI, particularly as it relates to the future of work, and has bridged important gaps in the social, ethical, and economic implications of AI and computing,” says Anantha Chandrakasan, MIT’s chief innovation and strategy officer, dean of the School of Engineering, and the Vannevar Bush Professor of Electrical Engineering and Computer Science.</p>
<p>In addition to her role as a faculty member in AeroAstro, Shah served as associate dean of Social and Ethical Responsibilities of Computing in the MIT Schwarzman College of Computing from 2019 to 2022, helping launch a coordinated curriculum that engages more than 2,000 students a year at the Institute. She currently directs the Interactive Robotics Group in MIT’s Computer Science and Artificial Intelligence Lab (CSAIL), and MIT’s Industrial Performance Center.</p>
<p>Shah and her team at the Interactive Robotics Group conduct research that aims to imagine the future of work by designing collaborative robot teammates that enhance human capability. She is expanding the use of human cognitive models for artificial intelligence and has translated her work to manufacturing assembly lines, health-care applications, transportation, and defense. In 2020, Shah co-authored the popular book “What to Expect When You’re Expecting Robots,” which explores the future of human-robot collaboration.</p>
<p>As an expert on how humans and robots interact in the workforce, Shah was named co-director of the Work of the Future Initiative, a successor group of MIT’s Task Force on the Work of the Future, alongside Ben Armstrong, executive director and research scientist at MIT’s Industrial Performance Center. In March of this year, Shah was named a co-leader of the Working Group on Generative AI and the Work of the Future, alongside Armstrong and Kate Kellogg, the David J. McGrath Jr. Professor of Management and Innovation. The group is examining how generative AI tools can contribute to higher-quality jobs and inclusive access to the latest technologies across sectors.</p>
<p>Shah’s contributions as both a researcher and educator have been recognized with many awards and honors throughout her career. She was named an associate fellow of the American Institute of Aeronautics and Astronautics (AIAA) in 2017, and in 2018 she was the recipient of the IEEE Robotics and Automation Society Academic Early Career Award. Shah was also named a Bisplinghoff Faculty Fellow, was named to <em>MIT Technology Review</em>’s TR35 List, and received an NSF Faculty Early Career Development Award. In 2013, her work on human-robot collaboration was included on <em>MIT Technology Review</em>’s list of 10 Breakthrough Technologies.</p>
<p>In January 2024, she was appointed to the first-ever AIAA Aerospace Artificial Intelligence Advisory Group, which was founded “to advance the appropriate use of AI technology particularly in aeronautics, aerospace R&amp;D, and space.” Shah currently serves as editor-in-chief of <em>Foundations and Trends in Robotics</em>, as an editorial board member of the AIAA Progress Series, and as an executive council member of the Association for the Advancement of Artificial Intelligence.</p>
<p>A dedicated educator, Shah has been recognized for her collaborative and supportive approach as a mentor. She was honored by graduate students as “Committed to Caring” (C2C) in 2019. For the past 10 years, she has served as an advocate, community steward, and mentor for students in her role as head of house of the Sidney Pacific Graduate Community.</p>
<p>Shah received her bachelor’s and master’s degrees in aeronautical and astronautical engineering, and her PhD in autonomous systems, all from MIT. After receiving her doctoral degree, she joined Boeing as a postdoc, before returning to MIT in 2011 as a faculty member.</p>
<p>Shah succeeds Professor Steven Barrett, who has led AeroAstro as both interim department head and then department head since May 2023.</p>
</div>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Exploring the history of data-driven arguments in public life</title>
		<link>https://www.sawberries.com/2024/04/28/william-deringer-explores-history-data-driven-arguments-0428/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[ross]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sun, 28 Apr 2024 12:53:46 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[economics]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Faculty]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[History of science]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Profile]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Program in STS]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[School of Humanities Arts and Social Sciences]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.sawberries.com/2024/04/28/william-deringer-explores-history-data-driven-arguments-0428/</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Political debates today may not always be exceptionally rational, but they are often infused with numbers. If people are discussing the economy or health care or climate change, sooner or later they will invoke statistics. It was not always thus. Our habit of using numbers to make political arguments has a history, and William Deringer [&#8230;]]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<div>
<p>Political debates today may not always be exceptionally rational, but they are often infused with numbers. If people are discussing the economy or health care or climate change, sooner or later they will invoke statistics.</p>
</p>
<p>It was not always thus. Our habit of using numbers to make political arguments has a history, and William Deringer is a leading historian of it. Indeed, in recent years Deringer, an associate professor in MIT’s Program in Science, Technology, and Society (STS), has carved out a distinctive niche through his scholarship showing how quantitative reasoning has become part of public life.</p>
</p>
<p>In his prize-winning 2018 book “<a href="https://news.mit.edu/2018/book-statistical-arguments-public-debate-0205" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Calculated Values</a>” (Harvard University Press), Deringer identified a time in British public life from the 1680s to the 1720s as a key moment when the practice of making numerical arguments took hold — a trend deeply connected with the rise of parliamentary power and political parties. Crucially, freedom of the press also expanded, allowing greater scope for politicians and the public to have frank discussions about the world as it was, backed by empirical evidence.</p>
</p>
<p>Deringer’s second book project, in progress and under contract to Yale University Press, digs further into a concept from the first book — the idea of financial discounting. This is a calculation to estimate what money (or other things) in the future is worth today, to assign those future objects a “present value.” Some skilled mathematicians understood discounting in medieval times; its use expanded in the 1600s; today it is very common in finance and is the subject of debate in relation to climate change, as experts try to estimate ideal spending levels on climate matters.</p>
</p>
<p>“The book is about how this particular technique came to have the power to weigh in on profound social questions,” Deringer says. “It’s basically about compound interest, and it’s at the center of the most important global question we have to confront.”</p>
</p>
<p>Numbers alone do not make a debate rational or informative; they can be false, misleading, used to entrench interests, and so on. Indeed, a key theme in Deringer’s work is that when quantitiative reasoning gains more ground, the question is why, and to whose benefit. In this sense his work aligns with the long-running and always-relevant approach of the Institute’s STS faculty, in thinking carefully about how technology and knowledge is applied to the world.</p>
</p>
<p>“The broader culture more has become attuned to STS, whether it’s conversations about AI or algorithmic fairness or climate change or energy, these are simultaneously technical and social issues,” Deringer says. “Teaching undergraduates, I’ve found the awareness of that at MIT has only increased.” For both his research and teaching, Deringer received tenure from MIT earlier this year.</p>
</p>
<p><strong>Dig in, work outward</strong></p>
</p>
<p>Deringer has been focused on these topics since he was an undergraduate at Harvard University.</p>
</p>
<p>“I found myself becoming really interested in the history of economics, the history of practical mathematics, data, statistics, and how it came to be that so much of our world is organized quantitatively,” he says.</p>
</p>
<p>Deringer wrote a college thesis about how England measured the land it was seizing from Ireland in the 1600s, and then, after graduating, went to work in the finance sector, which gave him a further chance to think about the application of quantification to modern life.</p>
</p>
<p>“That was not what I wanted to do forever, but for some of the conceptual questions I was interested in, the societal life of calculations, I found it to be a really interesting space,” Deringer says.</p>
</p>
<p>He returned to academia by pursuing his PhD in the history of science at Princeton University. There, in his first year of graduate school, in the archives, Deringer found 18th-century pamphlets about financial calculations concering the value of stock involved in the infamous episode of speculation known as the South Sea Bubble. That became part of his dissertation; skeptics of the South Sea Bubble were among the prominent early voices bringing data into public debates. It has also helped inform his second book.</p>
</p>
<p>First, though, Deringer earned his doctorate from Princeton in 2012, then spent three years as a Mellon Postdoctoral Research Fellow at Columbia University. He joined the MIT faculty in 2015. At the Institute, he finished turning his dissertation into the “Calculated Values” book — which won the 2019 Oscar Kenshur Prize for the best book from the Center for Eighteenth-Century Studies at Indiana University, and was co-winner of the 2021 Joseph J. Spengler Prize for best book from the History of Economics Society.</p>
</p>
<p>“My method as a scholar is to dig into the technical details, then work outward historically from them,” Deringer says.</p>
</p>
<p><strong>A long historical chain</strong></p>
</p>
<p>Even as Deringer was writing his first book, the idea for the second one was taking root in his mind. Those South Sea Bubble pamphets he had found while at Princeton incorporated discounting, which was intermittently present in “Calculated Values.” Deringer was intrigued by how adept 18th-century figures were at discounting.</p>
</p>
<p>“Something that I thought of as a very modern technique seemed to be really well-known by a lot of people in the 1720s,” he says.</p>
</p>
<p>At the same time, a conversation with an academic colleague in philosophy made it clear to Deringer how different conclusions about discounting had become debated in climate change policy. He soon resolved to write the “biography of a calculation” about financial discounting.</p>
</p>
<p>“I knew my next book had to be about this,” Deringer says. “I was very interested in the deep historical roots of discounting, and it has a lot of present urgency.”</p>
</p>
<p>Deringer says the book will incorporate material about the financing of English cathedrals, the heavy use of discounting in the mining industry during the Industrial Revolution, a revival of discounting in 1960s policy circles, and climate change, among other things. In each case, he is carefully looking at the interests and historical dynamics behind the use of discounting.</p>
</p>
<p>“For people who use discounting regularly, it’s like gravity: It’s very obvious that to be rational is to discount the future according to this formula,” Deringer says. “But if you look at history, what is thought of as rational is part of a very long historical chain of people applying this calculation in various ways, and over time that’s just how things are done. I’m really interested in pulling apart that idea that this is a sort of timeless rational calculation, as opposed to a product of this interesting history.”</p>
</p>
<p>Working in STS, Deringer notes, has helped encourage him to link together numerous historical time periods into one book about the numerous ways discounting has been used.</p>
</p>
<p>“I’m not sure that pursuing a book that stretches from the 17th century to the 21st century is something I would have done in other contexts,” Deringer says. He is also quick to credit his colleagues in STS and in other programs for helping create the scholarly environment in which he is thriving.</p>
</p>
<p>“I came in with a really amazing cohort of other scholars in SHASS,” Deringer notes, referring to the MIT School of Humanities, Arts, and Social Sciences. He cites others receiving tenure in the last year such as his STS colleague Robin Scheffler, historian Megan Black, and historian Caley Horan, with whom Deringer has taught graduate classes on the concept of risk in history. In all, Deringer says, the Institute has been an excellent place for him to pursue interdisciplinary work on technical thought in history.</p>
</p>
<p>“I work on very old things and very technical things,” Deringer says. “But I’ve found a wonderful welcoming at MIT from people in different fields who light up when they hear what I’m interested in.”</p>
</div>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Seven from MIT elected to American Academy of Arts and Sciences for 2024</title>
		<link>https://www.sawberries.com/2024/04/25/seven-mit-elected-american-academy-arts-and-sciences-0425/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[ross]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 25 Apr 2024 14:14:54 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Aeronautical and astronautical engineering]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Awards, honors and fellowships]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Chemistry]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[economics]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Faculty]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mathematics]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Media Lab]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Physics]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[School of Architecture and Planning]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[School of Humanities Arts and Social Sciences]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[School of Science]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.sawberries.com/2024/04/25/seven-mit-elected-american-academy-arts-and-sciences-0425/</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Eight MIT faculty members are among the 250 leaders from academia, the arts, industry, public policy, and research elected to the American Academy of Arts and Sciences, the academy announced April 24. One of the nation’s most prestigious honorary societies, the academy is also a leading center for independent policy research. Members contribute to academy [&#8230;]]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<div>
<p>Eight MIT faculty members are among the 250 leaders from academia, the arts, industry, public policy, and research elected to the American Academy of Arts and Sciences, the academy announced April 24.</p>
</p>
<p>One of the nation’s most prestigious honorary societies, the academy is also a leading center for independent policy research. Members contribute to academy publications, as well as studies of science and technology policy, energy and global security, social policy and American institutions, the humanities and culture, and education.</p>
</p>
<p>Those elected from MIT in 2024 are:</p>
</p>
<ul>
<li>Edward F. Crawley, professor of aeronautics and astronautics, post-tenure;</li>
<li>Nathaniel Hendren, professor of economics;</li>
<li>Mei Hong, David A. Leighty Professor of Chemistry;</li>
<li>Tod Machover, Muriel R. Cooper Professor of Interactive Media Design;</li>
<li>Anna Mikusheva, professor of economics;</li>
<li>Elchanan Mossel, professor of mathematics; and</li>
<li>Xiao-Gang Wen, Cecil and Ida Green Professor of Physics.</li>
</ul>
<p>“We honor these artists, scholars, scientists, and leaders in the public, non-profit, and private sectors for their accomplishments and for the curiosity, creativity, and courage required to reach new heights,” says David Oxtoby, president of the academy. “We invite these exceptional individuals to join in the academy’s work to address serious challenges and advance the common good.”</p>
</p>
<p>Since its founding in 1780, the academy has elected leading thinkers from each generation, including George Washington and Benjamin Franklin in the 18th century, Maria Mitchell and Daniel Webster in the 19th century, and Toni Morrison and Albert Einstein in the 20th century. The current membership includes more than 250 Nobel and Pulitzer Prize winners.</p>
</div>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Tackling cancer at the nanoscale</title>
		<link>https://www.sawberries.com/2024/04/25/killian-lecture-speaker-paula-hammond-nanoparticles-0410/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[ross]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 25 Apr 2024 12:13:36 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Alumni/ae]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Awards, honors and fellowships]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Cancer]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Chemical engineering]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Community]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Faculty]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Koch Institute]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[nano]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Nanoscience and nanotechnology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[School of Engineering]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.sawberries.com/2024/04/25/killian-lecture-speaker-paula-hammond-nanoparticles-0410/</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[When Paula Hammond first arrived on MIT’s campus as a first-year student in the early 1980s, she wasn’t sure if she belonged. In fact, as she told an MIT audience yesterday, she felt like “an imposter.” However, that feeling didn’t last long, as Hammond began to find support among her fellow students and MIT’s faculty. [&#8230;]]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<div>
<p>When Paula Hammond first arrived on MIT’s campus as a first-year student in the early 1980s, she wasn’t sure if she belonged. In fact, as she told an MIT audience yesterday, she felt like “an imposter.”</p>
<p>However, that feeling didn’t last long, as Hammond began to find support among her fellow students and MIT’s faculty. “Community was really important for me, to feel that I belonged, to feel that I had a place here, and I found people who were willing to embrace me and support me,” she said.</p>
<p>Hammond, a world-renowned chemical engineer who has spent most of her academic career at MIT, made her remarks during the 2023-24 James R. Killian Jr. Faculty Achievement Award lecture.</p>
<p>Established in 1971 to honor MIT’s 10th president, James Killian, the Killian Award recognizes extraordinary professional achievements by an MIT faculty member. Hammond was chosen for this year’s award “not only for her tremendous professional achievements and contributions, but also for her genuine warmth and humanity, her thoughtfulness and effective leadership, and her empathy and ethics,” according to the award citation.</p>
<p>“Professor Hammond is a pioneer in nanotechnology research. With a program that extends from basic science to translational research in medicine and energy, she has introduced new approaches for the design and development of complex drug delivery systems for cancer treatment and noninvasive imaging,” said Mary Fuller, chair of MIT’s faculty and a professor of literature, who presented the award. “As her colleagues, we are delighted to celebrate her career today.”</p>
<p>In January, Hammond began serving as MIT’s vice provost for faculty. Before that, she chaired the Department of Chemical Engineering for eight years, and she was named an Institute Professor in 2021.</p>
<p><strong>A versatile technique</strong></p>
<p>Hammond, who grew up in Detroit, credits her parents with instilling a love of science. Her father was one of very few Black PhDs in biochemistry at the time, while her mother earned a master’s degree in nursing from Howard University and founded the nursing school at Wayne County Community College. “That provided a huge amount of opportunity for women in the area of Detroit, including women of color,” Hammond noted.</p>
<p>After earning her bachelor’s degree from MIT in 1984, Hammond worked as an engineer before returning to the Institute as a graduate student, earning her PhD in 1993. After a two-year postdoc at Harvard University, she returned to join the MIT faculty in 1995.</p>
<p>At the heart of Hammond’s research is a technique she developed to create thin films that can essentially “shrink-wrap” nanoparticles. By tuning the chemical composition of these films, the particles can be customized to deliver drugs or nucleic acids and to target specific cells in the body, including cancer cells.</p>
<p>To make these films, Hammond begins by layering positively charged polymers onto a negatively charged surface. Then, more layers can be added, alternating positively and negatively charged polymers. Each of these layers may contain drugs or other useful molecules, such as DNA or RNA. Some of these films contain hundreds of layers, others just one, making them useful for a wide range of applications.</p>
<p>“What’s nice about the layer-by-layer process is I can choose a group of degradable polymers that are nicely biocompatible, and I can alternate them with our drug materials. This means that I can build up thin film layers that contain different drugs at different points within the film,” Hammond said. “Then, when the film degrades, it can release those drugs in reverse order. This is enabling us to create complex, multidrug films, using a simple water-based technique.”</p>
<p>Hammond described how these layer-by-layer films can be used to promote bone growth, in an application that could help people born with congenital bone defects or people who experience traumatic injuries.</p>
<p>For that use, her lab has created films with layers of two proteins. One of these, BMP-2, is a protein that interacts with adult stem cells and induces them to differentiate into bone cells, generating new bone. The second is a growth factor called VEGF, which stimulates the growth of new blood vessels that help bone to regenerate. These layers are applied to a very thin tissue scaffold that can be implanted at the injury site.</p>
<p>Hammond and her students designed the coating so that once implanted, it would release VEGF early, over a week or so, and continue releasing BMP-2 for up to 40 days. In a study of mice, they found that this tissue scaffold stimulated the growth of <a href="https://news.mit.edu/2014/bone-repair-treat-injuries-0818" target="_blank" rel="noopener">new bone</a> that was nearly indistinguishable from natural bone.</p>
<p><strong>Targeting cancer</strong></p>
<p>As a member of MIT’s Koch Institute for Integrative Cancer Research, Hammond has also developed layer-by-layer coatings that can improve the performance of nanoparticles used for cancer drug delivery, such as liposomes or nanoparticles made from a polymer called PLGA.</p>
<p>“We have a broad range of drug carriers that we can wrap this way. I think of them like a gobstopper, where there are all those different layers of candy and they dissolve one at a time,” Hammond said.</p>
<p>Using this approach, Hammond has created particles that can deliver a one-two punch to cancer cells. First, the particles release a dose of a nucleic acid such as short interfering RNA (siRNA), which can turn off a cancerous gene, or microRNA, which can activate tumor suppressor genes. Then, the particles release a chemotherapy drug such as cisplatin, to which the cells are now more vulnerable.</p>
<p>The particles also include a negatively charged outer “stealth layer” that protects them from being broken down in the bloodstream before they can reach their targets. This outer layer can also be modified to help the particles get taken up by cancer cells, by incorporating molecules that bind to proteins that are abundant on tumor cells.</p>
<p>In more recent work, Hammond has begun developing nanoparticles that can target ovarian cancer and help prevent recurrence of the disease after chemotherapy. In about 70 percent of ovarian cancer patients, the first round of treatment is highly effective, but tumors recur in about 85 percent of those cases, and these new tumors are usually highly drug resistant.</p>
<p>By altering the type of coating applied to drug-delivering nanoparticles, Hammond has found that the particles can be designed to either get inside tumor cells or stick to their surfaces. Using particles that stick to the cells, she has designed a treatment that could help to jumpstart a patient’s immune response to any recurrent tumor cells.</p>
<p>“With ovarian cancer, very few immune cells exist in that space, and because they don’t have a lot of immune cells present, it’s very difficult to rev up an immune response,” she said. “However, if we can deliver a molecule to neighboring cells, those few that are present, and get them revved up, then we might be able to do something.”</p>
<p>To that end, she designed nanoparticles that deliver IL-12, a cytokine that stimulates nearby T cells to spring into action and begin attacking tumor cells. In a study of mice, she found that this treatment induced a long-term memory T-cell response that prevented recurrence of ovarian cancer.</p>
<p>Hammond closed her lecture by describing the impact that the Institute has had on her throughout her career.</p>
<p>“It’s been a transformative experience,” she said. “I really think of this place as special because it brings people together and enables us to do things together that we couldn’t do alone. And it is that support we get from our friends, our colleagues, and our students that really makes things possible.”</p>
</div>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
