<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>History of science &#8211; sawberries</title>
	<atom:link href="http://localhost/sawberries/category/economics/history-of-science/feed/?simply_static_page=1688648" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>https://www.sawberries.com</link>
	<description>www.sawberry.com site</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Thu, 16 May 2024 07:55:42 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=6.5.3</generator>

<image>
	<url>https://www.sawberries.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/04/cropped-DALL·E-2024-04-26-12.21.04-A-512x512-favicon-design-that-incorporates-a-playful-twist-on-the-concept-of-a-strawberry-symbolizing-connections-between-people.-The-strawberry-shou-32x32.webp</url>
	<title>History of science &#8211; sawberries</title>
	<link>https://www.sawberries.com</link>
	<width>32</width>
	<height>32</height>
</image> 
	<item>
		<title>The power of App Inventor: Democratizing possibilities for mobile applications</title>
		<link>https://www.sawberries.com/2024/05/16/power-of-app-inventor-democratizing-possibilities-mobile-applications-0510/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[ross]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 16 May 2024 07:55:42 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Apps]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Artificial Intelligence]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Education, teaching, academics]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Electrical Engineering & Computer Science (eecs)]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Global]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[History of MIT]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[History of science]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[K-12 education]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Media Lab]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[MIT Schwarzman College of Computing]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Online learning]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Open access]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Open source]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Programming]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[School of Architecture and Planning]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[School of Engineering]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[STEM education]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.sawberries.com/2024/05/16/power-of-app-inventor-democratizing-possibilities-mobile-applications-0510/</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[In June 2007, Apple unveiled the first iPhone. But the company made a strategic decision about iPhone software: its new App Store would be a walled garden. An iPhone user wouldn’t be able to install applications that Apple itself hadn’t vetted, at least not without breaking Apple’s terms of service. That business decision, however, left [&#8230;]]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<div>
<p>In June 2007, Apple unveiled the first iPhone. But the company made a strategic decision about iPhone software: its new App Store would be a walled garden. An iPhone user wouldn’t be able to install applications that Apple itself hadn’t vetted, at least not without breaking Apple’s terms of service.</p>
<p>That business decision, however, left educators out in the cold. They had no way to bring mobile software development — about to become part of everyday life — into the classroom. How could a young student code, futz with, and share apps if they couldn’t get it into the App Store?</p>
<p>MIT professor Hal Abelson was on sabbatical at Google at the time, when the company was deciding how to respond to Apple’s gambit to corner the mobile hardware and software market. Abelson recognized the restrictions Apple was placing on young developers; Google recognized the market need for an open-source alternative operating system — what became Android. Both saw the opportunity that became App Inventor.</p>
<p>“Google started the Android project sort of in reaction to the iPhone,” Abelson says. “And I was there, looking at what we did at MIT with education-focused software like <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Logo_(programming_language)">Logo</a> and <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Scratch_(programming_language)">Scratch</a>, and said ‘what a cool thing it would be if kids could make mobile apps also.’”</p>
<p>Google software engineer Mark Friedman volunteered to work with Abelson on what became “Young Android,” soon renamed Google App Inventor. Like Scratch, App Inventor is a block-based language, allowing programmers to visually snap together pre-made “blocks” of code rather than need to learn specialized programming syntax.</p>
<p>Friedman describes it as novel for the time, particularly for mobile development, to make it as easy as possible to build simple mobile apps. “That meant a web-based app,” he says, “where everything was online and no external tools were required, with a simple programming model, drag-and-drop user interface designing, and blocks-based visual programming.” Thus an app someone programmed in a web interface could be installed on an Android device.</p>
<p>App Inventor scratched an itch. Boosted by the explosion in smartphone adoption and the fact App Inventor is free (and eventually open source), soon more than 70,000 teachers were using it with hundreds of thousands of students, with Google providing the backend infrastructure to keep it going.</p>
<p>“I remember answering a question from my manager at Google who asked how many users I thought we&#8217;d get in the first year,” Friedman says. “I thought it would be about 15,000 — and I remember thinking that might be too optimistic. I was ultimately off by a factor of 10–20.” Friedman was quick to credit more than their choices about the app. “I think that it&#8217;s fair to say that while some of that growth was due to the quality of the tool, I don&#8217;t think you can discount the effect of it being from Google and of the effect of Hal Abelson&#8217;s reputation and network.”</p>
<p>Some early apps took App Inventor in ambitious, unexpected directions, such as “Discardious,” developed by teenage girls in Nigeria. Discardious helped business owners and individuals dispose of waste in communities where disposal was unreliable or too cumbersome.</p>
<p>But even before apps like Discardious came along, the team knew Google’s support wouldn’t be open-ended. No one wanted to cut teachers off from a tool they were thriving with, so around 2010, Google and Abelson agreed to transfer App Inventor to MIT. The transition meant major staff contributions to recreate App Inventor without Google’s proprietary software but MIT needing to work with Google to continue to provide the network resources to keep App Inventor free for the world.</p>
<p>With such a large user base, however, that left Abelson “worried the whole thing was going to collapse” without Google’s direct participation.</p>
<p>Friedman agrees. “I would have to say that I had my fears. App Inventor has a pretty complicated technical implementation, involving multiple programming languages, libraries and frameworks, and by the end of its time at Google we had a team of about 10 people working on it.”</p>
<p>Yet not only did Google provide significant funding to aid the transfer, but, Friedman says of the transfer’s ultimate success, “Hal would be in charge and he had fairly extensive knowledge of the system and, of course, had great passion for the vision and the product.”</p>
<p>MIT enterprise architect Jeffrey Schiller, who built the Institute’s computer network and became its manager in 1984, was another key part in sustaining App Inventor after its transition, helping introduce technical features fundamental to its accessibility and long-term success. He led the integration of the platform into web browsers, the addition of WiFi support rather than needing to connect phones and computers via USB, and the laying of groundwork for technical support of older phones because, as Schiller says, “many of our users cannot rush out and purchase the latest and most expensive devices.”</p>
<p>These collaborations and contributions over time resulted in App Inventor’s greatest resource: its user base. As it grew, and with support from community managers, volunteer know-how grew with it. Now, more than a decade since its launch and four years after its overdue inclusion in the Apple App Store, App Inventor recently crossed several major milestones, the most remarkable being the creation of its 100 millionth project and registration of its 20 millionth user. Young developers continue to make incredible applications, boosted now by the advantages of AI. College students created “<a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=RGiFiBSu4Ho">Brazilian XôDengue</a>” as a way for users to use phone cameras to identify mosquito larvae that may be carrying the dengue virus. High school students recently developed “<a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=dyeZAqOqco8">Calmify</a>,” a journaling app that uses AI for emotion detection. And a mother in Kuwait wanted something to help manage the often-overwhelming experience of new motherhood when returning to work, so she built the chatbot “<a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=4uEQsam7C4k">PAM (Personal Advisor to Mothers)</a>” as a non-judgmental space to talk through the challenges.</p>
<p>App Inventor’s long-term sustainability now rests with the App Inventor Foundation, created in 2022 to grow its resources and further drive its adoption. It is led by executive director Natalie Lao.</p>
<p>In <a href="https://www.appinventorfoundation.org/s/App-Inventor-Foundation-Annual-Impact-Report-2023.pdf">a letter</a> to the App Inventor community, Lao highlighted the foundation’s commitment to equitable access to educational resources, which for App Inventor required a rapid shift toward AI education — but in a way that upholds App Inventor’s core values to be “a free, open-source, easy-to-use platform” for mobile devices. “Our mission is to not only democratize access to technology,” Lao wrote, “but also foster a culture of innovation and digital literacy.”</p>
<p>Within MIT, App Inventor today falls under the umbrella of the MIT RAISE Initiative — Responsible AI for Social Empowerment and Education, run by Dean for Digital Learning Cynthia Breazeal, Professor Eric Klopfer, and Abelson. Together they are able to integrate App Inventor into ever-broader communities, events, and funding streams, leading to opportunities like this summer’s inaugural <a href="https://raise.mit.edu/events/ai-education-summit/">AI and Education Summit</a> on July 24-26. The summit will include awards for winners of a <a href="https://raise.mit.edu/events/global-ai-hackathon/">Global AI Hackathon</a>, whose roughly 180 submissions used App Inventor to create AI tools in two tracks: Climate &amp; Sustainability and Health &amp; Wellness. Tying together another of RAISE’s major projects, participants were encouraged to draw from <a href="https://dayofai.org/">Day of AI</a> curricula, including its newest courses on <a href="https://dayofai.org/new-courses-on-data-science-climate-change/">data science and climate change</a>.</p>
<p>“Over the past year, there&#8217;s been an enormous mushrooming in the possibilities for mobile apps through the integration of AI,” says Abelson. “The opportunity for App Inventor and MIT is to democratize those new possibilities for young people — and for everyone — as an enhanced source of power and creativity.”</p>
</div>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>President Sally Kornbluth and OpenAI CEO Sam Altman discuss the future of AI</title>
		<link>https://www.sawberries.com/2024/05/06/president-sally-kornbluth-openai-ceo-sam-altman-discuss-future-ai-0506/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[ross]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 06 May 2024 15:01:15 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Artificial Intelligence]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Business and management]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Careers]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Community]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Ethics]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[History of science]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Human-computer interaction]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Innovation and Entrepreneurship (I&E)]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Invention]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Labor and jobs]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Machine Learning]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[MIT Schwarzman College of Computing]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[MIT Sloan School of Management]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[President Sally Kornbluth]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[School of Architecture and Planning]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[School of Engineering]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[School of Humanities Arts and Social Sciences]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[School of Science]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Special events and guest speakers]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Sustainability]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Technology and society]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.sawberries.com/2024/05/06/president-sally-kornbluth-openai-ceo-sam-altman-discuss-future-ai-0506/</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[How is the field of artificial intelligence evolving and what does it mean for the future of work, education, and humanity? MIT President Sally Kornbluth and OpenAI CEO Sam Altman covered all that and more in a wide-ranging discussion on MIT’s campus May 2. The success of OpenAI’s ChatGPT large language models has helped spur [&#8230;]]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<div>
<p>How is the field of artificial intelligence evolving and what does it mean for the future of work, education, and humanity? MIT President Sally Kornbluth and OpenAI CEO Sam Altman covered all that and more in a wide-ranging discussion on MIT’s campus May 2.</p>
<p>The success of OpenAI’s ChatGPT large language models has helped spur a wave of investment and innovation in the field of artificial intelligence. ChatGPT-3.5 became the fastest-growing consumer software application in history after its release at the end of 2022, with hundreds of millions of people using the tool. Since then, OpenAI has also demonstrated AI-driven image-, audio-, and video-generation products and partnered with Microsoft.</p>
<p>The event, which took place in a packed Kresge Auditorium, captured the excitement of the moment around AI, with an eye toward what’s next.</p>
<p>“I think most of us remember the first time we saw ChatGPT and were like, ‘Oh my god, that is so cool!’” Kornbluth said. “Now we’re trying to figure out what the next generation of all this is going to be.”</p>
<p>For his part, Altman welcomes the high expectations around his company and the field of artificial intelligence more broadly.</p>
<p>“I think it’s awesome that for two weeks, everybody was freaking out about ChatGPT-4, and then by the third week, everyone was like, ‘Come on, where’s GPT-5?’” Altman said. “I think that says something legitimately great about human expectation and striving and why we all have to [be working to] make things better.”</p>
<p><strong>The problems with AI</strong></p>
<p>Early on in their discussion, Kornbluth and Altman discussed the many ethical dilemmas posed by AI.</p>
<p>“I think we’ve made surprisingly good progress around how to align a system around a set of values,” Altman said. “As much as people like to say ‘You can’t use these things because they’re spewing toxic waste all the time,’ GPT-4 behaves kind of the way you want it to, and we’re able to get it to follow a given set of values, not perfectly well, but better than I expected by this point.”</p>
<p>Altman also pointed out that people don’t agree on exactly how an AI system should behave in many situations, complicating efforts to create a universal code of conduct.</p>
<p>“How do we decide what values a system should have?” Altman asked. “How do we decide what a system should do? How much does society define boundaries versus trusting the user with these tools? Not everyone will use them the way we like, but that’s just kind of the case with tools. I think it’s important to give people a lot of control … but there are some things a system just shouldn’t do, and we’ll have to collectively negotiate what those are.”</p>
<p>Kornbluth agreed doing things like eradicating bias in AI systems will be difficult.</p>
<p>“It’s interesting to think about whether or not we can make models less biased than we are as human beings,” she said.</p>
<p>Kornbluth also brought up privacy concerns associated with the vast amounts of data needed to train today’s large language models. Altman said society has been grappling with those concerns since the dawn of the internet, but AI is making such considerations more complex and higher-stakes. He also sees entirely new questions raised by the prospect of powerful AI systems.</p>
<p>“How are we going to navigate the privacy versus utility versus safety tradeoffs?” Altman asked. “Where we all individually decide to set those tradeoffs, and the advantages that will be possible if someone lets the system be trained on their entire life, is a new thing for society to navigate. I don’t know what the answers will be.”</p>
<p>For both privacy and energy consumption concerns surrounding AI, Altman said he believes progress in future versions of AI models will help.</p>
<p>&#8220;What we want out of GPT-5 or 6 or whatever is for it to be the best reasoning engine possible,” Altman said. “It is true that right now, the only way we’re able to do that is by training it on tons and tons of data. In that process, it’s learning something about how to do very, very limited reasoning or cognition or whatever you want to call it. But the fact that it can memorize data, or the fact that it’s storing data at all in its parameter space, I think we&#8217;ll look back and say, ‘That was kind of a weird waste of resources.’ I assume at some point, we’ll figure out how to separate the reasoning engine from the need for tons of data or storing the data in [the model], and be able to treat them as separate things.”</p>
<p>Kornbluth also asked about how AI might lead to job displacement.</p>
<p>“One of the things that annoys me most about people who work on AI is when they stand up with a straight face and say, ‘This will never cause any job elimination. This is just an additive thing. This is just all going to be great,’” Altman said. “This is going to eliminate a lot of current jobs, and this is going to change the way that a lot of current jobs function, and this is going to create entirely new jobs. That always happens with technology.&#8221;</p>
<p><strong>The promise of AI</strong></p>
<p>Altman believes progress in AI will make grappling with all of the field’s current problems worth it.</p>
<p>“If we spent 1 percent of the world’s electricity training a powerful AI, and that AI helped us figure out how to get to non-carbon-based energy or make deep carbon capture better, that would be a massive win,” Altman said.</p>
<p>He also said the application of AI he’s most interested in is scientific discovery.</p>
<p>“I believe [scientific discovery] is the core engine of human progress and that it is the only way we drive sustainable economic growth,” Altman said. “People aren’t content with GPT-4. They want things to get better. Everyone wants life more and better and faster, and science is how we get there.”</p>
<p>Kornbluth also asked Altman for his advice for students thinking about their careers. He urged students not to limit themselves.</p>
<p>“The most important lesson to learn early on in your career is that you can kind of figure anything out, and no one has all of the answers when they start out,” Altman said. “You just sort of stumble your way through, have a fast iteration speed, and try to drift toward the most interesting problems to you, and be around the most impressive people and have this trust that you’ll successfully iterate to the right thing. &#8230; You can do more than you think, faster than you think.”</p>
<p>The advice was part of a broader message Altman had about staying optimistic and working to create a better future.</p>
<p>“The way we are teaching our young people that the world is totally screwed and that it’s hopeless to try to solve problems, that all we can do is sit in our bedrooms in the dark and think about how awful we are, is a really deeply unproductive streak,” Altman said. “I hope MIT is different than a lot of other college campuses. I assume it is. But you all need to make it part of your life mission to fight against this. Prosperity, abundance, a better life next year, a better life for our children. That is the only path forward. That is the only way to have a functioning society &#8230; and the anti-progress streak, the anti ‘people deserve a great life’ streak, is something I hope you all fight against.”</p>
</div>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Exploring the history of data-driven arguments in public life</title>
		<link>https://www.sawberries.com/2024/04/28/william-deringer-explores-history-data-driven-arguments-0428/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[ross]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sun, 28 Apr 2024 12:53:46 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[economics]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Faculty]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[History of science]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Profile]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Program in STS]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[School of Humanities Arts and Social Sciences]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.sawberries.com/2024/04/28/william-deringer-explores-history-data-driven-arguments-0428/</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Political debates today may not always be exceptionally rational, but they are often infused with numbers. If people are discussing the economy or health care or climate change, sooner or later they will invoke statistics. It was not always thus. Our habit of using numbers to make political arguments has a history, and William Deringer [&#8230;]]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<div>
<p>Political debates today may not always be exceptionally rational, but they are often infused with numbers. If people are discussing the economy or health care or climate change, sooner or later they will invoke statistics.</p>
</p>
<p>It was not always thus. Our habit of using numbers to make political arguments has a history, and William Deringer is a leading historian of it. Indeed, in recent years Deringer, an associate professor in MIT’s Program in Science, Technology, and Society (STS), has carved out a distinctive niche through his scholarship showing how quantitative reasoning has become part of public life.</p>
</p>
<p>In his prize-winning 2018 book “<a href="https://news.mit.edu/2018/book-statistical-arguments-public-debate-0205" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Calculated Values</a>” (Harvard University Press), Deringer identified a time in British public life from the 1680s to the 1720s as a key moment when the practice of making numerical arguments took hold — a trend deeply connected with the rise of parliamentary power and political parties. Crucially, freedom of the press also expanded, allowing greater scope for politicians and the public to have frank discussions about the world as it was, backed by empirical evidence.</p>
</p>
<p>Deringer’s second book project, in progress and under contract to Yale University Press, digs further into a concept from the first book — the idea of financial discounting. This is a calculation to estimate what money (or other things) in the future is worth today, to assign those future objects a “present value.” Some skilled mathematicians understood discounting in medieval times; its use expanded in the 1600s; today it is very common in finance and is the subject of debate in relation to climate change, as experts try to estimate ideal spending levels on climate matters.</p>
</p>
<p>“The book is about how this particular technique came to have the power to weigh in on profound social questions,” Deringer says. “It’s basically about compound interest, and it’s at the center of the most important global question we have to confront.”</p>
</p>
<p>Numbers alone do not make a debate rational or informative; they can be false, misleading, used to entrench interests, and so on. Indeed, a key theme in Deringer’s work is that when quantitiative reasoning gains more ground, the question is why, and to whose benefit. In this sense his work aligns with the long-running and always-relevant approach of the Institute’s STS faculty, in thinking carefully about how technology and knowledge is applied to the world.</p>
</p>
<p>“The broader culture more has become attuned to STS, whether it’s conversations about AI or algorithmic fairness or climate change or energy, these are simultaneously technical and social issues,” Deringer says. “Teaching undergraduates, I’ve found the awareness of that at MIT has only increased.” For both his research and teaching, Deringer received tenure from MIT earlier this year.</p>
</p>
<p><strong>Dig in, work outward</strong></p>
</p>
<p>Deringer has been focused on these topics since he was an undergraduate at Harvard University.</p>
</p>
<p>“I found myself becoming really interested in the history of economics, the history of practical mathematics, data, statistics, and how it came to be that so much of our world is organized quantitatively,” he says.</p>
</p>
<p>Deringer wrote a college thesis about how England measured the land it was seizing from Ireland in the 1600s, and then, after graduating, went to work in the finance sector, which gave him a further chance to think about the application of quantification to modern life.</p>
</p>
<p>“That was not what I wanted to do forever, but for some of the conceptual questions I was interested in, the societal life of calculations, I found it to be a really interesting space,” Deringer says.</p>
</p>
<p>He returned to academia by pursuing his PhD in the history of science at Princeton University. There, in his first year of graduate school, in the archives, Deringer found 18th-century pamphlets about financial calculations concering the value of stock involved in the infamous episode of speculation known as the South Sea Bubble. That became part of his dissertation; skeptics of the South Sea Bubble were among the prominent early voices bringing data into public debates. It has also helped inform his second book.</p>
</p>
<p>First, though, Deringer earned his doctorate from Princeton in 2012, then spent three years as a Mellon Postdoctoral Research Fellow at Columbia University. He joined the MIT faculty in 2015. At the Institute, he finished turning his dissertation into the “Calculated Values” book — which won the 2019 Oscar Kenshur Prize for the best book from the Center for Eighteenth-Century Studies at Indiana University, and was co-winner of the 2021 Joseph J. Spengler Prize for best book from the History of Economics Society.</p>
</p>
<p>“My method as a scholar is to dig into the technical details, then work outward historically from them,” Deringer says.</p>
</p>
<p><strong>A long historical chain</strong></p>
</p>
<p>Even as Deringer was writing his first book, the idea for the second one was taking root in his mind. Those South Sea Bubble pamphets he had found while at Princeton incorporated discounting, which was intermittently present in “Calculated Values.” Deringer was intrigued by how adept 18th-century figures were at discounting.</p>
</p>
<p>“Something that I thought of as a very modern technique seemed to be really well-known by a lot of people in the 1720s,” he says.</p>
</p>
<p>At the same time, a conversation with an academic colleague in philosophy made it clear to Deringer how different conclusions about discounting had become debated in climate change policy. He soon resolved to write the “biography of a calculation” about financial discounting.</p>
</p>
<p>“I knew my next book had to be about this,” Deringer says. “I was very interested in the deep historical roots of discounting, and it has a lot of present urgency.”</p>
</p>
<p>Deringer says the book will incorporate material about the financing of English cathedrals, the heavy use of discounting in the mining industry during the Industrial Revolution, a revival of discounting in 1960s policy circles, and climate change, among other things. In each case, he is carefully looking at the interests and historical dynamics behind the use of discounting.</p>
</p>
<p>“For people who use discounting regularly, it’s like gravity: It’s very obvious that to be rational is to discount the future according to this formula,” Deringer says. “But if you look at history, what is thought of as rational is part of a very long historical chain of people applying this calculation in various ways, and over time that’s just how things are done. I’m really interested in pulling apart that idea that this is a sort of timeless rational calculation, as opposed to a product of this interesting history.”</p>
</p>
<p>Working in STS, Deringer notes, has helped encourage him to link together numerous historical time periods into one book about the numerous ways discounting has been used.</p>
</p>
<p>“I’m not sure that pursuing a book that stretches from the 17th century to the 21st century is something I would have done in other contexts,” Deringer says. He is also quick to credit his colleagues in STS and in other programs for helping create the scholarly environment in which he is thriving.</p>
</p>
<p>“I came in with a really amazing cohort of other scholars in SHASS,” Deringer notes, referring to the MIT School of Humanities, Arts, and Social Sciences. He cites others receiving tenure in the last year such as his STS colleague Robin Scheffler, historian Megan Black, and historian Caley Horan, with whom Deringer has taught graduate classes on the concept of risk in history. In all, Deringer says, the Institute has been an excellent place for him to pursue interdisciplinary work on technical thought in history.</p>
</p>
<p>“I work on very old things and very technical things,” Deringer says. “But I’ve found a wonderful welcoming at MIT from people in different fields who light up when they hear what I’m interested in.”</p>
</div>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
